<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Murder will out, or, The King's letter justifying the Marquess of Antrim and declaring that what he did in the Irish rebellion was by direction from his royal father and mother, and for the service of the crown.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 205 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 50 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A70633</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M3095A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R41829</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12259955</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12259955</idno>
            <idno type="VID">57844</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A70633)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 57844)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ;179:14 or 1708:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Murder will out, or, The King's letter justifying the Marquess of Antrim and declaring that what he did in the Irish rebellion was by direction from his royal father and mother, and for the service of the crown.</title>
                  <author>Arlington, Henry Bennet, Earl of, 1618-1685.</author>
                  <author>Charles II, King of England, 1630-1685.</author>
                  <author>Gregory XV, Pope, 1554-1623.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>31 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Collection of letters and declarations chiefly by Charles, and a letter from Pope Gregory XV. Includes Charles's letter exonerating MacDonnell which is signed: By His Majesty's command, Henry Bennet.</note>
                  <note>This item appears at reel 179:14 and at reel 1708:1.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of originals in Huntington Library and University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  II, --  King of England, 1630-1685.</term>
               <term>Antrim, Randal MacDonnell, --  Earl of, 1609-1683.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  History --  Rebellion of 1641.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Puritan Revolution, 1642-1660.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:57844:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:57844:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>A DEFENCE OF THE PARLIAMENT of 1640. And the PEOPLE of ENGLAND, AGAINST <hi>King Charles</hi> I. And his ADHERENTS; CONTAINING A ſhort Account of ſome of the many Illegal, Arbitrary, Popiſh and Tyrannical Actions of King <hi>CHARLES</hi> I. unjuſtly called the <hi>Pious Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr</hi>; together with the following Tracts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>1. The Pope's Letter to King <hi>Charles.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. K. <hi>Charles</hi>'s Letter in Anſ. thereunto.</item>
                        <item>3. The Articles of Marriage made (in Favour of Papiſts) with <hi>France.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>4. King <hi>Charles</hi> his Commiſſion to the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebels, And</item>
                        <item>5. <hi>Philem, O Neal</hi> and <hi>Rorie Macquire</hi>'s Declaration to the <hi>Iriſh</hi> thereupon.</item>
                        <item>6. King <hi>Charles</hi> II's Letter to the Court of Claims of <hi>Ireland,</hi> in behalf of that great Rebel, the Marqueſs of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trim,</hi> to reſtore him to his Eſtate; for that the ſaid Marqueſs, had made it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, That what he acted in that Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, was done by the Expreſs Orders, and Commands of <hi>Charles</hi> I. his Father.</item>
                        <item>7. King <hi>Charles</hi> I's Warrant by Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary <hi>Nicholas,</hi> to the King's Printer, Commanding him to Print no more than 40 of thoſe Proclamations, that Proclaim'd the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebels.</item>
                        <item>8. An Abſtract of thoſe ſtrange Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of Peace, King <hi>Charles</hi> I. made with the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebels.</item>
                        <item>9. King <hi>Charles</hi> his two Letters to the Proteſtants of <hi>Rochel,</hi> wherein he aſſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them of Relief againſt the <hi>French</hi> K.</item>
                        <item>10 The Miſerable and Deplorable Remonſtrance thoſe poor Proteſtants made to him, upon his Sacrificing them to the Mercy of the <hi>French</hi> King.</item>
                        <item>11. The Earl of <hi>Angl<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ſey</hi>'s Memoran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum. Dr. <hi>Anthony Walker</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi>'s Proofs, That <hi>Eicon Baſilice</hi> was not Writ by King <hi>Charles,</hi> but by Dr. <hi>Gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Exeter.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>12. A Copy of the Kings, and <hi>Pame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia</hi>'s Prayers, taken out of <hi>Eicon Baſilice,</hi> and Sir <hi>Phillip Sydny</hi>'s <hi>Arcadia</hi> (which agree almoſt in every Word.)</item>
                        <item>13. Twenty Articles againſt that wicked Prelate <hi>Laud.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>14. To give a clear Demonſtration of this holy Martyr's Religion and Piety, ſee his Declaration for the Lawfulneſs of Sports and Paſtimes on the Lord's Day, Printed at large in this Book.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, 1698.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:57844:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:57844:2"/>
                  <head>TO THE READER.</head>
                  <p>IT is not the leaſt of Man's Unhappineſs, that he is the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Enemy of his own Intereſt, having Opportunities for his own Advantage, he lets them ſlip, and by Brutiſh In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cogitancy, rather than Natural Impotency, (as our Parents at firſt) he is ſoon cheated into his own Miſery; his preſent Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment is his chiefeſt Atchievement, and he will have his Will tho' it be his Woe. He is apt to kill his Friends, (as the <hi>Jews</hi> did Chriſt) for their Endeavours to Save him, and to Court his Enemy (as <hi>Eglon</hi> did <hi>Ehud</hi>) whoſe Deſign was to Slay him. The great Controverſy (between the Advocates for King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, and his wicked Favourites, and the Friends of the Parliament and People, that were neceſſitated to Reſiſt him, could never have been ſpun out into above 40 Years length, had the dim Eyes of dull People been clear'd up to a true diſcerning of their Friends from their Oppreſſive Foes. How apt have the Idolizers of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt been, with the Army of the <hi>Aſſyrians,</hi> to travel to <hi>Samaria</hi> inſtead of <hi>Dothan,</hi> and with the <hi>Jews</hi> to gratify <hi>Caeſar,</hi> in Crucifying their Saviour? Whereas heretofore they generally reputed for
<pb facs="tcp:57844:3"/>
Saints thoſe faithful and couragious Barons, who loſt their Lives in the Field, making a glorious War againſt Tyrants for the Common Liberty. Such as <hi>Symon de Mamfort,</hi> Earl of <hi>Lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter,</hi> againſt <hi>Henry</hi> the Third; <hi>Thomas Platagenet,</hi> Earl of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> againſt <hi>Edward</hi> the Second, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I cannot willingly aſcribe the Love of Tyranny and Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, to the Natural Diſpoſition of an <hi>Engliſh Man,</hi> but rather to two other Cauſes; the firſt is the Clergy of all Ranks, whoſe Pulpit Stuff from before 1640, till now, hath generally been the Doctrine, and perpetual Infuſion of Servility and Wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, to their Hearers, and their Lives moſt commonly the Types of Worldlineſs, with a ſlender Pattern of Vertue, Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Self-Denial, in their whole Practice. The Second is, I attribute it to the factious Inclination of moſt Mendivided from the Publick Intereſt of their Country, by ſeveral Selfiſh Ends and Humours of their Own; who may truly be call'd Sacrificers of the Common Welfare of Mankind, to their own private Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, that they might thereby attain to their Ambitious Purpoſes. <hi>Dryden</hi> (as I am inform'd) gives this true Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of theſe Sort of Men, <hi>viz. Mark thoſe which Dote on <hi>Arbitrary Power,</hi> and you'l find them either <hi>Hot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brain'd-Fools,</hi> or <hi>Needy Bankrupts.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>'Tis a wonderful and amazing thing, to find ſo great a part of Mankind fondly and fooliſhly Doting, nay, which is more Unchriſtian, with a ſort of Idolatry, Idolizing this Prince, when they are not capable of giving to the World a clear De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of one good Act he did deſignedly for the Benefit of his People: Certainly if his Virtue and Piety towards God, and his Country, had been in the leaſt conſpicuous, his mighty Adorers have been defective in their Panegerical En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comiums of him; for I muſt with the greateſt Aſſurance de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, that neither by reading the Defences of him, or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation with the greateſt of his Advocates, could I find the leaſt Cauſe to Eſteem him a Saint, or to clear him from the
<pb facs="tcp:57844:3"/>
Tyrannical Oppreſſion, nay, from the Blood and Miſery of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> ſo juſtly laid to his Charge by the Parliament of 1640, and thoſe worthy Patriots that join'd with them. Let the Advocates for Tyranny and Arbitrary Power ſay what they will to the contrary, I am confident the People of <hi>England</hi> have a great Eſteem and Value for a King that Governs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Law, and, in all his Actions, aims at his People's Good equal with his own; and if at any time they betake themſelves to Arms againſt their Prince, 'tis his, and not their Fault: Neither is it rational to believe, that the Generality of the Nobility, Gentry and Commonality of <hi>England,</hi> would, without an apparent Cauſe and Neceſſity, engage in a Bloody Civil War, and thereby run the hazard of their Lives and Fortunes: And he that ſhall conſider impartially, in a Civil or Religious Senſe, the Quality of thoſe that eſpouſed that King againſt their Native Country, will find the Parliament, and thoſe that joined with them, did infinitely exceed, in all reſpects, the Party that aſſiſted that King. For it is notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly known, that the Popiſh and Superſtitious People through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Kingdom, were united, as one Man for the King againſt the Parliament; and if we conſider them in a Civil reſpect, were not all the Pattentees, Monopolizers, Cruel Uſurping Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſors, but Lords, Knights and Gentlemen, the Pillars of the Star-Chamber, Councel-Table, High Commiſſion Court, &amp;c. were not theſe the great Abettors, and Supporters of that Bloody War, againſt the Parliament and People of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Were not his Clergy, for the generality of them, a wretched Parcel of Court Sycophants, that gave vent to thoſe Plaguy-Doctrines of Non-Reſiſtance, Abſolute and Arbitrary Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (after the Mode of <hi>France</hi>) in Loans, Free-Quarter, Ship-money, Monopolies, &amp;c. during the Oppreſſive Miniſtery of <hi>Buckingham, Stafford,</hi> and <hi>Laud,</hi> that countenanced thoſe two <hi>Court Paraſites</hi> and Ear-Wiggs, <hi>Mountague</hi> and <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waring,</hi> who poyſoned the Ears of King <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>First,</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:57844:4"/>
with ſuch infectious Doctrine that proved to be fatal to the <hi>King</hi> and Kingdoms. 'Tis true indeed, both <hi>Montague</hi> and <hi>Manwaring</hi> were doom'd and condemn'd for the ſame in open Parliament, <hi>Sentenced</hi> and <hi>Fined,</hi> and made incapable of all <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Benefices</hi> and <hi>Promotions.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But King <hi>Charles</hi> was ſo much in Love with theſe two wicked Levites, and their Doctrines, that ſoon after the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament was diſſolved, he puniſhed them with two Fat Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricks.</p>
                  <p>That the World may know for what <hi>Manwaring</hi> was thus Rewarded by the King, I ſhall produce three of his pernicious Aſſertions out of his two Sermons before the King, Printed under the Title of Religion ond Allegiance.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>That the King is not bound to obſerve the Laws concerning the</hi> Subjects Rights, <hi>but that his</hi> Will <hi>in Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing</hi> Loans <hi>and</hi> Taxes <hi>without conſent in</hi> Parliament <hi>doth oblige the</hi> Subjects <hi>Conſcience, <hi>Upon Pain of Eternal Damnation.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>That they who refuſed the</hi> Loan, <hi>did offend againſt the</hi> Law of God, <hi>and againſt the</hi> Kings Supreme Authority; <hi>and thereby became</hi> Guilty <hi>of</hi> Impiety, <hi>Diſloyalty, Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>That</hi> Authority <hi>of</hi> Parliament <hi>is not neceſſary for the raiſing of</hi> Aids <hi>and</hi> Subſidies; <hi>and Dr.</hi> Sibthorp, Vicar <hi>of</hi> Brackley, <hi>printed a Sermon, which he Preached at the Aſſizes at</hi> Northampton, <hi>and Dedicated to the</hi> King, <hi>where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he Poyſons his Country with theſe vile</hi> Poſitions.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>That it is the Prince's Duty to direct and make Laws, (his Text, by the way, was</hi> Rom. 13.7. Render therefore to all their Dues) <hi>he juſtified this by that Oppoſite Proof,</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:57844:4"/>
Eccleſ. 8.3, 4. He doth whatſoever pleaſes him.—Who may ſay unto him, what doeſt thou?</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>That</hi> all <hi>Antiquity is</hi> abſolutely for abſolute Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence <hi>to Princes,</hi> in al Civil and Temporal Things.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>That if Princes</hi> command any thing <hi>which Subjects</hi> may not perform, <hi>becauſe againſt the Laws of God, of Nature, or Impoſſible,</hi> yet they are bound to undergo the Puniſhment, <hi>without Reſiſtance, and</hi> ſo to vield a <hi>Paſſive Obedience,</hi> where they cannot Exhibit an Active One. <hi>P—g, Sh—k,</hi> and others, <hi>have largely ſince that time, obliged the World with theſe</hi> Enſlaving Doctrines.</p>
                  <p>As this King took great care to Reward ſuch Miniſters as theſe, ſo he was reſolved to make Examples of thoſe Pious and Worthy Clergy-men, that ſtood up againſt the Oppreſſions of thoſe Times; for Brevities Sake, I ſhall inſtance but two of the many that might be Named. The firſt was, that Good Man Dr. <hi>Abbot,</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> becauſe he could not in Conſcience comply with the King, who with Menaces re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired him to Licenſe that abominable Sermon of <hi>Sibthrops,</hi> (before mention'd) <hi>and thereby make that Good by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, which had been done againſt the Laws.</hi> And when the Lord <hi>Conway,</hi> Secretary of State, was ſent with a threatning Meſſage from the King to him, this good Old Man perſiſted in his Refuſal, ſaying, with the Pſalmiſt, <hi>I ſhall not be affraid of any Evil Tydings, for my heart is fixed, truſting in the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The King inſtantly <hi>Suſpended</hi> this Archbiſhop, and alſo <hi>confined him,</hi> and committed the <hi>Archiepiſcopal Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> to <hi>five Biſhops,</hi> all of the <hi>New Church of</hi> England, and <hi>Sibthorp's</hi> Patrons, <hi>viz. London, Durham, Rocheſter</hi> and <hi>Oxford,</hi> and honeſt <hi>Laud</hi> of <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Wells.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:57844:5"/>The ſecond was Dr. <hi>Williams,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> who alſo felt the heavy Oppreſſion of this <hi>Proteſtant King.</hi> In the firſt Year of his Reign, he was Lord Keeper of the <hi>Great Seal,</hi> but upon his appearing in <hi>Parliament</hi> againſt the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms great Grievance, the Duke of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> he was Diſgraced und Sequeſtred from the <hi>King's</hi> Preſence, and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil Table. In his ſecond Year, he was accuſed for ſpeaking publickly againſt the <hi>Loan,</hi> and alſo for refuſing to give way to proceedings in his Courts againſt the <hi>Puritans.</hi> The King Impriſon'd him in the <hi>Tower,</hi> but this good Biſhop, out-li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving his Impriſonment, <hi>upon the King's throwing the Gauntlet,</hi> he came to a <hi>Tryal of Skill,</hi> for the Old <hi>Engliſh</hi> Liberties, and he reſolutely ſaid, <hi>Nolumus Leges Angliae Mutari,</hi> and took Command in the <hi>Parliament's Army,</hi> and bravely aſſerted his <hi>Country's</hi> Liberties with his <hi>Sword.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If I ſhould proceed to relate how this King dealt by the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility and Gentry; both Lawyers and others that ſtood up for the Laws of the Land, and Liberties of the People, this Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical Story would ſwell to too great a Bulk for a Preface; I ſhall therefore give a ſhort Account of the matters contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the following Treatiſe, <hi>viz.</hi> that He Favoured, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected, and was Ruled by, the worſt of Men, both Clergy and Laity; <hi>Secondly,</hi> That He highly favoured Papiſts; <hi>Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> That He Govern'd by an Arbitrary Power, and raiſed Money upon his Subjects without Act of Parliament, which is directly againſt the Conſtitution of the Government of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and of a moſt dangerous Conſequence to the People of <hi>England;</hi> for when ever ſuch a Power is Eſtabliſhed in theſe Kingdoms, the People may bid a ſad farewell to all their Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity, for they would ſoon undergood the ſame Miſerable Fate, the poor People of <hi>France</hi> have done ever ſince that King vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated their <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> call'd, <hi>the Edict of</hi> Nants, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which is to be Taxed according to that Prince's Will and Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; <hi>Fourthly,</hi> That he was not that Pious Prince the mad
<pb facs="tcp:57844:5"/>
World without reaſon would repreſent him to be; of all theſe, you have too many Inſtances in the following Treatiſe, which for the ſatisſfaction of Mankind, contains not onely 26 Articles, or Charges againſt this <hi>King,</hi> but alſo the following Tracts, all of which were never Printed at large in any one Book be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>viz. The Popes Letter to King</hi> Charles <hi>I. and King</hi> Charles <hi>his Letter in Anſwer thereunto, calling the Pope <hi>Moſt Holy Father,</hi> &amp;c. The Articles of Marriage made (in Favour of Papiſts) with</hi> France. <hi>King</hi> Charle<hi>'s Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to the</hi> Iriſh <hi>Rebels, and</hi> Philem Oneles, <hi>and</hi> Rorie Macquire<hi>'s Declaration thereupon. King</hi> Charles <hi>II's Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the Court of Claims of</hi> Ireland, <hi>in behalf of that great Rebel, the Marqueſs of</hi> Antrim, <hi>to reſtore him to his Eſtate, for that the ſaid Marqueſs had made it appear, that what he acted in that Rebellion, was done by the Expreſs Orders and Commands of</hi> Charles <hi>I. His Father King</hi> Charles <hi>I's Warrant by Secretary</hi> Nicholas, <hi>to the King's Printer, Commanding him to Print no more than Forty Proclamations that Proclaimed the</hi> Iriſh <hi>Rebels. An Abſtract of thoſe Strange Articles of Peace, that King</hi> Charles <hi>the Firſt made with the</hi> Iriſh <hi>Rebells. The two Letters he writ to aſſure the</hi> Rochellers <hi>of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving them, and the miſerable and deplorable Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance thoſe poor People made to him upon his Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing them to the Mercy of the</hi> French <hi>King. The Earl of</hi> Angleſey<hi>'s Memorandum. Dr.</hi> Anthony Walker, <hi>and Mrs.</hi> Gauden<hi>'s Proofs, that</hi> Eicon Baſilice <hi>was not Writ by King</hi> Charles, <hi>but by Dr.</hi> Gauden <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Exeter. <hi>That Copy of the Kings, and</hi> Pamelia's <hi>Prayers taken out of</hi> Eicon Baſilice, <hi>and Sir</hi> Philip Sydneys Arcadia, <hi>will agree almoſt in every Word. Twenty Articles againſt that wicked Prelate <hi>Laud,</hi> and to give a clear Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this</hi> Holy Martyrs <hi>Religion and Piety. His</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration <hi>for the lawfulneſs of <hi>Sports</hi> and <hi>Paſtimes</hi> on the <hi>Lord's Day</hi> is printed in this Book at Large.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:57844:6"/>
                     <hi>To conclude,</hi> If all theſe and many more ſad matters of Fact, already in this, and other Books produced to the World, will not be of force enough to ſatisfie the generality of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, that they have been moſt notoriouſly impoſed upon, by the <hi>Clergy,</hi> and ſome of the <hi>Laity,</hi> in their <hi>Defence</hi> of <hi>King</hi> Charles <hi>I.</hi> againſt the <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>1640.</hi> and <hi>People</hi> of <hi>England.</hi> I ſhall conclude, that nothing but the <hi>coming down of an Angel from Heaven,</hi> will be able to <hi>convince</hi> them of their <hi>Error;</hi> I ſhall, therefore leave them to God, and end all with this hearty Prayer, That he would be pleaſed ſo to open their Eyes, that they might ſee what will make for the Peace and Happineſs of theſe Kingdoms, and no longer promote and keep up thoſe Unhappy Diviſions, that are yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, after above 40 Years Controverſie on this Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholly Subject.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="errata">
                  <head>ERRATA.</head>
                  <p>PAge 2. line 5. read <hi>Immerited.</hi> p. 4. l. 11. r. <hi>Gorges.</hi> p. 4. l. 15. r. <hi>Deſert</hi> f. <hi>Defect.</hi> p. 4. laſt line r. <hi>Coat.</hi> p. 5. l. 24. r. <hi>that.</hi> p. 6. l. 12. r. <hi>the King.</hi> p. 6. l. 25. r <hi>Bath.</hi> p. 9. l. 13. r. <hi>Prins.</hi> p. 10. l. 25. Dele <hi>and alſo King</hi> Charles II's <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration after his Reſtoration.</hi> p. 12. l. 23. r. <hi>Papiſts.</hi> p. 14. l. 10. r. <hi>things</hi> f. <hi>time.</hi> p. 15. l. 10 r. <hi>proportion.</hi> p. 18. l. 5. dele <hi>it.</hi> p. 18. l. 9. incert (<hi>to</hi>) after <hi>Relations.</hi> p. 21. l. 21. r. <hi>Wentworth.</hi> p. 21. l. 28. r. <hi>Suſpiria.</hi> p. 23. l. 3. r. <hi>diſmiſs.</hi> p. 27. l. 25. r. <hi>have done.</hi> p. 28. l. 27 r. <hi>Zyons.</hi> p. 37. l. 18. r. <hi>alia</hi> p. 39. l. 21. <hi>after imaginable</hi> r. <hi>to enſlave his people.</hi> p. 44. l. 25. r. <hi>Article.</hi> p. 46. l. 12. r. <hi>therein.</hi> p. 48. l. 12. r. <hi>irreconcilable.</hi> p. 50. l. 29. r. <hi>have.</hi> p. 51. l. 34. dele <hi>not.</hi> p. 54. l. 19. r. <hi>cordially</hi> f. <hi>Cardinals,</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="account">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:57844:6"/>
                  <head>ENGLANDS <hi>Black Liſt;</hi> OR, A ſhort Account of ſome of the many <hi>Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legal, Arbitrary, Popiſh</hi> and <hi>Tyrannical Actions</hi> of King <hi>Charles</hi> I. <hi>falſely</hi> and <hi>unjuſtly</hi> call'd the <hi>Pious Martyr of ever Bleſſed Memory</hi>; I ſhall not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to deſcribe them Gradually, or Annually, but as they Occur.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. HE took in the <hi>Duke of</hi> Buckingham to be one of the <hi>chief Conductors</hi> of <hi>all his Affairs,</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the ſaid <hi>Duke was impeached</hi> for a <hi>very ſuſpicious Playſter and Portion adminiſtred to King</hi> James <hi>the Firſt.</hi> See the Earl of <hi>Briſtols,</hi> and Sir <hi>Dudley Digg</hi>'s Speeches againſt him in <hi>Ruſhworth.</hi> The Duke's Mother, and many near about him, <hi>were Papiſts, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced Men popiſhly Devoted,</hi> to <hi>places of the chief C<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>mmand in the Court and Camp.</hi> Three Parliaments in the beginning of this Reign, <hi>found</hi> and <hi>declared this Duke the cauſe of all their Miſeries and Diſaſters, the Grievance of Grievances</hi>; yet King <hi>Charles</hi> would againſt all Juſtice protect him.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:57844:7"/>2. He made that <hi>wicked Biſhop Laud</hi> (who was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards deſervedly beheaded) <hi>another of his Favourites, by whoſe precious Councils poor</hi> England <hi>hath notoriouſly ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi>; to write his Life according to his Actions, would ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently darken the Luſtre of thoſe immerite and impious Encomiums given by <hi>that Notorious Jacobite Mr.</hi> Wharton. The Pious Dr. <hi>Abbatt,</hi> then Arch Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> hath in his Writings given a ſad account of him. 'Tis ſaid that <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> Sancroft <hi>had a great hand in putting forth this Book.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. His <hi>Marrying</hi> Heneretta Maria <hi>of</hi> France, a <hi>violent Papiſt,</hi> and agreeing <hi>to private Articles</hi> in <hi>favour</hi> of <hi>Papiſts, viz.</hi> That thoſe who had been Impriſoned, as well <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical as Temporal,</hi> ſhould be <hi>Releaſed:</hi> That <hi>Papiſts ſhould be no more moleſted for their Religion</hi>; by which means the <hi>Papiſts grew impudent,</hi> and <hi>Scoff'd</hi> at <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Law.</hi> Read the <hi>Articles at large in this Book.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. That received a <hi>Letter from the Pope,</hi> and <hi>writ him an Anſwer, ſaluting Antichriſt with</hi> the Title of <hi>Sanctiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me Pater, Moſt Holy Father.</hi> That <hi>Procured the Pope's Diſpenſation for his Marriage,</hi> which was ſolemnized by Proxy, <hi>according to the Ceremonies of the Romiſh Church.</hi> See the <hi>Pope's</hi> and <hi>King's Letter</hi> at large in this Book.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. That purſuant to his <hi>Private Article with</hi> France, immediately <hi>Granted a ſpecial Pardon to twenty Popiſh Prieſts for all the Offences</hi> they had Committed againſt the Laws, and Built a Chapel at <hi>Somerſet-Houſe,</hi> with Conveniencies for Fryars which were <hi>permitted</hi> to <hi>walk abroad in their Habits. <hi>Baker</hi> the Jeſuit,</hi> was one of many that was <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned</hi> after the Lords and Commons had ſent a Petition to him for advancing the <hi>True Religion,</hi> and <hi>ſuppreſſing of Popery.</hi> He made <hi>Weſton <hi>(who died a Papiſt)</hi>
                     </hi> his Lord <hi>Treaſurer,</hi> and <hi>preferred ſo many Papiſts</hi> to <hi>places</hi> of <hi>great
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:57844:7"/>
Truſt,</hi> as Lord <hi>Lieutenants, Deputy Lieutenants, Juſtices of the Peace,</hi> &amp;c. That the Commons of <hi>England, complain'd by their Petition, of</hi> near <hi>One Hundred of all Ranks</hi>; he <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain'd</hi> the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> and <hi>Temporal Courts</hi> from <hi>inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medling</hi> with <hi>Papiſts,</hi> which was little leſs then a <hi>Tollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> He not only <hi>Schreened, but Pardoned <hi>Mountague</hi>
                     </hi> his Chaplain, whom the <hi>Commons had Voted,</hi> had <hi>endeavoured to Reconcile</hi> England <hi>to</hi> Rome, <hi>and inſtanced, that</hi> he main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd theſe <hi>Poſitions. That the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>is, and ever was, a True Church; That Images might be uſed for the inſtructions of the Ignorant, and for Exortation of Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; That Saints have a Memory, and a more peculiar charge of their Friends; and that it may be admitted, that ſome Saints have a peculiar Patronage, Cuſtody, Protection and Power, as Angels alſo have over certain Perſons and Countrys by ſpecial Deputation; That impiouſly and prophanely ſcoffed at Preaching, Lectures, Bibles, and all ſhew of Religion; and though the Commons prayed, that for theſe and other matters, <hi>Mountague</hi> might be Puniſhed, and his Books Burnt, yet the King would do neither, but Pardon'd him as aforeſaid; being incenſed at the Commons proſecuting a Man after his own Heart.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6. That to the great Diſhonour of <hi>England,</hi> the Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal of the Proteſtant Religion, and the great Weakening of the Proteſtant Intereſt abroad, <hi>Did lend Eight Ships (E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quip'd with the ſubſidies given for the relief of his diſtreſſed Proteſtant Siſter, the Electreſs</hi> Palatine, <hi>and the poor oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Proteſtants of the</hi> Palatinate) <hi>to the</hi> French <hi>King, to fight againſt the miſerable Proteſtants of</hi> Rochel. Captain <hi>Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nington</hi> in the <hi>Vantguard</hi> went Admiral; the Commanders and Mariners proteſted againſt the Service, though temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with Chains of Gold, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Declaring they would ſink rather then fight againſt their own Religion. <hi>The Duke of</hi> Rohan, <hi>and the</hi> French <hi>Proteſtants, ſollicited the King not to let the Ships go again,</hi> and had good Words and Hopes:
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:57844:8"/>
Nevertheleſs, Ordered <hi>Pennington</hi> by <hi>Letter, Dated the 28th. of</hi> July, 1625. without Delay, to Conſign the <hi>Vant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard</hi> into the <hi>Hands of the Marqueſs</hi> de Effiat <hi>for the</hi> French <hi>King's Service,</hi> and to require the ſeven other Ships in his Name, to put themſelves into the Service of the <hi>French,</hi> Commanding <hi>Pennington</hi> to uſe all <hi>Force, even to ſinking in caſe of Refuſal.</hi> Hereupon <hi>Pennington</hi> put his Ship into the <hi>Abſolute Power of the</hi> French <hi>King,</hi> and Commanded the reſt to do ſo; <hi>But the honeſt Sea-men refuſed to be ſlaves to the</hi> French, <hi>and fight againſt the Proteſtant Religion, till forced by Shots: But Sir</hi> Ferdinando Gerges, <hi>to his Eternal Honour, brought away the</hi> Neptune <hi>with Deteſtation of the Action. All the</hi> Engliſh, <hi>Men and Boys, except (one Gunner who was ſlain in Charging a piece of Ordnance,</hi> according to his defect) <hi>declined the Service and quitted the Ships, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing to ſerve againſt the</hi> Rochellers. In <hi>September</hi> follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>theſe ſeven Ships were actually imployed againſt the</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chellers, almoſt to their utter ruin. <hi>The</hi> French <hi>boaſted that the</hi> Vantguard <hi>mow'd the Hereticks down like Graſs</hi>; by theſe <hi>wicked means, were theſe good People wholly loſt:</hi> They held the Town till the Year 1628. <hi>but were reduced to incredible Miſery, having lived long upon Horſe Fleſh, Hides, Leather, Doggs and Cats,</hi> &amp;c. There were but <hi>Four Thouſand leſt of Fifteen Thouſand Souls,</hi> many dyed with <hi>Famine,</hi> and they uſually <hi>carried their Coffins into the Church-yard, and there laid themſelves and Dyed.</hi> A <hi>Sad Story,</hi> that ought never to be <hi>forgotten</hi> in the <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of Our <hi>Bleſſed Martyr's Reign, (as wickedly call'd.)</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">7. That in <hi>Civil Matters, took his Peoples Goods from them againſt their Wills, and their Liberties againſt the Laws</hi>; that <hi>pluck'd</hi> up the <hi>Root</hi> of all Property; that <hi>acted</hi> almoſt <hi>like the</hi> Turks, who ſend their <hi>Janizaries,</hi> and <hi>place their Halbards at the Door,</hi> and then <hi>are Maſters of all</hi>; for in the very <hi>beginning</hi> of his <hi>Reign,</hi> he <hi>levied twelve thouſand Soldiers contrary to Law, and then</hi> required the <hi>Country</hi> to furniſh the <hi>charge of Coal</hi> and <hi>conduct Money.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:57844:8"/>8. That appointed Commiſſioners to <hi>Try, Condemn</hi> and <hi>Execute</hi> thoſe he unjuſtly call'd <hi>Delinquents</hi> by Martial <hi>Law,</hi> directly againſt the Laws of the Land, and ſome were <hi>Executed</hi> thereby.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. That ſtruct directly at the <hi>Property</hi> of the <hi>Subject's Goods,</hi> by iſſuing out Commiſſions (<hi>contrary to many Laws</hi>) for <hi>Raiſing Money by way of Loan,</hi> and the Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners were ordered to certify to the <hi>Council Board,</hi> the <hi>Names</hi> of all <hi>Refractery Perſons</hi>; particularly, he Demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>One Hundred Thouſand Pounds of the City of</hi> London, and upon their <hi>Refuſal,</hi> he threatned them, ſaying, <hi>He would frame his Councils as appartained to a King.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="10">10. That againſt all Law, required, the <hi>Londoners</hi> to ſet forth <hi>Twenty Ships Manned and Victualed for three Months,</hi> againſt which the <hi>Mayor, Aldermen</hi> and <hi>Common Council Petition,</hi> but to no purpoſe: Being anſwered, <hi>That Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Pleadings were not to be received,</hi> and that the <hi>Precedents of formers Times were Obedience, not Direction.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Deputy Lieutenants</hi> and <hi>Juſtices</hi> of the <hi>Peace</hi> of <hi>Dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſetſhire,</hi> being Commanded <hi>to ſet forth Ships,</hi> inſiſted, That the Caſe was <hi>without Preſident,</hi> for which, they were ſeverely <hi>checked,</hi> and told, that <hi>State Occaſions</hi> were not to be guided by <hi>Ordinary Preſidents.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thoſe <hi>Perſons of Quality,</hi> that refuſed to <hi>ſubſcribe</hi> to the <hi>Loan,</hi> were <hi>turned out</hi> of the <hi>Commiſſion of the Peace</hi> and <hi>Lieutenancy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sir <hi>Peter Hayman,</hi> upon his <hi>refuſal of the Loan,</hi> was <hi>commanded againſt his Will,</hi> to go upon the <hi>King's Service, beyond the Seas</hi>; others of meaner <hi>Rank,</hi> were either <hi>bound to appear</hi> before the <hi>Leiutenancy</hi> of the <hi>Tower,</hi> to be <hi>Enrold</hi> for Soldiers for <hi>Denmark,</hi> or were impreſſed to ſerve in the <hi>King's Ships.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:57844:9"/>Sir <hi>Randolph Crew,</hi> the then Learned Lord Chief Juſtice of the <hi>King's Bench,</hi> for <hi>Declaring againſt the Loan,</hi> and not giving Judgment, that the King might Impriſon, <hi>du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Pleaſure, was turned out,</hi> and Sir <hi>Nicholas Hide</hi> put in his <hi>Room,</hi> who preſently complyed with the King.</p>
                  <p>Sir <hi>Thomas Darnell,</hi> Sir <hi>John Corbet,</hi> Sir <hi>Walter Earl,</hi> Sir <hi>John Hevingham,</hi> Sir <hi>Edward Hamden,</hi> five of the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men Impriſoned for <hi>Refuſing the Loan,</hi> brought their <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beas Corpus</hi> in <hi>Michaelmas</hi> Term, in the third year of his Reign. The Warden of the <hi>Fleet</hi> made his <hi>Return,</hi> that <hi>they were detained in his Cuſtody by the ſpecial command of King</hi>; and Sir <hi>Robert Heath,</hi> then <hi>Attorney Generral,</hi> juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied this ſort of <hi>Impriſonment,</hi> though no ſpecial Cauſe was aſſign'd, and the Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Hide</hi> (who was made on purpoſe for it) did ſingly give <hi>Judgment</hi> for remanding the <hi>Gentlemen</hi> to perpetual <hi>Impriſonment.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="11">11. That <hi>Billotted Soldiers</hi> (many of which were Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts) upon whom he pleaſed for Puniſhments; theſe <hi>Soldiers</hi> committed ſo many <hi>Diſorders,</hi> maſtered the <hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> and diſturbed the <hi>Peace,</hi> that there was a <hi>General Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cry</hi> againſt them, many being <hi>undone</hi> by them: Yet this was not redreſſed.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. That in the year 1627. <hi>Iſſued a Commiſſion under the Great Seal to ſeveral Temporal Lords,</hi> with <hi>Neal</hi> and <hi>Laud,</hi> Biſhops of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> and <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Wells,</hi> and others to <hi>Raiſe Money by way of Exciſe,</hi> and to enforce the Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (and which is very probable) to awe the Parliament, which was to Aſſemble the 17<hi>th.</hi> of <hi>March</hi>; He</p>
                  <p n="13">13. Upon the 13<hi>th.</hi> day of <hi>January,</hi> 1627. ſent a private Seal to the Lord Treaſurer, to this Effect: <hi>We command you forthwith to pay to</hi> Philip Burlemark, <hi>Merchant, Thirty Thouſand Pounds, to be paid by him over by Bill of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:57844:9"/>
into the Low Countrys and</hi> Germany, <hi>unto Sir</hi> Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Balfoure, <hi>and</hi> John Dolbier, <abbr>Eſq</abbr> (who was a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt) <hi>for <hi>Levying and Providing certain Numbers of Horſe, with Arms for Horſe and Foot,</hi>
                     </hi> to be brought o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver into this Kingdom, <hi>for our Service,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Burlemark</hi> being afterwards call'd into the Houſe of Commons, and examin'd about this matter, Declared, <hi>That he received the Thirty Phouſand Pounds</hi>; That one <hi>Thouſand Horſe</hi> were levied, and theſe <hi>Horſes</hi> and their <hi>Riders</hi> were to come over, and <hi>Arms</hi> were to be provided for them in <hi>Holland,</hi> but heard a Countermand was gone to ſtay them.</p>
                  <p n="14">14. That cauſed Mr. <hi>Chambers,</hi> a Merchant, <hi>to be fined two thouſand Pounds,</hi> to be committed to the <hi>Fleet,</hi> until he made his <hi>Submiſſion,</hi> for ſaying, <hi>That the Merchants in no part of the World are ſcrued and wrung as in</hi> England; and that in <hi>Turkey</hi> they have more <hi>Encouragement.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="15">15. That <hi>Oppreſſed and Impriſon'd all Rank or Order of Men,</hi> viz. The Earl of <hi>Briſtol</hi> was two Years <hi>confined</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being charged with any <hi>Accuſation,</hi> or brought to <hi>Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al,</hi> or permitted to <hi>Anſwer</hi> for himſelf for <hi>offering to accuſe the Duke of</hi> Buckingham. He Committed the Earl of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rundel</hi> to the <hi>Tower,</hi> in time of <hi>Parliament,</hi> without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing any <hi>cauſe</hi> of his <hi>Commitment,</hi> which was a mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt <hi>violation of the Privileges</hi> of the <hi>Houſe of Peers</hi>; and though the <hi>Lords</hi> preſented a <hi>Remonſtrance,</hi> yet this <hi>Lord</hi> was long <hi>detained Priſoner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="16">16. That ſent a <hi>threatning Meſſage</hi> to the <hi>Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,</hi> That if he had not a timely Supply, he would <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take himſelf</hi> to <hi>New Councils.</hi> Which could only mean the <hi>putting an End to the uſe of Parliaments.</hi> That at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother time, ſaid to the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons, <hi>Remember</hi>
                     </hi> that <hi>Parliaments</hi> are altogether in my <hi>Power,</hi> therefore as <hi>I find the fruits of them, Good or Evil, they are to continue or not to be.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="17">
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:57844:10"/>17. His ſhameful <hi>betraying</hi> the poor <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> and uſing the Money (given by the charitable Proteſtants of <hi>England</hi> for their relief) in <hi>Equipping Ships</hi> to be ſent to the Aſſiſtance of the <hi>French</hi> King, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the poor Proteſtants of the <hi>Iſles of Rhee and Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chell.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="18">18. That without doubt, had a <hi>great hand in the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious Iriſh Rebellion,</hi> wherein above 150 thouſand poor <hi>Proteſtant Souls</hi> were moſt Barbarouſly Murthered, and this will more plainly appear by reading the <hi>Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> given by this King <hi>in the</hi> 17th. <hi>Year of his Reign, dated from</hi> Edinborough, and alſo the Commiſſion thereupon of <hi>Peilem Oneale,</hi> and <hi>Rorie Macguire</hi> to all the Papiſts, both <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Iriſh,</hi> within the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland</hi>; both which for the Readers better ſatisfaction, are Printed at large in this Book; and alſo a ſheet of Paper, call'd, <hi>Murther will Out,</hi> containing <hi>King Charles</hi> II's <hi>Letter to the Court of Claims in</hi> Ireland, 1663. Requiring the then Commiſſioners to reſtore the <hi>Earl of Antrim to his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate,</hi> for that he had made <hi>it appear,</hi> he had acted no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but by <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Commiſſion</hi> from King <hi>Charles</hi> I. read the Letter at large. Take notice this <hi>Earl of Antrim</hi> had been a <hi>very great Rebell,</hi> yet reſtored for ſerving that King, in murthering his <hi>Proteſtant Subjects</hi>; neither can any impartial Men think that <hi>King Innocent</hi> of this <hi>Wicked Act,</hi> if they conſider how <hi>Treacherouſly and Baſely he delt with the Proteſtants of</hi> England, of the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> of the <hi>Iſles of</hi> Rhee <hi>and</hi> Rochell. What <hi>Articles</hi> he made with <hi>France</hi> in <hi>favour of Popery</hi> upon his Match; what a mighty <hi>Influence</hi> his <hi>Popiſh Queen</hi> had over him; how he <hi>employed</hi> in great <hi>Places</hi> of <hi>Truſt,</hi> not only great <hi>Favourers</hi> of <hi>Popery,</hi> but alſo many <hi>profeſt Papiſts,</hi> and was very much Adviſed and Govern'd by their Counſels to the great <hi>Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row</hi> and <hi>Miſery</hi> of his poor <hi>Proteſtant Subjects</hi>; as alſo that in the Summer before that dreadful <hi>October</hi> 1641. a <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee</hi> of the moſt <hi>Active Papiſts,</hi> all afterwards in the <hi>head</hi>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:57844:10"/>
of the <hi>Rebellion,</hi> were in great <hi>favour</hi> at <hi>White-Hall,</hi> and admitted to many <hi>private Conſultations</hi> there with the <hi>King</hi> in the <hi>Queens Preſence</hi>; and thoſe <hi>Iriſh Prieſts depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not thence till within two Months before that Bloody Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion and Maſſacre.</hi> It was at that time, <hi>I morally be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve,</hi> that <hi>King Charles</hi> favoured the <hi>Iriſh Maſſacre,</hi> and the <hi>Iriſh Papiſts</hi> were ſo well aſſured of it, that they call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelves the <hi>Queen's Army,</hi> and ſaid they had good <hi>Warrant</hi> in <hi>Black</hi> and <hi>White</hi> for their <hi>Proceedings,</hi> and cryed out againſt the <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> as the King's Enemies. He that has a deſire of being ſatisfied how <hi>great a favourer King</hi> Charles <hi>was of Papiſts,</hi> let him read Mr. <hi>Pinn</hi>'s <hi>Book, called, <hi>The Royal Court Favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite.</hi>
                     </hi> He was very much <hi>adviſed</hi> by the then <hi>Parliament,</hi> to <hi>ſend early Relief to the poor Proteſtants of</hi> Ireland, but it is notoriouſly <hi>known,</hi> how <hi>backward</hi> he <hi>was therein,</hi> and that he <hi>ſuffered</hi> them to be <hi>Sacrificed</hi> to the <hi>cruel Mercy</hi> of the <hi>Iriſh Cut-Throats.</hi> It is alſo plain, that the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment had long and often requeſted the <hi>King</hi> to <hi>Declare</hi> the <hi>Iriſh, Rebels</hi>
                     </hi>; yet was this rare <hi>Proteſtant Martyr</hi> ſo <hi>Tender</hi> of the <hi>Poor Catholicks Reputation,</hi> for <hi>Acting</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his <hi>Commands,</hi> that no leſs than <hi>three Months</hi> paſt, before he would <hi>gratifie</hi> the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Commons</hi> with <hi>Proclaiming them Rebels,</hi> and when he had againſt his <hi>real inclination thus done,</hi> he was <hi>reſolved</hi>; That <hi>but a ſmall number ſhould be Printed and Publiſhed,</hi> and in order there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, the following Warrant was ſent to the King's Printer from his <hi>Secretary of State.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="warrant">
                              <p>IT is <hi>His Majeſty's Pleaſure, that you forthwith Print, in very good Paper,</hi> and <hi>ſend unto Me,</hi> for his <hi>Majeſties Service, Fourty Copies</hi> of the <hi>Proclamation incloſed,</hi> leaving convenient ſpace for his Majeſty to Sign above, and to affix the Privy Signet underneath: <hi>And His Maieſties Expreſs Command, is, Chat you Print not above the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:57844:11"/>
ſaid Number of Copies,</hi> and <hi>forbear</hi> to <hi>make any further Publication</hi> of <hi>them till his Pleaſure</hi> be further <hi>Signified,</hi> for which, this ſhall be your <hi>Warrant.</hi>
                              </p>
                              <closer>
                                 <dateline>
                                    <hi>White-Hall,</hi>
                                    <date>Jan. 2. 1641.</date>
                                 </dateline>
                                 <signed>Edward Nicholas.</signed>
                              </closer>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>See here what ſpecial care was taken, that a few only ſhould come to the knowledge of this Proclamation, when at the ſame time it was well obſerved, he dealt far other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe by the <hi>Scots,</hi> for they were more <hi>ſharply Proclaimed,</hi> and thoſe Proclamations with great <hi>care</hi> and <hi>dilligence,</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed throughout the whole Kingdom, and ordered to be read in all Churches accompanied with <hi>Publick Prayers</hi> and <hi>Execrations.</hi> But his <hi>Averſion</hi> to the Proclaiming and Proceeding againſt the <hi>Iriſh Rebels,</hi> is not to be much wondred at; for they call themſelves <hi>The Queen's Army,</hi> and declared that they <hi>Roſe</hi> to <hi>maintain</hi> the <hi>King's Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative,</hi> and the <hi>Queen's Religion,</hi> againſt the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; much more might be collected from divers Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, of this Tragical Story, which for Brevity Sake, I ſhall now omit.</p>
                  <p n="19">19. That to his Eternal Infamy againſt all Laws, both Humane and Divine, cauſed <hi>A Declaration</hi> to be Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed concerning the <hi>Lawfulneſs of Sports, Paſtimes,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>on the Lord's Day,</hi> and gave Archbiſhop <hi>Laud</hi> an <hi>Order, under his Hand,</hi> to ſee that this Declaration was <hi>Printed.</hi> Read the <hi>Order,</hi> and Declaration Printed at large in this Book; and alſo King <hi>Charces</hi> II's Declaration after his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoration. It is a wonderful and amazing thing, that there can be found amongſt us, ſuch <hi>Clergymen</hi> and <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> that againſt all Reaſon and Truth, ſhall make a <hi>Saint,</hi> nay, a <hi>Martyr,</hi> of this (as you ſee) <hi>Pious King</hi>; How theſe Men at the Great Day of Judgment, will be able to <hi>Anſwer</hi> for the many <hi>abominable Lies, and Blaſphemies</hi> they
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:57844:11"/>
have been <hi>Guilty of,</hi> in <hi>Defending this King's Tyrannies and Oppreſſions,</hi> and <hi>Deifying <hi>him after</hi>
                     </hi> a moſt <hi>ſcandalous Rate,</hi> is a Myſtery to me: The Publication of this <hi>Licentious Book,</hi> was ſo apparently deſtructive to <hi>Religion,</hi> and ſo <hi>diſhonourable to God,</hi> and the <hi>King,</hi> That the <hi>Pious</hi> and <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Clergy</hi> of that time, abſolutely <hi>refuſed</hi> either to <hi>Read it,</hi> or to <hi>permit it</hi> the ſaid <hi>abominable Declaration</hi> to be <hi>Read</hi>; and how barbarouſly, and unchriſtianly they were <hi>uſed for their Refuſal,</hi> is too well known.</p>
                  <p n="20">20 That gave <hi>Wicked, Arbitrary</hi> and <hi>Tyrannical Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Inſtructions</hi> and <hi>Commiſſions</hi> to the <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Strafford,</hi> Lord Lieutenant of <hi>Ireland</hi>; all which, the ſaid Earl, took ſuch care to Execute, that the Parliament which was made up of <hi>Grave, Able, and diſcerning Perſons, fell ſo ſeverely upon him,</hi> that they cauſed him to be <hi>Committed</hi> to the <hi>Tower, Impeached</hi> him, and ſoon after cauſed him to be according to his deſerts, <hi>Beheaded.</hi> He pleaded the <hi>King's Authority</hi> for what he had done, but the Commons ſaw no reaſon to acquit him. 'Twas obſerved, that tho the King and Queen would not publickly <hi>Solicite for his Relief,</hi> yet ſeveral <hi>ſecret Inſtances were made by them both,</hi> to ſave him that had obeyed their Commands, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But the juſt Cries of the People, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> neceſſitated the King a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Will to ſign the <hi>Warrant</hi> for his <hi>Execution.</hi> And having now given a ſhort account of the Earl of <hi>Strafford,</hi> I think it proper for the ſatisfaction of all thoſe good Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that <hi>deſire to be rightly informed, for what</hi> Laud <hi>Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of</hi> Canterbury <hi>was moſt juſtly Beheaded.</hi> The Houſe of Commons having proof, that he had a great <hi>Hand</hi> in all the <hi>Arbitrary Proceedings</hi> and <hi>Dealings</hi> with <hi>Rome,</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember 18<hi>th.</hi> 1640. they Voted him to be a <hi>Traytor</hi>; and Mr. <hi>Hollis</hi> was ſent to the Lords, to <hi>Accuſe</hi> him of <hi>High-Treaſon,</hi> which he did immediately; aſſuring the Lords, that in convenient time, there ſhould be a <hi>charge</hi> put in againſt him, to make <hi>Good the Accuſation,</hi> deſiring that he might be <hi>ſequeſtred</hi> from the <hi>Houſe</hi> and <hi>Committed,</hi> which
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:57844:12"/>
was forthwith done by the Lords. The <hi>Articles</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he was charged, conſiſt of theſe Heads, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>1. For that he had Treacherouſly endeavoured <hi>to ſubvert</hi> the <hi>Fundamental Laws</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>England</hi>; and inſtead thereof to <hi>Introduce</hi> an <hi>Arbitrary</hi> and <hi>Tyrannical Government</hi> againſt <hi>Law.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. That he had laboured to <hi>Overthrow</hi> the <hi>Authority of Parliaments,</hi> and the <hi>Force</hi> of the <hi>Laws</hi> of the Kingdom of <hi>England.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>3. That he had laboured to <hi>corrupt</hi> and <hi>pervert</hi> the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters</hi> of <hi>Juſtice.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>4. That he himſelf had <hi>corruptly bought</hi> and <hi>ſold Juſtice</hi> in his <hi>Seat.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>5. That he had put a <hi>New Book of Cannons</hi> in <hi>Execution</hi> againſt <hi>Law.</hi> Vide 2 Vol. 2<hi>d.</hi> Part of <hi>Ruſhworth</hi>'s Hiſt. Collect. Fol. 1365. <hi>&amp; ſequent.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>6. That he had Traytorouſly <hi>aſſumed to himſelf a Papal and Tyrannical Power, both in Eccleſiaſtical</hi> and <hi>Temporal Matters.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>7. That he had laboured to <hi>ſubvert</hi> the <hi>Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> and inſtead thereof, to <hi>ſet up Popiſh Superſtition</hi> and <hi>Idolatry.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>8. That he had <hi>prefer'd notorious Papiſt</hi> to <hi>Places</hi> of <hi>Dignity.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>9. That he had <hi>choſen</hi> to himſelf a <hi>Chaplain Popiſhly affected.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>10. That he had <hi>kept Confederacy</hi> and <hi>Intelligence</hi> with <hi>Popiſh Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Jeſuits.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>11. That he had <hi>cruelly perſecuted Godly Miniſters.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>12. That he had <hi>laboured</hi> to <hi>make Diviſions</hi> and <hi>Diſcord between us and other Churches.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>13. That he had <hi>ſtir'd up War</hi> and <hi>Enmity</hi> between his Majeſties two <hi>Kingdoms</hi> of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>14. That he had <hi>Slandered,</hi> and <hi>Incenſed</hi> His Majeſty againſt <hi>Parliaments.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <pb n="13" facs="tcp:57844:12"/>15. That he had <hi>laboured to ſlander Parliaments</hi> with the <hi>Nick Name</hi> of <hi>Puritans,</hi> and <hi>commended the Papiſts</hi> for <hi>harmleſs</hi> and <hi>peaceable Subjects.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>16. That he had <hi>Traytorouſly indeavoured</hi> to <hi>advance</hi> the Power of the <hi>Council Table,</hi> the <hi>Cannons of the Church,</hi> and the <hi>King's Prerogative,</hi> above the <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Statutes</hi> of the Realm.</item>
                        <item>17. That he had <hi>Wittingly</hi> and <hi>Willingly, Harboured, Countenanced</hi> and <hi>Relieved, divers Popiſh Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Jeſuits</hi>; and particularly one call'd, <hi>Santa Clara</hi> alias <hi>Damport</hi> a <hi>dangerous Perſon,</hi> and <hi>Franciſcan Fryar</hi>; and did alſo <hi>provide Maintenance,</hi> and <hi>Entertainment</hi> for one <hi>Monſieur</hi> St. <hi>Gyles,</hi> a <hi>Popiſh Prieſt</hi> at <hi>Oxford,</hi> knowing him to be a <hi>Popiſh Prieſt.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>18. That he had <hi>threatningly ſaid,</hi> there muſt be a <hi>Blow given to the Church,</hi> ſuch as had not <hi>been yet given, before it could be brought to Conformity.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>19. That he <hi>puniſhed divers Miniſters</hi> in Proſecution of the laſt <hi>Cannons, made by himſelf.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>20. That he had wickedly and malitiouſly <hi>Adviſed</hi> His Majeſty to <hi>diſſolve</hi> the laſt <hi>Parliament,</hi> and preſently after it was Diſſolved, told His Majeſty, <hi>That then he was abſolved from all Rules of Government, and left free to uſe all extraordinary Ways for his Supply.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe were the <hi>chief Heads</hi> of the <hi>Charge</hi> againſt that <hi>Proud, Popiſh,</hi> and <hi>Arbitrary Prelate,</hi> for which he was ſent Priſoner to the <hi>Tower.</hi> After ſome <hi>cloſe Inquiries</hi> and <hi>Examinations</hi> taken from the Informations of the <hi>late Lord Deputy of</hi> Ireland; it was ſufficiently known, that the Archbiſhop was the <hi>Conduite Pipe,</hi> through which the <hi>Popiſh Party,</hi> made the pernicious Seed of Diviſion <hi>run ſo ſmoothly</hi>; that he was the <hi>Wicked Inſtrument</hi> they made uſe of to <hi>ſtir</hi> up the <hi>Diviſion between the two Kingdoms of</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Scotland, and between the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> and the <hi>Presbyterians.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:57844:13"/>Theſe <hi>heavy charges</hi> being made good againſt this <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and he moſt <hi>righteouſly executed</hi> for theſe his notorious <hi>Evil Actions,</hi> Why are moſt of our <hi>Clergy,</hi> and ſome of our <hi>Laity</hi> ſo wicked, as to <hi>vindicate him,</hi> and without the <hi>leaſt Reaſon,</hi> or ſhaddow of <hi>Truth,</hi> cry him up for a <hi>Bleſſed Martyr,</hi> that had <hi>violated all the Laws</hi> of the Land, and was ſo great <hi>a Cauſe of moſt of the Miſeries of</hi> England? That to prevent the <hi>Peoples</hi> being too <hi>Religious,</hi> adviſed and highly promoted the <hi>Declaration</hi> of <hi>Sports</hi> on the <hi>Lord's Day</hi>; a time ſo <hi>odious</hi> in the ſight of any thing of a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> that it ought never to be forgotten.</p>
                  <p n="21">21. That after he had <hi>compleatly acted the part of a great Tyrant,</hi> and thereby had juſtly loſt the general Love, Eſteem, and Affection of the beſt Proteſtants of the three Kingdoms. He willingly conſented that Biſhop <hi>Gauden,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Duppa,</hi> &amp;c. ſhould <hi>compoſe a Book,</hi> and call it, <hi>His Portraiture or Picture</hi>; and this Book the King was <hi>to own as his, that it was compoſed by him,</hi> when God knows he had neither <hi>ſo much Piety,</hi> nor <hi>Capacity,</hi> as that Work re-required, though as a Noble Peer lately ſaid, <hi>Let that Book be Written by the King, or by any body elſe, there is little in it that deſerves Eſteem.</hi> The deſign of this Book was three-fold; the firſt was, By the Lies thereby, to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie the King's Arbitrary and Illegal Actions; ſecondly, Heavily to load the People of <hi>England</hi> with Rebellion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for ſtanding up for the legal <hi>Liberties</hi> and <hi>Properties</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to them, though abſolutely forced thereunto, to prevent the Inundation of <hi>Miſery</hi> and <hi>Popiſh Slavery,</hi> that the King and his wicked Court Favourites were then bringing on the <hi>three Kingdoms</hi>; thirdly, The cunning drift of the Factious and Defeated Party, deſign'd to make the ſame <hi>Advantage of his Book, as they did before of his Regal Name and Authority,</hi> and intended it, not only for a Defence of the <hi>King's former Actions,</hi> but alſo for <hi>promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their own future Deſigns.</hi> As for the Book, who ever is the real Author, has no occaſion to value himſelf for
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:57844:13"/>
that Work, <hi>two things</hi> being with the greateſt eaſe to be <hi>prov'd upon him.</hi> Firſt, That he is a moſt <hi>Notorious Lyer,</hi> both as to his Aſſertions of the <hi>King's Innocency</hi> of thoſe ſad <hi>matters juſtly laid to his Charge,</hi> and alſo of his many <hi>unjuſt Accuſations</hi> of the <hi>People of</hi> England; and ſecondly, That <hi>he was a Thief,</hi> and had ſo much <hi>Piety,</hi> as to have recourſe to the famous Sir <hi>Philip Sydney</hi>'s Arcadia (<hi>a Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance</hi>) in the time of his <hi>Troubles,</hi> and from thence to <hi>ſteal the Prayer of</hi> Pamelia (to an Heathen Diety) <hi>being under Impriſonment</hi>; not finding a ſuitable <hi>Form</hi> in the <hi>Liturgy, Pſalms</hi> of <hi>David,</hi> or any other places of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Scripture. And that the Reader may be ſatisfied of the Truth of this <hi>Piece of Thievery,</hi> I have thought fit to Print both <hi>Prayers</hi> in <hi>Collums</hi> one againſt the other. That of <hi>Pamelias</hi> may be found in <hi>Pembrook</hi>'s <hi>Arcadia,</hi> p. 248. 13 Edit. Printed 1674. That of <hi>King Charles</hi> I's, is call'd a <hi>Prayer</hi> in time of Captivity, Printed in a Great Folio, call'd, the <hi>Works of King</hi> Charles, and alſo in his <hi>Eicon Baſilike.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="prayer">
                              <head>The King's Prayer.</head>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>O</hi> Powerful, O Eternal God, to whom nothing is ſo Great, that it may reſiſt, or ſo Small, that it is contemn'd; look upon my Miſery with thine Eye of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and let thine Infinite Power vouchſafe to limit out ſome proportion of Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance unto me, as to thee ſhall ſeem moſt Convenient. Let not Injury, O Lord, Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph over me, and let my
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:57844:14"/>
Faults by thy Hand be Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, and make not my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt Enemies the Miniſters of thy Juſtice. But yet, my God, if in thy Wiſdom, this be the apteſt Chaſtiſment for my unexcuſable Tranſgreſſion; if this ungrateful Bondage be fitteſt for my over high Deſires if the Pride of my (not enough humble) heart be thus to be broken, O Lord, I yield unto thy Will, and chearfully em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace what ſorrow thou wilt have me ſuffer; only thus much let me crave of thee (let my craving, O Lord, be accepted of, ſince it even proceeds from thee) that by thy goodneſs, which is thy ſelf, thou wilt ſuffer ſome Beam of thy Majeſty, ſo to ſhine in my mind, that I, who in my greateſt Affliction, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge it my Nobleſt Title to be thy Creature, may ſtill de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend confidently on thee; let Calamity be the Exerciſe, but not the overthrow of my Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue; O let not their prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Power be to my Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; and if it be thy Will that they more and more vex me with Puniſhment, yet, O Lord, never let their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs have ſuch a hand, but that I may ſtill carry a pure
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:57844:14"/>
mind and ſtedfaſt Reſolution, ever to ſerve thee without fear, or Preſumption, yet with that humble confidence, which may beſt pleaſe thee; ſo that at laſt I may come to thy E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Kingdom, through the Merits of thy Son our alone Saviour, Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                              </p>
                           </div>
                           <div type="prayer">
                              <head>
                                 <hi>Pamelia</hi>'s Prayer to the Heathen Deity.</head>
                              <p>O All ſeeing Light, and Eternal Life of all things, to whom nothing is either ſo Great, that it may reſiſt, or ſo Small, that it is contemn'd; look upon my Miſery, with thine Eye of Mercy, and let thine Infinite Power vouchſafe to limit out ſome proporrion of Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance unto me, as to thee ſhall ſeem moſt Convenient. Let not Injury, O Lord, Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph over me, and let my
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:57844:14"/>
Faults by thy hand be Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, and make not mine unjuſt Enemies the Miniſter of thy Juſtice. But yet, my God, if in thy Wiſdom, this be the apteſt Chaſtiſment for my unexcuſable Folly; if this low Bondage be fitteſt for my over high Deſire; if the Pride of my (not enough humble) heart be thus to be broken, O Lord, I yield unto thy Will, and joyful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly embrace what ſorrow thou wilt have me ſuffer; only thus much let me crave of thee (let my craving, O Lord, be accepted of thee, ſince even that proceeds from thee;) let me crave e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by the Nobleſt Title, which in my greateſt Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, I may give my ſelf, that I am thy Creature, and by thy goodneſs which is thy ſelf; that thou wilt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer ſome Beam of thy Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty to ſhine into my mind, that it may ſtill depend con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently on thee; let Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity be the Exerciſe, but not the overthrow of my ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue; let their Power prevail, but prevail not to Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; let my Greatneſs be their Prey; let my pain be
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:57844:14"/>
the ſweetneſs of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge; let them (if ſo it ſeem good unto thee) vex me with more and more Puniſhment; but, O Lord, let never their Wickedneſs have ſuch a hand, but that I may carry a pure mind in a pure Body; <hi>and pauſing a while,</hi> O moſt gracious Lord, <hi>ſaid ſhe,</hi> whatever becomes of me, preſerve the vertuous <hi>Muſidorus.</hi>
                              </p>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>Having now given an Account of the deſign of Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing this ſpecial Book, and alſo what it is compoſed of, I ſhall now produce divers Reaſons (enough I think to convince any rational Man that will not be willfully blind. And firſt, I ſhall give you the Noble Earl of <hi>Angleſey</hi>'s <hi>Memorandum,</hi> perfixt before the Book reputed to be King <hi>Charles</hi> I's, called, <hi>Icon Baſilice,</hi> and found by <hi>Edward Millington,</hi> who ſold the ſaid Earl's Library, all Written with the Earl's own Hand, in theſe Words:</p>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="memorandum">
                              <p>
                                 <hi>King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, and Duke of <hi>York,</hi>
                                 </hi> did both (in the laſt Seſſion of <hi>Parliament,</hi> 1675. when I ſhew'd <hi>Them</hi> in the <hi>Lord's Houſe,</hi> the Written Copy of this <hi>Book,</hi> wherein are ſome Corrections, and Alterations written with the late King <hi>Charles</hi> I's own Hand, <hi>Aſſure me,</hi> That this was none of the ſaid King's Compiling, but made by Dr. <hi>Gauden,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Exeter</hi>; which I here incert for the undeceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing others in this Point, by atteſting ſo much under my Hand.</p>
                              <closer>
                                 <signed>ANGLESEY.</signed>
                              </closer>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:57844:15"/>This Noble Earl's <hi>Advertiſement,</hi> or <hi>Memorandum,</hi> muſt have the greater Weight, for that he concealed it (for ought I can hear) from the Publick, which doubtleſs he would not have done, if he had had any deſign to carry it on by making it Publick. This <hi>Memorandum</hi> being true, the World has the Words of two <hi>Kings,</hi> that Biſhop <hi>Gauden,</hi> and not King <hi>Charles, <hi>Compoſed this lying Book:</hi>
                     </hi> For further proof, that Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> writ this Book, take a Summary Account of ſome Papers relating, <hi>Eicon Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilice,</hi> now, or lately in the Hands of Mr. <hi>North,</hi> Merchant, living on <hi>Tower Hill,</hi> London; whereby it appears that Dr. <hi>Gauden,</hi> late Biſhop of <hi>Exeter,</hi> and afterwards of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> was the Author of that Book, and not King <hi>Charles</hi> I. as the World hath for above Forty Years been impoſed upon to believe.</p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>North</hi> is a worthy Perſon, and a Member of the Church of <hi>England</hi>; he, and Mr. <hi>Charles Gauden</hi> (the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop's Son) married two Siſters, and Mr. <hi>Gauden</hi> dying about Ten Years ſince, all his Papers were left with his Widow, and Mr. <hi>North</hi> having occaſion to look them o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, for ſome relating to his Siſter-in-laws affairs, found theſe relating to the <hi>Eicon Baſilice,</hi> carefully tied up to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>North,</hi> by reaſon of his Marriage, had many years acquaintance with Biſhop <hi>Gauden's</hi> Family, and knows that the Biſhop's Widow, at firſt gave them to her Dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Son, <hi>Iohn Gauden,</hi> and upon his Death, they came to Mr. <hi>Charles Gauden.</hi> And further, that in his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny years knowledge of that Family, it hath conſtantly, and without any manner of doubt, been declared, that the Biſhop was the Author of the Book. There are ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Letters and Papers, I ſhall briefly give the Contents of them, for the truth of which, I ſhall refer to the <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Papers,</hi> and to thoſe many reverend and worthy Perſons, who have Read, or been at the Reading of them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:57844:15"/>Biſhop <hi>Gauden,</hi> at the time of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second's Reſtauration, was incumbent of <hi>Bocking</hi> in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> and from that fat Parſonage was promoted to the <hi>Lean Biſhoprick</hi> of <hi>Exeter,</hi> which he complain'd was not ſufficient to keep up the Port of a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and thought that by his Merits he might lay claim to a better; and the Death of Dr. <hi>Duppa,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> being daily expected, he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd himſelf to the King, with great Importunity, to be tranſlated thither; pleading his Deſert, which, as is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent from the Papers I mention, could be no other than that of having written a Book which did ſuch great Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to the <hi>Royal Family,</hi> that King <hi>Charles</hi> the 2d. thought himſelf oblig'd to promiſe him that Biſhoprick, tho' when it became Void gave it to an other.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. There is Letter from Sir <hi>Edward Nicholas,</hi> Secretary of State, to Dr. <hi>Gauden,</hi> dated <hi>January</hi> 1660, wrote by the King's Command, intimating the King had received his Letter, and that he ſhould not have Cauſe to complain of his removal from <hi>Bocking.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. In the Biſhops Letter to Chancellor <hi>Hide,</hi> dated 28. <hi>December</hi> 1661, and his Petition to the King, the Biſhop ſets forth, That he had <hi>an high</hi> Rack [The Biſhoprick of <hi>Exeter</hi>] but Empty Manger; and declares what hazards he had run of Life and Eſtate; and what great Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage had accrued to the Crown by his Service: That what he had done was <hi>for Comforting and incouraging of the King's Friends, Expoſing his Enemies,</hi> and <hi>converting,</hi> &amp;c. He pleads that <hi>what was done like a King, ſhould have a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Retribution</hi>; and Inſtances in the Caſes of <hi>Joſeph, Mordecai,</hi> and <hi>Daniel,</hi> who were Honoured and Rewarded for the Service they did to the Reſpective Princes, (tho' as he obſerves) they were Captives in a ſtrange Land.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The Biſhops Letter to the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> dated the 17th of <hi>January</hi> 1661: Strongly urges the great Services he had done, and Importunately Begs his <hi>Royal Highneſs,</hi> to intercede for him with the <hi>King.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:57844:16"/>4. There is an Original Letter from the Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor <hi>Hide</hi> (all of his own hand writing) to the Biſhop of <hi>Exeter,</hi> dated 13<hi>th.</hi> of <hi>March</hi> 1661, importing, that the Chancellor had received ſeveral Letters from him: That he was uneaſy under the Biſhop's Importunity, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes his not being yet able to ſerve him; Speaks of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexing a <hi>Commendum</hi> to his Biſhoprick; and towards the cloſe it hath this remarkable Expreſſion, <hi>The Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar you mention,</hi> has indeed been imparted to me as a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret; I am ſorry I ever knew it, and <hi>When it ceaſes to be a Secret, it will pleaſe none but Mr. Milton.</hi> This is Subſcribed, <hi>Edw. Hide,</hi> C.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Mrs. <hi>Gauden</hi> after the Death of the Biſhop, writes to her Son Mr. <hi>John Gauden,</hi> That ſhe had ſent him an Hogſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head of Cyder, and Orders ſome Pictures to be ſent her by the ſame Man.</p>
                  <p>In this Letter ſhe ſpeaks of the Book commonly call'd the <hi>Kings</hi>; ſhe calls it the <hi>Jewel</hi>; and tells her Son, that <hi>her Husband hoped to make a Fortune by it,</hi> and wonders it ſhould be doubted whether her Husband wrote it; but ſays, <hi>She has a Letter of a very Great Man's</hi> that will clear it up.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. There is alſo a long <hi>Narrative</hi> of Mrs. <hi>Gauden</hi>'s Hand-writing, ſhewing, that her Husband wrote the Book. This ſhe ſent to her Son, with the Letter, wherein ſhe ſaid, <hi>She had ſent it that ſhe might be a</hi> Clavis <hi>to him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Narrative ſets forth, That after her Husband had wrote the Book, He ſhewed it to the Lord <hi>Capel,</hi> who ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved it, and was for the printing of it; but wiſhed <hi>the King</hi> might have a Sight of it.</p>
                  <p>That an Opportunity was taken to Convey it to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty by the Lord Marquiſs of <hi>Hertford,</hi> when He went to the <hi>Treaty</hi> at the <hi>Iſle of Wight.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That the Marquiſs after his Return from thence, told her Husband, that he gave the Book to the <hi>King</hi>; and his <hi>Majeſty</hi> did not like it, but was for putting it out, not
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:57844:16"/>
as his own, but another's. But it being Urged, That <hi>CROMWEL,</hi> and others of the Army, <hi>having got a great Reputation with the People,</hi> for Parts and Piety, <hi>it would do beſt to be in the King's Name.</hi> His <hi>Majeſty</hi> took time to conſider of it.</p>
                  <p>That the Marquiſs told her Husband, <hi>He knew not what was become of the Papers</hi>; and ſaid, <hi>God knows what will become of the King.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That her Husband not hearing the King's pleaſure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it, and finding Danger haſtening on him, he having kept a Copy by him, ſent it by one Mr. <hi>Symmonds,</hi> a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted Miniſter, to the Preſs, together with a Letter. That Mr. <hi>Royſton</hi> was the Painter, but did not know but the <hi>King</hi> wrote it: That part of it was ſeized in the Preſs, together with her Husband's Letter, and Mr. <hi>Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds</hi> was taken.</p>
                  <p>Nevertherleſs the Work was carried on, and finiſhed a few days after his Majeſty's death: That when it was publiſhed, the Parliament was Enraged; and her Husband conceiving his Life and Eſtate to be in danger, fled to Sir <hi>John Wennworth</hi>'s, near <hi>Yarmouth,</hi> intending thence to paſs the Seas: But Mr. <hi>Symmonds</hi> falling ſick, and dying ſoon after, not having been Examin'd, and it not being diſcovered that her Husband was concern'd in it, (the Letter which had been taken having no Name to it) he altered his purpoſe, and returned home.</p>
                  <p>That there was an Epiſtle at firſt intended: That the firſt Title was <hi>Suſpiſia Regalia,</hi> but changed to <hi>Eicon Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilice</hi>; and that there were two Chapters added.</p>
                  <p>That the Marquiſs of <hi>Hertford,</hi> the Lord <hi>Capel,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Duppa,</hi> and Biſhop <hi>Morley,</hi> were at firſt the only Perſons privy to it.</p>
                  <p>That after the King's Reſtoration, Dr. <hi>Morley</hi> told her Husband, That his Merit was ſuch, that he could Ask nothing but he could receive it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:57844:17"/>That <hi>Duppa,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> being very ſick, her Husband went to the <hi>King,</hi> and <hi>acquainted him that He was the Author of the Book</hi>; and for the Truth thereof ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed to Biſhop <hi>Duppa,</hi> his Majeſty's <hi>Tutor,</hi> who was yet living; and made an Apology for printing it, without his Majeſty's Father's Order, or his; but pleaded the Circumſtances of Time, and the King's danger.</p>
                  <p>That His Majeſty told her Husband, That till then, He never knew that he wrote it, but thought it was his Father's; yet wondred how he could have time: And ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved <hi>That it was wrote like a Scholar, as well as like a King</hi>; and ſaid that if it had been publiſhed ſooner, it might have ſaved his Fathers Life. That at the ſame time the King gave him a Promiſe of the Biſhoprick of <hi>Wincheſter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That when he afterwards acquainted the <hi>Duke of York</hi> That he was the Author of that Book, yet went under his Father's Name, the <hi>Duke</hi> anſwered, He thought his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Wrote it. That her Husband then told his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that the <hi>King</hi> had promiſed him the Biſhoprick of <hi>Wincheſter</hi>; and that his Highneſs aſſured him of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour.</p>
                  <p>That Biſhop <hi>Duppa</hi> dying, her Husband apply'd to the <hi>King</hi> upon his Promiſe; but Dr. <hi>Morley,</hi> (who had told her Husband that he might have what he would ask) got it; and her Husband was made Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter</hi>; but having enjoy'd it but about half a Year, fell Sick and Dyed.</p>
                  <p>That She Petitioned the King; ſetting forth, That her Husband left her a Widdow, with four Sons and a Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: That it coſt her Husband 200 <hi>l.</hi> to remove from <hi>Exeter</hi> to <hi>Worceſter</hi>; and pray'd his Majeſty to beſtow the half Years Rents upon her, which he denied, and gave them to another.</p>
                  <p>Reader, take Notice, This is the Subſtance, tho' not perhaps the Expreſs Words of Mrs. <hi>Gaudens</hi> Papers, and it
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:57844:17"/>
could be wiſhed, that the Papers themſelves were made Publick, then this ſhort account would be fully juſtified.</p>
                  <p>I cannot diſmiſh this matter without admiring the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable Providence of God, in the ſeveral ſteps towards the Diſcovery thereof, which was the intereſt of ſo great a number of Men, to have for ever Concealed and Buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. And</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Had not Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> been diſappointed of the Biſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prick of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> we ſhould never have heard of his compiling the <hi>Icon Baſilice</hi>; nor would he ever have bragg'd, <hi>That he had done like a King, if he had had a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Retribution.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Had Mrs. <hi>Gauden</hi> but been made Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter</hi> for half an Year, ſhe would probably have robb'd her Husband of the Glory of this Book, and ſuffered it to have been for ever a <hi>Iewel</hi> of the <hi>Crown.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That the World may have a further ſatisfaction in this matter, I ſhall give a ſhort account of what the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend and Pious Dr. <hi>Walker,</hi> lately Rector of <hi>Feyfield</hi> in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> hath Written and Publiſhed a ſhort time before he died, in Anſwer to the Ignorance and lying Impertinence of Dr. <hi>Hollingworth,</hi> Dr. <hi>Anthony Walker,</hi> in this Book call'd the <hi>True Account</hi> of the <hi>Author,</hi> of a Book Entitled, <hi>Icon Baſilice,</hi> &amp;c. gives the Reaſon of his Writing on this Subject. It was occaſion'd by Dr. <hi>Hollingworth</hi>'s Reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Charge on him, for declaring, That <hi>King</hi> Charles I. <hi>was not the Author of that Book.</hi> He ſecondly, ſolemnly appeals to the Searcher of Hearts, Avenger of Falſhood, and Revealer of Secrets; that he will write nothing for Truth, that he was not thoroughly perſwaded of, and that by as full Evidence as he judged ſuch a matter of Fact wanted, and at ſuch diſtance of Time, is capable of. Thirdly, that he will with undiſguiſed openneſs, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the means of his Knowledge, the reaſons of his Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, and the probable Arguments upon which his opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is Grounded. His Word are theſe: <hi>Fol.</hi> 3. <hi>Sect.</hi> 11.</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="24" facs="tcp:57844:18"/>
                        <hi>I</hi> know <hi>and</hi> believe <hi>the</hi> Book, <hi>whoſe Author is enquired after, was Written by Dr.</hi> Gauden, (<hi>except two Chapters Writ by Biſhop</hi> Duppa) <hi>ſo far as the ſubjoined means may produce ſuch Knowledge, and the Reaſons may induce ſuch Belief.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Firſt, <hi>Dr.</hi> Gauden, <hi>ſometime before the Whole was finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, was pleaſed to acquaint me with his Deſign, and ſhewed me the Heads of divers Chapters, and ſome of the Diſcourſes written of them, and after ſome time ſpent in perſual, he vouchſaft to ask my Opinion concerning it, and after ſome conſideration, I told him, I ſuppoſed, it would be much for the</hi> King's Reputation, Honour and Safety: <hi>But I expreſly added,</hi> I ſtuck at the lawfulneſs of it, and modeſtly asked him, how he ſatisfyed himſelf, ſo to impoſe upon the World? <hi>To which he ſo readily replied, that I concluded he had thought on it before,</hi> viz. look on the Title, 'tis the Portraicture, <hi>&amp;c. and no Man draws his own Picture, which ſatisfyed himſelf; and that he perfectly remembers, that in the</hi> 2 <hi>Chapter of the Earl of</hi> Strafford, <hi>in the firſt Edition,</hi> p. 8. l. 18, 19, 20. <hi>he explain'd, that he meant Dr.</hi> Juxton, <hi>then Biſhop of</hi> London, <hi>in the following paſſage,</hi> viz. He only hath been leaſt vext by them, who counſel'd me, not to conſent againſt the Vote of my own Conſcience.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, <hi>That ſome good time after, what had paſſed as now related, we being both in</hi> London, <hi>and having dined to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, Dr.</hi> Gauden <hi>in the Afternoon deſired me to walk with him to a</hi> Friend; <hi>when we were gone part of the way, he told me, he was going to the Biſhop of</hi> Salisbury, <hi>Dr.</hi> Duppa (<hi>whom he had acquainted with</hi> his deſign) <hi>to fetch what he had left with his</hi> Lordſhip <hi>to be peruſed, or to ſhew him what he had further Written, deſired me after a little Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to with-draw and leave them two alone, which I did, and after they had been ſome conſiderable time together, Dr.</hi> Gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den <hi>returned, and in the ſtreet gave me this Account of their Conference. My Lord of</hi> Salisbury <hi>told me there were</hi> two ſubjects more, <hi>he</hi> wiſhed <hi>I had</hi> thought on, <hi>and propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:57844:18"/>
them to me,</hi> viz. <hi>The</hi> Ordinance <hi>againſt the</hi> Common Prayer Book, <hi>and the</hi> denying <hi>His Majeſty the</hi> Attendance <hi>of his</hi> Chaplains (<hi>which are now the</hi> 16th. <hi>and</hi> 24th. <hi>Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in the Printed Book, and deſired me to Write two Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters upon them, which I promiſed, I would. But before we parted, he recalled that requeſt, and ſaid, I pray go you on, to finiſh what remains, and leave theſe two to me: I will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare two Chapters upon them, which accordingly he did, as Dr.</hi> Gauden <hi>owned to me and others whom he had made privy to the whole, and</hi> never pretended to have Written theſe, as he did to have done all the reſt.</p>
                     <p>Thirdly, <hi>Sometime after the King was Beheaded, I asked Dr.</hi> Gauden, <hi>whether the King had ever ſeen the Book? he gave me this Anſwer, I know it certainly, no more then you; but I uſed my beſt endeavours he might, for I delivered a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py of it to the Marqueſs of</hi> Hartford, <hi>when he went to the Treaty at the Iſle of</hi> Wight, <hi>and intreated his</hi> Lordſhip, <hi>if he could obtain any private opportunity, he would deliver it to</hi> His Majeſty, <hi>and humbly deſire to know</hi> His Pleaſure <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning it. But matters running then high againſt the</hi> King, <hi>he had no anſwer by that</hi> Lord.</p>
                     <p>Fourthly, <hi>After he was Lord Biſhop of</hi> Worceſter Elect, <hi>I asked him in private, whether that King</hi> Charles II. <hi>knew that he wrote it? He gave me this Anſwer; I cannot poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively and certainly ſay, he doth, becauſe, he was never pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to take expreſs notice of it to me. But, I take it for gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, he doth; for I am ſure the Duke of</hi> York <hi>doth, for he hath ſpoken of it to me, and</hi> own'd it as a ſeaſonable and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable ſervice, <hi>and he knowing it, I queſtion not but the</hi> King <hi>alſo doth.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Fifthly, <hi>Mrs.</hi> Gauden <hi>his Wife, Mr.</hi> Gifford (<hi>who, if I am not miſtaken,</hi> Tranſcribed <hi>that</hi> Copy <hi>that was ſent to the Iſle of</hi> Wight) <hi>and my ſelf, believed it as much as we could any thing, and when we ſpake of it in his Preſence, or Abſence, did it, without the leaſt</hi> Doubt <hi>of his having</hi> Writ it; <hi>and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:57844:19"/>
we ſhould be impoſed upon to the higheſt degree imaginable, if Dr.</hi> Gauden <hi>wrote it not.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Sixthly, <hi>Dr.</hi> Gauden <hi>delivered to me with his own hand, what was laſt ſent up (after part was Printed, or at leaſt in Mr.</hi> Royſton's <hi>hand to be Printed) and after he had ſhew'd it me, and ſealed it up, gave me ſtrict caution, with what wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſs to carry and deliver it, and according to his Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I delivered it,</hi> Saturday <hi>December</hi> 23d. 1648. <hi>in the Evening to one</hi> Peacock (<hi>Brother to Dr.</hi> Gauden<hi>'s Steward or Bayliff) who was inſtructed by what hands he ſhould tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit it to Mr.</hi> Royſton, <hi>and in the ſame method, a few days after the Impreſſion was finiſhed,</hi> I received ſix Books <hi>by the hand of Mr.</hi> Peacock, <hi>as an acknowledgment of</hi> that little I contributed to that Service; <hi>one of which I have ſtill by me, and to juſtifie this matter againſt the ignorant impudence of Dr.</hi> Hollingsworth, <hi>be Declares</hi> Fol. 15. <hi>That he is ready to</hi> confirm <hi>his</hi> Knowledge <hi>and</hi> Belief <hi>herein with a</hi> Solemn Oath.</p>
                     <p>Mrs. <hi>Gauden,</hi> Widow, reſiding at <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> and often Declaring that her Husband had writ that, call'd, the <hi>King's Book,</hi> it coming at laſt to the knowledge of Dr. <hi>Nicholſon</hi> then Biſhop of <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> who deſiring to be fully ſatisfied in that point, did put the Queſtion to her; upon her <hi>receiving the Sacrament,</hi> and ſhe then affirmed, that it was <hi>wrote by her Husband.</hi> This, Perſons of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted credit now living in <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> can affirm for a Truth; and it is not queſtion'd, but the preſent Biſhop of <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> will acknowledge that thoſe Perſons have related this matter to him, that it is well known to Mrs. <hi>Gauden</hi>'s Brother, and ſeveral of her Relations, that Mrs. <hi>Gauden</hi> conſtantly in her Converſation, Declared, <hi>That her Husband was the Author of this Book.</hi> I could, if neceſſity requird, produce a great many Arguments more out of Doctor <hi>Walkers,</hi> or other Writings, to prove the Truth of this matter, but ſhall conclude it with this one
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:57844:19"/>
of the <hi>Doctors,</hi> in reference to the Providence of this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <q>
                        <hi>Though</hi> God <hi>had many Holy, Righteous and Gracious ends to ſerve his Providence by, in the</hi> Publication of this Book; <hi>yet as I find it expreſſed in this very Book,</hi> Chap. the laſt p. 262. of the firſt Edition. <hi>God's wiſe Providence (we know) oft permits many Events, which his revealed Word, in no ſort approves.</hi> And, <hi>I confeſs, I have many cogent reaſons to perſuade me, that God was not well pleaſed with Dr.</hi> Gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, <hi>others, or my ſelf; for what we contributed to it.</hi> And <hi>though for the aforeſaid ends, he ſuffered it to ſucceed,</hi> yet I know not but he may have other ends now to ſerve, <hi>by ſuffering this Diſcovery to be Wrung, and reſted from me,</hi> (I had almoſt ſaid) <hi>by ſome Bodies (viz.</hi> Hollingworths) <hi>Impertinent Affection, to meddle with what he underſtands not.</hi>
                     </q> Thus ſpake that good Man.</p>
                  <p>I had not enlarged ſo much on this 21<hi>ſt.</hi> Article, but that I was deſirous of giving full ſatisfaction to the World, of the <hi>Real Author</hi> of <hi>Eicon Baſilice.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That Poſterity might not be deceived by the many Impudent, Ignorant, Falſe, and Scandalous <hi>Aſſertions</hi> of moſt of the <hi>Clergy,</hi> and too many of the <hi>Laity,</hi> who to their Eternal Shame have taken more care and pains to defend that <hi>Book,</hi> and its pretended Author King <hi>Charles</hi> I. than they done to Vindicate the <hi>Holy Bible,</hi> and the <hi>Truth of the Chriſtian Religion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="22">22. That cauſed the <hi>Star-Chamber</hi> and <hi>High-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion-Courts</hi> to be made Uſe of, to the general Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of the People of <hi>England,</hi> and was unwilling to part with them, till he found theſe Courts were highly offenſive to the Parliament, and that it was not Seaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to diſpleaſe the Kingdom at that time, for which Reaſons at laſt he paſs'd the Bills to take them away: And indeed there were many, and great Reaſons, why thoſe abominable oppreſſive Courts ſhould be pull'd down,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:57844:20"/>
and taken away. For that <hi>Old Serpent</hi> Arch-Biſhop <hi>Laud,</hi> and divers of his Brethren, had caſt off all Humanity, and were metamorphoſed into <hi>Ravenous Wolves,</hi> and theſe <hi>Courts</hi> were under their Management. The <hi>Star-Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> had abounded in Extravagant Cenſures, whereby the Subjects were oppreſs'd by Grievious Fines, Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Stigmatizings, Mutilations, Whippings, Pillories, Gags, Baniſhments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And the <hi>High Commiſſion Court,</hi> was grown to ſuch Exceſs of Sharpneſs and Severity, as was not much leſs than the <hi>Spaniſh Inquiſition.</hi> To re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat two or three of the many Inſtances of the Horrid Oppreſſions, and barbarous Cruelty, exerciſed in theſe <hi>Tyrannical Courts.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Upon the 17<hi>th.</hi> of <hi>February,</hi> 1629. Dr. <hi>Leighton</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of <hi>Black Fryers Church,</hi> (it ſeems then he was no Conventicler) was ſeized by a Warrant from the <hi>High Commiſſion Court,</hi> and dragged to Biſhop <hi>Laud</hi>'s Houſe; from thence without any Examination, he was carried to <hi>New-gate,</hi> and there clapt into <hi>Irons,</hi> and thruſt into a <hi>Naſty Hole,</hi> where he continued from <hi>Tueſday</hi> Night, till <hi>Thurſday</hi> Noon, without Meat or Drink: They kept him in that loathſome Place, where Snow and Rain beat in upon him Fifteen Weeks, not permitting his Wife, or any Friend, to come near him, and <hi>denyed to give him a Copy of his Commitment</hi>; then they brought him into the <hi>Star-Chamber Court,</hi> where an <hi>Information</hi> was Exhibited a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, for Publiſhing a Book, call'd, <hi>Lyon's Plea againſt the Prelates.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Dr. <hi>Leighton</hi> confeſs'd, that in 1628. He drew up the Heads of that Book, and having the approbation of five hundred Perſons, under their hands, ſome whereof were Parliament Men. He went into <hi>Holland,</hi> and got between five and ſix hundred Printed for the uſe of the Parliament; but they being Diſſolved, he returned home, not bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any of them into the Land, but made it his ſpecial care
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:57844:20"/>
to ſuppreſs them. In the ſame information, the Doctor was charged with theſe Words in the ſaid Book; <hi>We do not read of greater Perſecutions of God's People in any Nation profeſſing the Goſpel, then in this our Iſland, eſpecially ſince the Death of Queen</hi> Elizabeth. He confeſſed the Words, and Anſwered, <hi>That the thing was too true, as appeared by the Prelates taking away Life and Livelihood from many M<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>niſters and private Men</hi>; of whom, many were pined to Death in Priſon, and many wandred up and down, their Families being left deſolate and helpleſs: That beſides this, <hi>the Blood of Souls</hi> had been endanger'd by the <hi>Removal</hi> of the <hi>Faithful Shepheards</hi> from the <hi>Flock</hi>; this was a cutting Truth. And</p>
                  <p>Wicked <hi>Laud,</hi> being enraged, <hi>Deſired the Court to put the higheſt Cenſure that could be put upon him</hi>; which they did to his Content, <hi>Condemning him to have his Ears cut, his Noſe ſlit, to be Branded in the Face, Whipped at a Poſt, to ſtand on a Pillory, to pay Ten Thouſand Pound fine (tho' they knew he was not worth ſo much) and to be perpetually Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned.</hi> This <hi>Helliſh Sentence</hi> being paſt, that vile Wretch <hi>Laud</hi> was ſo well pleaſed with it, that he pull'd of his <hi>Cap,</hi> and holding up his Hands, <hi>gave thanks to God who had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him Victory over his Enemies.</hi> This Sentence being ſo miſerably ſevere, the Execution thereof was little expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted. But,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Laud</hi> had his deſign; for upon the 26<hi>th.</hi> of <hi>November,</hi> 1630. The Cenſure was Executed in a moſt cruel manner, <hi>His Ears were cut, his Noſe ſlit, his Face Branded with burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Irons, he was tyed to a Poſt, and Whipped with a treble Cord, to that cruel Degree,</hi> that he himſelf Writing the Hiſtory thereof Ten Years after, affirmed that <hi>every laſh brought away the Fleſh,</hi> and that he ſhould feel it to his dying day. He was laſtly, <hi>put into the Pillory,</hi> and kept there near two hours in Froſt and Snow; and then, after this moſt barbarous Uſage, not permitted to return to his Quarters
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:57844:21"/>
in the <hi>Fleet Priſon,</hi> in a Coach provided to carry him, but compelled in that ſad Condition, and ſevere Seaſon, to go by Water.</p>
                  <p>After this, <hi>was kept Ten Weeks in Dirt and Mire,</hi> not being ſheltered from Rain and Snow; <hi>They ſhut him up moſt cloſely, Twenty Two Months, and he remain'd a Priſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Ten or Eleven Tears, not ſuffered to breath in the open Air,</hi> until that <hi>Noble Parliament</hi> of <hi>November,</hi> 1640. moſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily delivered him. When he came abroad to proſecute his Petition, in that <hi>Parliament,</hi> he could neither <hi>Go, See,</hi> nor <hi>Hear.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This <hi>Diſmal Story,</hi> will be an <hi>Eternal Blot,</hi> not only on <hi>Laud,</hi> who was the chief Inſtrument in that <hi>ſad Oppreſſion,</hi> but alſo upon the <hi>pretended Martyr King</hi> Charles, for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting ſuch Barbarous, and inhumane Cruelties to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed on his Subjects. I ſhall ſhew you ſomething mo<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e of this <hi>Bloody Villains Barbarity,</hi> viz.</p>
                  <p>That upon the firſt of <hi>February,</hi> 1632. <hi>Laud</hi> procured Mr. <hi>Prin,</hi> to be ſent cloſe Priſoner to the <hi>Tower,</hi> there he lay till the 21<hi>ſt.</hi> of <hi>June,</hi> 1633. when an Information (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out mentioning any particular Paſſages in his Book) was exhibited againſt him, in the <hi>Star Chamber Court,</hi> for Publiſhing a Book concerning <hi>Interludes,</hi> intitled. <hi>Hiſtrio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſtix, which was Licenſed by a Chaplain of Dr.</hi> Abbatts, Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury.</hi> Upon the 17<hi>th.</hi> of <hi>February,</hi> 1633. notwithſtanding his Book was Licenſed, yet he had this heavy Sentence paſſed upon him, <hi>viz. To be Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned for Life, pay Five Thouſand Pounds Fine, be Expell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> Lincolns-Inn, <hi>Diſabled to Exerciſe the Proſeſſion of a Barriſter, Degraded by the Univerſity of</hi> Oxford <hi>of his Degrees there taken; and that done, to be ſet in the Pillory at</hi> Weſtminſter, <hi>and have one of his Ears there cut off, and at another time, to be ſet in the Pillory in</hi> Cheap-ſide, <hi>and there to have his other Ear cut off.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:57844:21"/>Though many of the Lords never dreamt of the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of this Horrid Judgment, nay, though Queen <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietta Maria,</hi> (which deſerves an Honourable Mention) and ſhe ſhall have it, for <hi>She was the preſent King's Royal Grandmother, earneſtly interceded with, the Biggotted, Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el, and Mercileſs King, (who was an abominable T—) to remit its Execution</hi>; yet on the <hi>7th.</hi> and 10<hi>th.</hi> of <hi>May,</hi> it was fully Executed with great Rigour, and Mr. <hi>Prin</hi> remain'd <hi>Sundry Tears</hi> in the <hi>Tower</hi> upon this cenſure.</p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Burton,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Baſtwrick,</hi> were alſo without the leaſt juſt cauſe violently proſecuted after the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; it will be too tedious to relate theirs and others un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian uſes; when <hi>Tyranny</hi> and <hi>Arbitrary Power</hi> were <hi>Rampant.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="23">23. That againſt the <hi>Law of Nature,</hi> againſt the <hi>Rules of Juſtice,</hi> falſely charged thoſe Innocent Men, the Noble Lord <hi>Mandeville,</hi> Mr. <hi>Hollis,</hi> Mr. <hi>Strode,</hi> and others, with <hi>Treaſon,</hi> for which in the Face of the <hi>Higheſt Judicature in the Kingdom,</hi> they were moſt unjuſtly Impriſoned, the King <hi>denying them the Names of their Accuſers</hi>; and which was an <hi>Act of Tyranny</hi> beyond Parrallel, <hi>He accuſed them, and yet would produce no Witneſs, he confeſſed them clear in his own Judgment, yet they muſt not profeſs their own Innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy for fear of wounding his Honour.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="24">24. That was not ſatisfied with Impriſoning and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing ſome of the Parliament Men, <hi>but tempted and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged his</hi> Engliſh <hi>Army, with no leſs than the</hi> Spoil <hi>of the City of</hi> London, <hi>to come up and deſtroy the</hi> Parliament. He in an <hi>Hoſtile and inexcuſable manner,</hi> made a moſt high In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſion upon the Priviledges of both <hi>Houſes</hi>; Hereupon ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Citizens</hi> unarm'd, reſorted to <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> to preſent their <hi>Petitions,</hi> and expreſs their ſtedfaſtneſs to the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> whoſe <hi>Lives</hi> and <hi>Safety,</hi> by more than ſlight Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, they doubted to be in <hi>Danger</hi>; the King having fortified <hi>White-Hall,</hi> and entertained <hi>Armed Men,</hi> not a
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:57844:22"/>
few, planted them at the <hi>Gate of his Palace.</hi> ['Tis remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, the firſt Blood that was drawn in this Cauſe, was in that very place where the <hi>King's own Blood was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſhed,</hi> 1 K. 21. 19.] where they Reviled, Menaced, and with drawn Swords, actually Wounded many of the <hi>Citizens,</hi> as they paſſed by in a peaceable manner, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of <hi>ſome dyed.</hi> Nay, they went farther, and were come to that height of Boldneſs, as to give out Inſolent and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacing Speeches againſt the <hi>Parliament</hi> it ſelf, and to <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brue their hands in the Blood of the King's Subjects in</hi> Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter-Hall, and at the Doors of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> as well as at his own <hi>Gate.</hi> And when the <hi>Parliament</hi> and People complain'd, and demanded Juſtice for thoſe <hi>Aſſaults,</hi> the King juſtified and abetted his own <hi>Crew</hi> in what they did.</p>
                  <p>Nor can the paſſing by of a multitude of the King's Subjects, <hi>armed with no other Weapons then Petitions,</hi> be juſtly call'd <hi>Tumults</hi>; neither could the <hi>Parliament</hi> have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid them, without the Breach of the Peoples Freedom. <hi>Unarmed Petitioners ſurely could not be formidable to any</hi>; and it muſt not be forgotten, that a very ſhort time before His Majeſty pretended to dread theſe Tumultuary Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, <hi>the City Entertained, Feaſted, and Conducted him to <hi>White-Hall,</hi> with as pompous Sollemnity, and coſtly Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of Love and Duty, as ever had been known.</hi> Nay, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had highly exaſperated the People by his Irruption with the Houſe of Commons, he went in his <hi>Coach un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guarded into the City:</hi> He received not the leſt Affront, much leſs, Violence in any of the Streets, but rather hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Demeanours and Supplications. He knew the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſo full of Awe and Reverence to his Perſon, as to commit himſelf ſingle amongſt the thickeſt of them, at a time when had moſt provoked them: <hi>This ſhews be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond doubt, That all his fear of Tumults, was but a meer pretence, and occaſions taken for his reſolved Abſence from
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:57844:22"/>
the Parliament, that he might turn his ſlaſhing at the</hi> Court Gate, <hi>to ſlaughtering in the Field.</hi> In order thereunto, the King retires firſt to <hi>Hampton Court,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding his Servants, who were then Members of Parliament, to leave their ſervice there, and to give their Attendance upon his Perſon. Soon after, his <hi>Popiſh Queen</hi> paſſes into <hi>Holland,</hi> carrying with her, all, or the the greateſt part of the Crown <hi>Jewels,</hi> which ſhe immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately Pawn'd, and with the Money bought Arms and Ammunition for the War which was not yet begun.</p>
                  <p>Upon the 1<hi>ſt.</hi> of <hi>March,</hi> 1641. <hi>Both Houſes called upon His Majeſty, by their Petition preſented at <hi>Theobalds</hi>; That for the Diſpatch of the great Affairs of the Kingdom, the ſafety of his Perſon, the Protection and Comfort of his Subjects, he would be pleaſed to continue his abode, near the Parliament, and not to with-draw himſelf to any of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moter Parts, which if he ſhould do, muſt needs be a cauſe of great danger and diſtraction; and they pray'd him to accept this humble Counſel, as the Effect of that Duty and Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance which they ow'd unto him, and which would not ſuffer them to admit of any thoughts, intentions, or endeavours, but ſuch as were neceſſary and advantagious for His Majeſties Greatneſs and Honour, and the Safety and Proſperity of the Kingdom.</hi> Theſe are Expreſſions ſurely, that did not in the leaſt ſavour of that <hi>Sedition</hi> and <hi>Rebellion,</hi> with which our <hi>wicked Clergymen,</hi> charge the Memory of this Great and Noble <hi>Parliament.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The King willingly giving himſelf up to the Conduct of Evil Counſellors, was deaf to the importunate ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Lords and Commons for his <hi>Return</hi>; they therefore <hi>called again upon him</hi> more earneſtly, and ſent after him a <hi>Declaration</hi> to <hi>New-Market,</hi> by the Earls of <hi>Pembrook</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> and a Committee of the <hi>Commons,</hi> wherein they laid before him the Cauſes of their own <hi>Fears</hi> and <hi>Jealouſies,</hi> in theſe particulars:</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:57844:23"/>1. <hi>That the deſign of</hi> altering Religion, <hi>had been potent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly carried on, by thoſe in greateſt Authority about him; the</hi> Queen's <hi>Agent at</hi> Rome, <hi>the</hi> Pope's Nuncio <hi>here, are not only Evidences of this Deſign, but have been great Actors in it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>That the War with</hi> Scotland, <hi>was procured to make way for this Intent, and chiefly fomented by the Papiſts, and others Popiſhly affected, whereof we have many Evidences.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>That the Rebellion in</hi> Ireland, <hi>was framed and contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved here in</hi> England; <hi>and that the</hi> Engliſh <hi>Papiſts ſhould have riſen about the ſame time</hi>: We have ſeveral Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, <hi>&amp;c. The</hi> Iriſh <hi>Rebels affirm, That they do nothing but by Authority from the King; they call themſelves the</hi> Queen's <hi>Army; the Booty which they take from the</hi> Engliſh, <hi>they mark with the</hi> Queen's <hi>mark, and it is proved, that their purpoſe was to come to</hi> England, <hi>after they had done in</hi> Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>The labouring to infuſe into Your Majeſties Subjects an evil Opinion of the</hi> Parliament, <hi>and other Symptons of a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of</hi> raiſing Arms, <hi>and dividing your People by a</hi> Civil War, <hi>in which Combuſtion,</hi> Ireland <hi>muſt needs be loſt, and this Kingdom miſerably waſted and conſumed, if not wholly ruined and deſtroyed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. <hi>That Your Majeſty ſent away the Lord</hi> Digby <hi>by your own Warrant beyond Sea, after a Vote had paſſed in the</hi> Houſe of Commons, <hi>Declaring, That he had appear'd in a Warlike manner at</hi> Kingſton <hi>upon</hi> Thames, <hi>to the terror of your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties good Subjects; that he being ſo got beyond Sea, he vented his traiterous Conceptions, that Your Majeſty ſhould declare your Self, and retire to a place of Strength, and inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated ſome ſervice which he might do in thoſe parts, whereby, in probability, he intended the procuring of ſome</hi> Foreign Force <hi>to ſtrengthen Your Majeſty, in that Condition into which he would have brought you; which malicious Counſel, we have great cauſe to doubt, made too deep an Impreſſion in Your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty,</hi>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:57844:23"/>
conſidering the courſe you are pleaſed to take, of ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting your Self from that Parliament, <hi>and carrying the Prince with you, which ſeems to expreſs a purpoſe in Your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty to keep your Self in a readineſs for the Acting of it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6. <hi>The manifold Advertiſements which we have had from</hi> Rome, Venice, Paris, <hi>and other parts,</hi> That they ſtill ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect that Your Majeſty has ſome great deſign in hand, for the altering of Religion, <hi>the breaking the Neck of your Parliament, and that you will yet find means to compaſs that deſign; that the</hi> Pope's Nuncio <hi>hath ſollicited the Kings of</hi> France <hi>and</hi> Spain <hi>to lend Your Majeſty</hi> 4000 <hi>Men a piece, to help to maintain your Royalty againſt the Parliament.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Theſe are ſome of the grounds of our</hi> Fears <hi>and</hi> Jealouſies, <hi>which made us ſo earneſtly to implore your Royal Authority and Protection for our Defence, and ſecurity, in all the ways of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility and Submiſſion, which being denyed by Your Majeſty,</hi> We do with ſorrow apply our ſelves to the uſe of that Power [<hi>viz. the Militia</hi>] which by the Fundamental Laws of this Kingdom, reſides in us; yet ſtill reſolving to keep our ſelves within the Bounds of Faithfullneſs, and Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance to your Sacred Perſon and your Crown.</p>
                  <p>And as to the <hi>Fears and Jealouſies</hi> which His Majeſty ſeem'd to have Entertained of them.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> thus Anſwered.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We have according to Your Majeſties deſires, laid our hands upon our Hearts; we have asked our ſelves in the ſtricteſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination of our Conſciences; we have ſearched our Affections, our Thoughts; conſidered our Actions, and can find none that can give Your Majeſty any juſt Occaſion to abſent your ſelf from</hi> White-Hall, <hi>and the</hi> Parliament; <hi>but that you may with more Honour and Safety continue there, than in any other place.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Your Majeſty lays a great Charge upon Us; if you will gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly be pleaſed to let us know the Particulars, we ſhall give a clear and ſatisfactory Anſwer: But what hope can we have of ever giving Your Majeſty ſatisfaction, when thoſe particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:57844:24"/>
which you have been made believe were true, yet being produced and made known to us, appeared to be falſe; and Your Majeſty notwithſtanding, will neither</hi> Puniſh, <hi>nor</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce <hi>the Authors: But go on to contract new Jealouſies and Fears, upon general and uncertain Grounds, affording Us no means or poſſibility of particular Anſwer, to the clearing of our ſelves.</hi> We beſeech Your Majeſty to conſider in what ſtate you are, <hi>how eaſie and fair a way You have to Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Honour, and Greatneſs, Plenty and Security, if you will joyn with the Parliament in the Defence of the Religion, and publick good of the Kingdom</hi>; this is all we expect from you. <hi>And for this we return to you, our Lives, Fortunes, and ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Endeavours to ſupport Your Majeſty, Your juſt Power and Soveraignty over us</hi>; but it is not Words that can ſecure us in theſe our humble Deſires. <hi>We cannot, but too well and ſorrowfully remember, what</hi> Gracious Meſſages <hi>we had from You this Summer, when</hi> with your Privity, <hi>the bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up the Army was in Agitation: We cannot but with the like Affections recall to our Minds, how, not two days before your own coming to the Commons Houſe, You ſent a</hi> Gracious Meſſage, <hi>that You would always have a care of their Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, as of your own Prerogative; of the ſafety of their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, as of your own Children: That which we expect, which will give us Aſſurance, that you have</hi> no thought but of Peace and Juſtice to your People, <hi>muſt be ſome real effect of your Goodneſs to them, in granting thoſe things which your preſent neceſſity of the Kingdom do inforce us to deſire; and that you will be Graciouſly pleaſed to put from you thoſe</hi> Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous Counſellors, <hi>which have cauſed all theſe Dangers and Diſtractions, and to continue your own Reſidence and the Princes, near</hi> London <hi>and the</hi> Parliament, <hi>which we hope will be an happy beginning of Contentment and Confidence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Your</hi> Majeſty <hi>and</hi> People, <hi>and be followed with many ſucceeding Bleſſings of Honour and Greatneſs to Your</hi> Majeſty, <hi>and of Security and Proſperity to them.</hi> Theſe are brief
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:57844:24"/>
Heads of the Declaration, to which the King Anſwered: <hi>Have I violated your Laws</hi>? To which both Houſes made this pertinent Reply. <hi>We are heartily ſorry We have ſuch plentiful Matter of an Anſwer to that Queſtion,</hi> Have I vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated your Laws?</p>
                  <p>I muſt alſo take Notice, that in the beginning of the Year, 1642. a time when the King was in appearance tranſacting matters amicably with the two Houſes, and we ſeemed to be in a deep Peace; a time when he Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>That he had received no other Carriage from his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, than what he profeſſed himſelf ſatisfied with; and that if the Bills he had paſt, were again to be offered, he ſhould cheerfully and readily Aſſent unto them.</hi> Even then, he diſpatch'd away Letters, and an Agent to the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> complaing of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and asking Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies from thence, <hi>AD PROPUL SANDOS HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STES,</hi> you know the Engliſh of that is, to <hi>Subdue his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies,</hi> and declared himſelf in theſe Words; <hi>Ad allia Conſilia Animum Convertendum Duximus:</hi> We reſolve to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take our ſelves to new Counſels. <hi>The very Words he uſed to that Parliament in the Year,</hi> 1628.</p>
                  <p>Further, upon the diſcovery of his Plot to bring up the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army againſt the <hi>Parliament,</hi> he turn'd to the <hi>Scottiſh Army</hi> then at <hi>New Caſtle,</hi> and baited his Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with a rich Reward, <hi>not only to have</hi> 300000 <hi>l. in hand, and the ſpoil of</hi> London, <hi>but four Northern Counties to be made</hi> Scotiſts. Moreover, to encourage them to joyn with him, he Declared to them, <hi>That he was to have Money and Horſe from</hi> Denmark, <hi>and that he would make</hi> York <hi>the place of his Reſidence,</hi> for the better accommodation of both Nations, or fuller Revenge upon <hi>London.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He alſo gathered Men in <hi>London,</hi> under pretence of raiſing <hi>Forces</hi> for <hi>Portugal, who were to poſſeſs themſelves of the</hi> Tower. The Queen in <hi>Holland</hi> was buying Arms, and His Majeſty had actually raiſed Forces in divers
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:57844:25"/>
Counties. The <hi>Parliament</hi> was all this time Petitioning in Peace; and for the Reaſons now aſſigned amongſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others, <hi>They humbly beſought him, that he would be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to put the</hi> Tower <hi>of</hi> London, <hi>and the Militia, into the Hands of ſuch Perſons, as ſhould be recommended unto him by both Houſes of Parliament.</hi> The King ſeemed to comply herein, and by his Anſwer promiſed them, <hi>That the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia ſhould be put into ſuch Hands, as they ſhould approve of, or recommend to him</hi>; hereupon <hi>both Houſes</hi> nominated Perſons of the greateſt Honour, as fit for that Truſt. I ſhall give you the Names of ſome of them; The Earls of <hi>Holland, Rutland, Bedford, Bullingbrook, Salisbury, War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick, Pembrook, Leiceſter, Stamford, Eſſex, Clare, Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thumberland, Lincoln, Suffolk,</hi> &amp;c. Lords, <hi>Paget, North, Strange, Roberts, Grey</hi> of <hi>Werk, Chandois, Dacres, Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deville, Wharton, Spencer, Brook, Herbert, Fielding, Lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleton, Lord Keeper,</hi> &amp;c. Men Eminent in all Qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Honour and Sufficiency were recommended for ſeveral <hi>Counties,</hi> and the King was deſired to agree there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, <hi>as he had promiſed</hi>; upon his delaying to give a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactory Anſwer, they again Petition, ſetting forth, That <hi>nothing could enable them to ſuppreſs the</hi> Rebellion <hi>in</hi> Ireland, <hi>and ſecure</hi> England, <hi>but the granting of their Humble Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> which they find ſo abſolutely neceſſary for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the King and Common-wealth, that <hi>the Laws of God and Man injoin them to ſee it put in Execution.</hi> They followed him to <hi>Theobalds,</hi> and his ſeveral removes to <hi>York,</hi> but he having <hi>Abdicated</hi> the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and being deaf <hi>to all their Importunities,</hi> they declared, <hi>That there had been of late a moſt deſperate Deſign upon the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, which they had juſt cauſe to believe was an effect of the</hi> Bloody Councels <hi>of</hi> Papiſts, <hi>and other evil</hi> affected Perſons, <hi>who had already raiſed a</hi> Rebellion <hi>in</hi> Ireland, <hi>and by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of many Diſcoveries, They could not but fear they would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, not only to ſtir up the like</hi> Rebellion <hi>and</hi> Inſurrection <hi>in
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:57844:25"/>
this Kingdom,</hi> but alſo to back them with <hi>Forces from A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad</hi>; and thereupon, <hi>both Houſes</hi> made an <hi>Ordinance</hi> for the <hi>ordering of the Militia of</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Wales, there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing an urgent and inevitable neceſſity for putting His Majeſties Subjects in a poſture of Defence for the Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard of both His Majeſty and his People; and they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, <hi>That in this Caſe of extream danger, and of His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Refuſal, the Ordinance agreed to by both Houſes for the Militia, doth oblige the People, and</hi> ought to be obeyed <hi>by the Fundamental Laws of this Kingdom.</hi> They further a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout that time Reſolved, <hi>That the King's Abſence ſo far re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote from his Parliament, was not only an</hi> Obſtruction, <hi>but might be a</hi> Deſtruction <hi>to the Affairs of</hi> Ireland.</p>
                  <p>Theſe (and many other) Reaſons that may, with the greateſt eaſe be given, 'tis notoriouſly manifeſt, That King <hi>Charles</hi> began, and carryed on, that <hi>Bloody Civil War</hi> againſt his poor Subjects without the <hi>leaſt Colour of Reaſon and Juſtice,</hi> for which wicked Acts, God juſtly ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered him to <hi>be brought to that ſhameful and untimely End.</hi> This King ſtuddying and endeavouring by all ways imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as he lived without the Love, ſo he died without the Lamentation of moſt People, but thoſe Villains, that had been large inſtruments, in bringing him, and his People, into that miſerable War and Diviſion.</p>
                  <p n="25">25. That after he had taken God to Witneſs of his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs to Treat at <hi>Uxbridge</hi> with the <hi>Parliament</hi> for avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Blood-ſhed (as pretended) he took the advantage of a Miſt, the fitteſt Weather for <hi>Deceit</hi> and <hi>Treachery,</hi> and followed at the Heels, thoſe <hi>Meſſengers</hi> of <hi>Peace,</hi> with a Train of <hi>Covert War,</hi> and with a Bloody ſurpriſe falls on the Parliaments ſecure Forces, which lay Quartering at <hi>Brentford,</hi> in the thoughts and expectation of a Treaty.</p>
                  <p>He gives his Reaſon why he ſeemed for <hi>Peace,</hi> in a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to his Queen, which was, That She muſt know as a certain <hi>Truth,</hi> That all, <hi>even his Party, are ſtrongly impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:57844:26"/>
for a Peace, which oblidged him ſo much the more to ſhew on all occaſions his Intentions to Peace; but tells her,</hi> no dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of Death ſhall make him do any thing unworthy of her Love. An excellent Reſolution no doubt, for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> made to his <hi>Popiſh Queen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>At the very inſtant of this <hi>Treaty,</hi> which was in 1644. the King uſed all imaginable meams to bring not only <hi>Foreign Forces,</hi> but the <hi>Iriſh Cut Throats,</hi> againſt the <hi>Parliament.</hi> To clear up this point, and alſo to ſhew how inſincere he was in his <hi>pretended Intentions of Peace,</hi> I will briefly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent his <hi>Underhand Tranſactions,</hi> as well with <hi>Foreign Princes,</hi> as thoſe <hi>Rebels</hi>; and in the firſt place, I ſhall take notice of ſome paſſages between <hi>Him</hi> and the <hi>Queen,</hi> in relation to this, and other Treaties.</p>
                  <p>In a Letter to <hi>Her</hi> of <hi>January</hi> 9<hi>th.</hi> 1644. he Writes thus: The <hi>Scots</hi> Commiſſioners have ſent to me to ſend a <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion</hi> to their General Aſſembly, <hi>Which I am reſolved not to do,</hi> but to the end of <hi>making ſome uſe of this occaſion,</hi> by ſending an honeſt Man to <hi>London,</hi> and that I may have the more time for a handſome Negative, I have demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Paſport for <hi>Phil. Warwick,</hi> by whom to return my Anſwer.</p>
                  <p>At another time the ſame Month <hi>He</hi> tells <hi>Her,</hi> That <hi>as for my calling thoſe a</hi> 
                     <note n="*" place="margin">He had agree to Treat with them as a Parliament, the <hi>Queen</hi> upbraided him for ſo doing, and he thus vindicates him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</note> 
                     <hi>Parliament, if there had been but</hi> Two <hi>of my Opinion, I had not done it; the calling did no ways acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge them to be a Parliament, upon which condition and conſtruction I did it, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly it is regiſtred in the Council Books.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Nothing is more evident, than that the King was ſteered by the <hi>Queen's Council,</hi> in the manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this <hi>Uxbridge</hi> Treaty, and that which is call'd the Church of <hi>England [<hi>The Biſhops</hi>]</hi> was greatly her care. By Letter in <hi>January</hi> 1644. before the beginning of that <hi>Treaty, She inſtructs him not to abandon thoſe who have ſerved
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:57844:26"/>
him, leſt they forſake him in his need; that</hi> She <hi>hopes he will have a care of her, and her Religion; that in Her Majeſties Opinion,</hi> Religion ſhould be the laſt thing upon which he ſhould Treat; <hi>for if he do agree upon ſtrickneſs againſt the Catholicks, it would diſcourage them to ſerve him, and if after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards there ſhould be no Peace, he could never expect ſuccours from</hi> Ireland, <hi>or any other</hi> Catholick Prince.</p>
                  <p>In another of her Letters, we find her writing thus: <hi>January</hi> 17. 1644. <hi>It comforts me much to ſee the Treaty ſhall be at</hi> Uxbridge.— <hi>I received Yeſterday Letters from the Duke of</hi> Lorrain, <hi>who ſends me word, if his ſervice be agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to you, he will bring</hi> 10000 <hi>Men.— Above all, have a care not to abandon thoſe who have ſerved you, as well the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, as the poor Catholicks.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By the King's Letters to the Queen in <hi>February,</hi> when the Treaty at <hi>Uxbridge</hi> was depending, <hi>He Stiles the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> Unreaſonable, Stubborn, Perfidious Rebels, preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes her to haſten all poſſible Aſſiſtance to him, particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that of the Duke of <hi>Lorrain.</hi> He tells her, That the <hi>limitted days</hi> for treating are now almoſt expired, without the leaſt Agreement upon any one Article, wherefore I fend for enlargement of days, <hi>That the whole Treaty may be laid open to the whole World,</hi> and <hi>I aſſure thee, thou needſt not doubt the Iſſue of this Treaty</hi>; for my <hi>Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners</hi> are ſo well choſen, (though I ſay it) that they will neither be Threatned nor Diſputed from the Grounds I have given them, which <hi>(upon my Word) Is according to the little Note thou ſo well remembers.</hi>—Be confident, that in making Peace, I ſhall ever ſhew my <hi>Conſtancy in adhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Biſhops, and all our Friends,</hi> (which could be meant of no other than the Catholicks; for the Queen in her Letter before mentioned, had given him Charge of both together) and not forget to put a ſhort Period to this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual Parliament.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:57844:27"/>We find in another Letter, Dated the 5<hi>th.</hi> of <hi>March,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing himſelf in theſe Words: <hi>I have thought of one means more to furniſh Thee with my aſſiſtance, than hitherto thou haſt had</hi>; it is, <hi>That I give Thee power to promiſe in my Name, that I will</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">If this were ſo good a King, Why ſo much clamour againſt King <hi>James</hi> the II. for deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame thing.</note> 
                     <hi>take away all the Penal Laws againſt the Roman Catholicks in</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, as ſoon as God ſhall enable me to do it.</p>
                  <p>In relation to <hi>Ireland,</hi> he wrote to the Marqueſs of <hi>Ormond</hi> to this Effect, <hi>Jan.</hi> 7.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Rebells</hi> here have agreed to <hi>Treat, and moſt aſſured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly one of the firſt</hi> and chiefeſt <hi>Articles</hi> they will inſiſt on, will be, <hi>To continue the</hi> Iriſh <hi>War,</hi> which is a <hi>Point not popular for me to break on,</hi> of which you are to make a double uſe; Firſt, <hi>To haſten with all poſſible diligence the Peace there,</hi> the timely concluſion of which will take off that Inconvenience, which otherwiſe I may be ſubject to, by the Refufal of that Article upon any other Reaſon; <hi>Secondly,</hi> By dexterous conveying to the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> the danger there may be of their <hi>Total Excluſion from thoſe Favours I intend them,</hi> in caſe the <hi>Rebells</hi> here clap up a Peace.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Not doubting of a Peace,</hi> I muſt again remember you, <hi>to preſs the Iriſh</hi> for their ſpeedy Aſſiſtance to Me here, and their Friends in <hi>Scotland.— I deſire</hi> that the <hi>Iriſh</hi> would ſend as great a Body as they can, to Land about <hi>Cumber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, which will put thoſe</hi> Northern <hi>Counties in a brave Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Upon the 14<hi>th. January,</hi> he Writes thus to the <hi>Queen:</hi> As for the <hi>Peace</hi> of <hi>Ireland,</hi> to ſhew <hi>Thee</hi> the <hi>Care</hi> I have had of it, and <hi>Fruits</hi> I hope to receive from it, I have ſent <hi>Thee</hi> the laſt Diſpatches, I have ſent concerning it.— <hi>For God's ſake, let none know the particulars of my Diſpatches.</hi> [<hi>Some ſecret piece of Villany againſt his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Subjects no Doubt, that he was ſo</hi> affraid <hi>of having it</hi> Diſcovered.]</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:57844:27"/>Another Letter to <hi>Her</hi> of the 20<hi>th.</hi> of <hi>March,</hi> hath this Expreſſion: <hi>I find that thou much miſtakes me concerning</hi> Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>I deſire nothing more than a Peace there, and ever for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid thy Commerce there.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By another Lettter, he commanded <hi>Ormond</hi> to <hi>Diſpatch the</hi> Iriſh <hi>Peace out of hand,</hi> and thereby promiſes, that the <hi>Penal Laws,</hi> againſt the Roman Catholicks, <hi>Shall not be put in Execution:</hi> The <hi>Peace</hi> being made, and that when the <hi>Iriſh</hi> give him that Aſſiſtance which they have promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for the ſuppreſſion of this <hi>Rebellion,</hi> then he would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to the Repeal of them by a Law; and Concludes, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commending to him again, the ſpeedy diſpatch of the Peace of</hi> Ireland.</p>
                  <p>Another Letter to <hi>Ormond,</hi> upon the 27<hi>th.</hi> of <hi>February</hi> 1644. was, <hi>That he thought himſelf bound in Conſcience, not to loſe that aſſiſtance which he might hope from his</hi> Iriſh Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, <hi>for ſuch ſcruples as in a leſs preſſing condition might rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably be ſtruck at by him, and therefore Commanded him to conclude a Peace with the</hi> Iriſh whatever it coſt; <hi>ſo that his Proteſtant Subjects there might be ſecured, and his Regal Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority preſerved.— If the preſent taking away the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> againſt Papiſts will do it</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>I ſhall not think it a hard Bargin, ſo that freely and vigourouſly they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage themſelves in my Aſſiſtance againſt my</hi> Rebells <hi>of</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Scotland, <hi>for which no Conditions can be too hard, not being againſt Conſcience or Honour.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By another Letter to the Marqueſs of <hi>Ormond,</hi> in the ſame Month, he Writes thus: <hi>Now again, I cannot but men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the neceſſity of haſtning the</hi> Iriſh Peace, <hi>for which, I hope, you are already furniſhed by Me, with Materials ſufficient.</hi> But in caſe (againſt all Expectation and Reaſon) <hi>Peace cannot be had upon thoſe Terms, you muſt not by any means fall to a New Rupture with them, but continue the Ceſſation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:57844:28"/>
                     <note n="⸫" place="margin">There was at this time high Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion in <hi>London,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians and Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants; therefore to ruin both, by fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting miſunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings between them, the Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants are to be <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joled</hi>; a thing wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy remembrance in all times.</note> He wrote to the Duke of <hi>Richmond,</hi> one of his <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners</hi> for the <hi>Uxbridge Treaty, To re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member to</hi> Cajole <hi>well the Independants and the Scots</hi>; nay, he inſtructed Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary <hi>Nicholas</hi> to bribe the <hi>Commiſſioners</hi> for the <hi>Parliament,</hi> with the promiſe of <hi>Security, Rewards and Places.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now upon the whole matter, let any impartial and unbyaſſed Perſon tell me, whether he doth not in his Conſcience believe, that the <hi>Parliament</hi> were far more ſincere in making an <hi>Honourable Peace</hi> for poor <hi>England,</hi> than this apparently, <hi>Falſe, Popiſh,</hi> and <hi>tricking King,</hi> whom the wicked part of Mankind ſo <hi>madly cry up for a Martyr.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="26">26. That for many Reaſons it was concluded, That King <hi>Charles</hi> had no ſmall ſhare in the abominable Act of <hi>Poyſoning</hi> his own Father, King <hi>James</hi> I. and that <hi>Good Man, Prince</hi> Henry, <hi>his Son.</hi> It being very plain, divers <hi>Parliaments</hi> were but ſhort lived; if they did but mutter, that an Enquiry ſhould be made of their <hi>untimely Ends,</hi> and that the Duke of <hi>Buckingham</hi> was protected for that, and other <hi>Villanies.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And that I may Demonſtrate to the World more fully than I have already done in the 6<hi>th. Articles,</hi> That King <hi>Charles</hi> I. did moſt Diſhonourably and Perfidiouſly <hi>Betray the poor Proteſtants</hi> of the Iſle of <hi>Rhee</hi> and <hi>Rochel.</hi> I ſhall produce Copies of two of his Letters to them.</p>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:57844:28"/>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div n="1" type="letter">
                              <head>LETTER I.</head>
                              <head>The King of <hi>England</hi>'s Letter, Directed to the <hi>Mayor, Sheriffs, Peers, Burghers,</hi> and Inhabitants of the City of <hi>Rochell,</hi> dated 19<hi>th.</hi> of <hi>May,</hi> Old Stile 1628.</head>
                              <opener>
                                 <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
                              </opener>
                              <p>BE not Diſcomforted, though my Fleet be return'd, <hi>hold out unto the laſt,</hi> for I am reſolved, that <hi>all my Fleet ſhall Periſh,</hi> rather than you ſhall not be <hi>Relieved,</hi> and to this end I have Countermanded it, and have ſent Ships to make them change their Deſign, that they had taken to come back: I ſhall <hi>ſhortly ſend you ſome number of Ships to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inforce it,</hi> and with the help of <hi>God,</hi> the Succeſs will be hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py for that <hi>Deliverance.</hi>
                              </p>
                              <closer>
                                 <signed>
                                    <hi>Your Good Friend,</hi> CHARLES <hi>R.</hi>
                                 </signed>
                              </closer>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>And on the 21<hi>ſt.</hi> in the Morning, there came to <hi>Rochell</hi> from <hi>England,</hi> a Soldier bringing another Letter from the <hi>King,</hi> Dated 27<hi>th.</hi> of <hi>May</hi> Old Stile, ſealed with the Arms of <hi>England,</hi> which was as followeth:</p>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div n="2" type="letter">
                              <opener>
                                 <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
                              </opener>
                              <p>I <hi>Have</hi> been troubled to here <hi>that my Fleet was upon the Point of</hi> Returning, <hi>without</hi> Anſwering my Commands, <hi>which were to force the Entry of your Proviſions, whatever
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:57844:29"/>
came of it, and have given it new</hi> Orders to Return into your Road, <hi>and not</hi> ſtir <hi>untill it hath</hi> relieved you with Victuals, <hi>or that I have ſent them an Additional ſtrength, for which I have cauſed Men to work with all</hi> Diligence; Be aſſured that I will never Abandon you, <hi>and that I will imploy</hi> all the Force <hi>of my</hi> Kingdom for your Deliverance, <hi>untill it pleaſe</hi> God <hi>to bleſs</hi> Me <hi>with giving</hi> you <hi>an aſſured</hi> Peace.</p>
                              <closer>
                                 <dateline>
                                    <hi>Given at Our Palace at</hi> Weſtm.
<date>
                                       <hi>May</hi> 27, 1628.
<hi>Old Stile.</hi>
                                    </date>
                                 </dateline>
                                 <salute>GENTLEMEN,</salute>
                                 <signed>Your Good Friend, <hi>CHARLES</hi> R.</signed>
                              </closer>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>Whoſoever ſhall carefully Read, and Conſider theſe two Letters, and the <hi>Sollemn Declarations</hi> there, and obſerve how contrary to his <hi>Royal Word,</hi> he Sacrificed theſe <hi>Poor Proteſtants,</hi> will have cauſe to harbour the worſt of thoughts of this King, and to bluſh at the horrid <hi>Impudence</hi> and <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety</hi> of thoſe <hi>Wicked Wretches,</hi> that would make a <hi>Saint</hi> and a <hi>Martyr</hi> of him. And to demonſtrate this <hi>Treachery,</hi> I ſhall incert a Copy of the <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> made by one of the Deputies of the <hi>City</hi> of <hi>Rochel,</hi> becauſe it will very much illuſtrate the Subject, and be as an <hi>Eternal mark of Infamy to the Memory of that Prince,</hi> and deſerves to be <hi>Engraven</hi> on <hi>Braſs,</hi> and Wrote on <hi>Marble,</hi> that ſo the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance</hi> of it may never be loſt; it is as followeth.</p>
                  <div type="journal_entry">
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:57844:29"/>
                     <head>A Copy of the <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> of the Sieur <hi>Vincent,</hi> to the King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> drawn out of his own Journals.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>SIR,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>
                        <hi>THE</hi> Grief <hi>which obliges us to fill the Ears of Your Majeſty with our</hi> Cries, <hi>and to Reiterate them ſo often, ought to be extream to the laſt</hi> Degree. <hi>Behold us now, Sir, proſtrate at your Feet, to Waſh them with</hi> our Tears, <hi>and God Almighty Grant, that we do not in a little time, come to</hi> Sigh <hi>out our</hi> laſt Breath, <hi>with the News of the</hi> Deſolation <hi>of our</hi> City. <hi>We know not how, Sir, to conceal it from</hi> You, <hi>the Sence we have of Her being at Her</hi> laſt Gaſp, <hi>puts us into Deſpair</hi>; ſeeing the Succours which Your Majeſty hath made us hope would be ready, <hi>hath been deferred from</hi> day to day for many Weeks together.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>SIR, the City of</hi> Rochell <hi>did by us beg of</hi> You, <hi>with all the Humility they were capable of Expreſſing, to</hi> receive them <hi>into your</hi> Protection, and You as Solemnly agreed to it; <hi>ſince they have had at divers times,</hi> all the Aſſurances poſſible, <hi>as well from your</hi> own Month, <hi>as</hi> under the Hand of Your Majeſty, <hi>that you would never</hi> abandon them: <hi>Whereupon by a</hi> Miracle of Conſtancy, <hi>they have held our hitherto firm a</hi> whole Year, <hi>contending with the Horrours of a moſt gaſtly</hi> Famine, <hi>that thereby they might give</hi> Your Majeſty, <hi>full leiſure to ſend them the Succours You were graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly pleaſed to</hi> promiſe them; <hi>and thus conſtant and unſhaken were</hi> they, <hi>even when all</hi> Europe, <hi>believed they ought to have deſpaired, in that after they had</hi> Relief, <hi>as they</hi> thought ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral days <hi>in</hi> their ſight, it returned without effecting, <hi>or</hi> attempting <hi>any thing. And though</hi> our Enemies <hi>have from
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:57844:30"/>
thence taken occaſion to make them divers</hi> Overtures <hi>of</hi> Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation, <hi>which their</hi> extream Neceſſities <hi>ſeemed to Counſel them to</hi> hearken unto; <hi>yet they choſe rather to run the</hi> Hazzard <hi>of their utter</hi> Deſtruction, <hi>then to be wanting in the leaſt to the</hi> Promiſes <hi>we had</hi> Sworn <hi>for them to</hi> Your Majeſty, <hi>or to ſhew they had the leaſt Diffidence of your</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>After all this,</hi> Sir, <hi>ſhall it be</hi> Recorded <hi>in the Hiſtory of</hi> Your Reign; <hi>That they</hi> periſhed in your Hands <hi>without having reaped any other</hi> Fruit <hi>of the Good Will Your</hi> Majeſty <hi>hath profeſſed</hi> towards them, <hi>and of the Aſſurance they have therein relied upon; then the rendring them irrecountable to their King, from whom otherwiſe they might have hoped to have found Grace and Favour!</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Pardon,</hi> Sir, <hi>this, from a People who</hi> ſee themſelves <hi>upon the very</hi> Threſhold <hi>of their Sepulchers, if they cannot avoid</hi> Sighs <hi>which may ſeem undecent in your</hi> Royal Preſence. <hi>It is common for thoſe that are</hi> near their End, <hi>to finiſh their</hi> Lives <hi>with</hi> Groans. <hi>In the</hi> Name of God, <hi>Sir, ſo long as there remains any</hi> Breath in us, <hi>and before we do quite</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, <hi>command your</hi> Succours <hi>to haſten to our Aſſiſtance; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided that diligence be yet uſed, we will remain</hi> Caution <hi>to Your Majeſty with the</hi> Peril <hi>of our</hi> Heads, <hi>that they will ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive time enough to</hi> ſave us. <hi>As to the Impoſſibilities that ſome may be willing to find in it, permit us to tell You freely,</hi> Sir, <hi>That thoſe are only founded, either in their fear, or their very little Affection for us; and that beſides the Report which ſome Perſons unſuſpected, have made to</hi> Your Majeſty, <hi>we beſeech You, be You judge, whether our</hi> City, <hi>which is within fight of the</hi> Digne <hi>and</hi> Palliſade, <hi>and carriage of her Cannon, would ſend time after time to implore</hi> Your Aſſiſtance, <hi>if they thought it would be unprofitable to them, and if having every day offers of Capitulation upon advantagious Conditions, if they would hearken to it for themſelves alone, they would be ſo imprudent to neglect the opportunity. But we are ready if
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:57844:30"/>
it ſhall pleaſe Your Majeſty to permit it, to take upon us the firſt Riſques and Hazzards of the Execution, to the end that we may be juſtified to all the World in the ſincerity of our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding; and that it may not be imputed to us, that we are prodigal of the Blood of Your Majeſties Subjects to ill purpoſe, to be ſparing of our own: No,</hi> Sir, <hi>there is no ſuch impoſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity as</hi> what ſome would pretend.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The only Cauſe of our Fears, comes from the</hi> ſlowneſs and continual neglects <hi>from one Day to another, and one Week to another, which makes our hopes Recoil. After the Return of your Fleet, we comforted our ſelves with the</hi> Promiſe <hi>that was made us by</hi> Your Majeſty, <hi>That it ſhould depart again within</hi> fifteen days; <hi>but when after</hi> twenty <hi>were</hi> paſt, <hi>there were added</hi> fourteen <hi>more to them: And after that, we found divers other</hi> neglectful Diſappointments, <hi>that have now</hi> taken up two Months compleat; <hi>Good God,</hi> Sir, How long has that time ſeemed to thoſe miſerable Wretches that have not Bread! <hi>We know very well the good Inclinations Your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty hath for our Weal; as alſo we have had moſt certain Proofs of the Duke of</hi> Buckingham, <hi>your high Admiral, his paſſionate applying himſelf for us, as alſo the ſame of the Lords of your Council; but ſhall we not be excuſable, if ſeeing the Effects thereof croſſed, by all theſe Delays? We entertain Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies, that Your Majeſty is not</hi> well ſerved, <hi>and that there is ſome ſecret Hand, which clandeſtingly obſtructs, that which the Zeal of others endeavours to advance. It is ordinary for Men in miſery to be ſuſpicious, and poſſibly here we are not injuriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo; indeed we do not know any Perſon on whom to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine our Diffidence, nor have we any intention to call to mind any thing that is paſt; may that,</hi> Sir, <hi>remain</hi> buried <hi>in Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Oblivion, and for the future at leaſt, let thoſe to whom Your Majeſty ſhall give your Commands, anſwer ſo well your kindneſs to us, with their Affection and Diligence, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any</hi> farther delay, <hi>your Fleet may</hi> put to Sea, <hi>and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver us yet out of the</hi> Cruel Arms <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Death<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ words">
                           <desc>〈◊…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="50" facs="tcp:57844:31"/>
                        <hi>If,</hi> Sir, <hi>upon this occaſion, you will pleaſe to</hi> Diſcern <hi>thoſe who ſerve you</hi> Faithfully, <hi>from other Men (if there be any ſuch) let Your</hi> Majeſty <hi>be pleaſed to hold it indubitable, that all thoſe who under any pretext whatſoever, ſhall Counſel the leaſt Delayings, do it from an ill Intention, there being none can pretend ignorance of the</hi> dreadful Neceſſities <hi>to which our</hi> City is reduced, <hi>and that</hi> one ſingle days <hi>delay more, may be the cauſe of</hi> its ruine. <hi>Have therefore</hi> ſome conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it, we beſeech You, <hi>by the</hi> Tears <hi>and pitiful</hi> Cries <hi>of more than</hi> Twelve Thouſand poor languiſhing Souls, <hi>whom</hi> Hunger devours, <hi>and who are</hi> all <hi>ready to</hi> Periſh, <hi>by the Intereſt of above a</hi> Million <hi>of others, who without doubt will</hi> ſee themſelves <hi>Buried under our</hi> Ruins, <hi>and who will find the</hi> Knife <hi>at their</hi> Throats, <hi>the very next day after</hi> we are loſt.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>By the Glory of your</hi> Scepter, <hi>under the</hi> Sanctuary <hi>of which we are come to put our ſelves, and which it hath pleaſed you to tender us for our Security</hi>; by the Magnificent Title of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender of the Faith, <hi>which obligeth Your Majeſty to relieve thoſe that are Oppreſſed for that very Reaſon; in ſhort,</hi> by the Faith <hi>and</hi> Word <hi>of a</hi> King, <hi>which it hath pleaſed</hi> You <hi>of your Grace to</hi> Engage <hi>us, permit not, Sir,</hi> our Innocent Blood <hi>to</hi> reflect <hi>upon</hi> your Crown, <hi>to</hi> ſtain it to Ages that ſhall ſucceed us, <hi>and at preſent to</hi> cry againſt Your Majeſty before God and Man.</p>
                     <p>This is that, <hi>Sir, which our Conſciences, and the Duty we owe to our Afflicted Fellow Citizens, oblige us to come and repreſent a new to Your Majeſty, in whoſe</hi> Charity, Magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimity, Piety, <hi>and</hi> inviolable Fidelity, <hi>we hawe ſuch Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, That we aſſure our ſelves, God will take this in good part, and in convenient Conſideration: And ſince that all our Supplications tend to make You be pleaſed, to cauſe your Fleet to ſet Sail with all poſſible Diligence, and to afford your Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence at</hi> Portſmouth, <hi>where it is ſo abſolutely neceſſary, that without it, we can ſcarce hope for any ſucceſs.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="51" facs="tcp:57844:31"/>
                        <hi>We therefore do in all Humility ſupplicate</hi> Your Majeſty, <hi>immediately to put in Execution the Reſolution you have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of going thither; and here,</hi> Sir, we fall upon our Knees before Your Majeſty, <hi>with moſt Ardent Prayer to God, that it will pleaſe him to make us find more and more</hi> Favour <hi>in your</hi> Sight, <hi>that even we, who now</hi> Supplicate You, <hi>may come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to</hi> render <hi>to You, our moſt humble and grateful</hi> Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgments, <hi>as to</hi> our Great Deliverer, <hi>from</hi> whom, <hi>next to God, we ſhall hold our</hi> Eſtates, Honours <hi>and</hi> Lives, <hi>and the memory of ſo ſignal a Deliverance, we may leave to our Children, to the end that they may Celebrate it after us.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Yet, <hi>all theſe Sufferings,</hi> and the <hi>lamentable Eſtate</hi> of the <hi>Rochellers,</hi> nor the ſad and <hi>preſſing Remonſtrance</hi> of their <hi>Deputies</hi> (enough to <hi>melt</hi> the <hi>Heart</hi> of any <hi>One,</hi> but a <hi>Cruel faithleſs Tyrant</hi>) were Efficatious enough to oblige that <hi>Wicked Court,</hi> to let this <hi>third Fleet</hi> ſet ſail before <hi>September</hi> following, under the Command of the Earl of <hi>Lindſey,</hi> who arrived before <hi>Rochell</hi> towards the latter end of the ſaid Month; but inſtead of ſuccouring the <hi>City,</hi> breaking the <hi>Digue,</hi> and opening the Paſſage, to get in <hi>Proviſions,</hi> which the King had made them to expect, and which they had already almoſt ſwallowed in their hopes. That Commander had <hi>ſet on Shore</hi> the Lord <hi>Mountague,</hi> (unknown to the Deputies that were on Board, and to the Duke of <hi>Soubize</hi>) who went ſtraight to the <hi>French</hi> King's Camp, where after ſome Conferences with the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal, with whom (as was then reported) he had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certed the <hi>Delivery</hi> of the <hi>City</hi> to the King, which was very far from giving it any Succour. He went Poſt for <hi>England,</hi> to give an Account of it to his Maſter. After the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Fleet had been a Month in the Road without doing <hi>any thing,</hi> and without ſending the <hi>Beſieged Army</hi> any manner of Victuals, which were on Board: Then the poor <hi>Rochellers,</hi> who were not able to hold <hi>out no longer,</hi> ſaw plainly how they were Abuſed and Betrayed; ſo
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:57844:32"/>
hereupon they reſolved (no more to expect the <hi>Illuſory Succours</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and the vain Hopes of aſſiſtance from them, to deliver up the City; and whilſt the Lord <hi>Montague</hi> was going for <hi>England,</hi> and to return to the <hi>French</hi> King with the Effects of his Negotiation, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to throw themſelves into the Arms of the King, their Sovereign, in hopes after all, by their Repentance for their ſo long Obſtinancy, to obtain his Grace and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour.</p>
                     <p>And about the end of <hi>October,</hi> their Agreement was made among themſelves, and Signed: And the firſt of <hi>November,</hi> the King made Entrance into <hi>Rochell,</hi> where he found the Inhabitants more like <hi>Skeletons,</hi> than <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Women.</hi> And this King had more compaſſion than the <hi>hard-hearted Oppreſſor of</hi> England, for he was ſo ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly touched with that ſad Sight, that he <hi>could not refrain letting fall ſome Tears.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>On the 5th. of <hi>November,</hi> the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Fleet, after ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been a Month and ſix days in the Road, and ſeen from thence the Reductien of <hi>Rochell</hi> to the Obedience of the King, ſet ſail, carrying a long with them a great par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>French,</hi> as well as Victuals, they had brought from <hi>England.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="27">27. That was an Exorbitant and Outragious <hi>T</hi>— up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the People of <hi>Scotland,</hi> as appears in many particulars; to recount ſome of them Briefly,</p>
                     <p n="1">1. In overturning their <hi>Church Government,</hi> Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by many Acts of Parliament, and obtruding upon them <hi>Laud</hi>'s <hi>Liturgy,</hi> and <hi>Popiſh Ceremonies,</hi> after that wicked Biſhop had ſent his <hi>Liturgy</hi> to <hi>Rome</hi> to be approved there.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. In denying them (the undoubted Right of all Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects) to Petition for Redreſs of their Grievances.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. In diſſolving their Synod and Parliament, Burning the Pacification made with them, by the <hi>Hangman's</hi> hands;
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:57844:32"/>
and Impriſoning the Lord's ſent by them, to Petitiom him to perform his Sollemn Promiſes, and Redreſs their Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. In levying <hi>Doctrines</hi> againſt them, and raiſing a <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil War,</hi> to juſtify himſelf in the Violation of their <hi>Laws.</hi> A <hi>Civil War</hi> it was, ſaid the Great Lord <hi>Digby,</hi> ſeeing we are of the ſame <hi>Religion,</hi> and under the ſame King. And</p>
                     <p n="5">5. In attempting to make uſe of the <hi>Love and Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> to Enſlave and Ruin the <hi>Scotiſh</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>It is not improper here to obſerve.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="1">1. That the <hi>Scotiſh</hi> Covenant was not a new <hi>Invention or Innovation,</hi> but Eſtabliſhed by the Law of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and taken by King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt, ſeventy Years before King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second took it.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. That <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Clergymen</hi> in Conjunction with Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, abetted and aſſiſted this <hi>T</hi>— in the violation of the <hi>Laws,</hi> when the Bulk of the <hi>Nobility, Gentry,</hi> and <hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of</hi> England, appeared undauntedly in Defence of the Laws and Liberties of the Kingdom.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. That <hi>Popery</hi> hath greatly ſpred in <hi>Scotland</hi> ever ſince <hi>Laud</hi>'s Superſtition was introduced here, the Number of Papiſts not exceeding 600. And therefore <hi>Presbetery</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now reſtored by a Law, it may be reaſonably hoped, that it will reduce many who have been deluded into that <hi>Idolatry.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="4">4. That <hi>Princes</hi> are not always to truſt to the <hi>Inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> and <hi>Suggeſtions</hi> of <hi>Scotiſh</hi> Biſhops; ſeeing that when they inſtigated King <hi>Charles</hi> I. <hi>to Diſſolve the Synod and Parliament,</hi> he was ſeduced by them into a belief. That the <hi>Scotiſh Covenanteers</hi> were a contemptible Number, and their Party in <hi>Scotland</hi> was ſufficient to deal with them.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. That the <hi>Scots</hi> were not <hi>Rebells</hi> in taking Arms to Aſſert their <hi>Rights,</hi> and Vindicate the <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Liberties</hi> of their <hi>Countrey.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="54" facs="tcp:57844:33"/>That the horrid Impoſition of <hi>Laud</hi>'s <hi>Popiſh Liturgy,</hi> did occaſion the Troubles of <hi>Scotland,</hi> is very manifeſt from Dr. <hi>Burnet's</hi> (now Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury</hi>) his Memoirs of Duke <hi>Hamilton,</hi> for he ſaith, <hi>Page</hi> 30. <hi>The Liturgy had ſome Alterations from the</hi> Engliſh, <hi>which made it more</hi> Invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious <hi>and leſs</hi> Satisfactory.— <hi>The</hi> Impoſing <hi>it, really</hi> va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried <hi>from their former Practices and Conſtitutions.</hi>— Pag. 33. <hi>The Lords Petition'd, complaining againſt the</hi> Liturgy, <hi>and Book of Canons</hi>; offering <hi>under the higheſt Penalties, to</hi> prove <hi>they</hi> contain'd things <hi>both</hi> contrary <hi>to</hi> Religion, <hi>and the</hi> Laws <hi>of the</hi> Land, pag. 36. <hi>The Earls of</hi> Traquaire <hi>and</hi> Roxbourgh, <hi>by</hi> Letter <hi>to the King, adviſed him to ſecure the People of that which they ſo much apprehended, the fear of</hi> Innovation of Religion, <hi>ſaying, that they found</hi> few <hi>or</hi> none <hi>well</hi> ſatisfied, pag. 33. <hi>The Earl of</hi> Traquaire <hi>went to</hi> Court, <hi>and gave Account, that all the</hi> Troubles <hi>were occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned by introducing the</hi> Liturgy; <hi>with which, ſcarce a</hi> Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber <hi>of</hi> Council <hi>(except Biſhops) was well</hi> ſatisfied: <hi>Neither were</hi> all theſe Cardinals <hi>for it, for the</hi> Archbiſhop <hi>of St.</hi> Andrews, <hi>from the</hi> beginning, <hi>had</hi> withſtood <hi>theſe</hi> Deſigns, <hi>and the</hi> Archbiſhop <hi>of</hi> Glaſcoe, <hi>was worſe</hi> pleaſed.</p>
                     <p>Their Commiſſioners in their <hi>Charge</hi> againſt <hi>Laud,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited to the <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> 1641. ſay, pag. 11. &amp;c. <hi>This</hi> Book <hi>inverteth the Order of the Communion in the Book of</hi> England, <hi>of the divers</hi> ſecret Reaſons of this Change, <hi>we mention one only: In joyning the Spiritual Praiſe and Thanksgiving, which is in the</hi> Book <hi>of</hi> England, <hi>pertinently after the Communion, with the Prayer of Conſecration before the Communion; and that under the Name of Memorial or Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, for no other ends, but that the Memorial and Sacrifice of Praiſe, mention'd in it, may be underſtood according to the Popiſh meaning</hi>; Bellarmin de Miſſa. Lib. 2. Chap. 21. <hi>not of the Spiritual Sacrifice, but of the Oblation of the Body of the Lord.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="55" facs="tcp:57844:33"/>
                        <hi>The Corporal Preſence of Chriſt's Body, is alſo to be found here; for the Words of the Maſs-Book, ſerving to this purpoſe, which are not to be</hi> found <hi>in the</hi> Book of <hi>England, are taken in here: Almighty God is inca<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>'d</hi>; That of his Almighty Goodneſs, he may vouchſafe ſo to Bleſs and ſanctifie with his Word and Spirit, theſe Gifts of Bread and Wine, that they be unto us the Body and Blood of Chriſt.— <hi>On the one part, the Expreſſions of the Book of</hi> England, <hi>at the delivery of the Elements:</hi> Of feeding on Chriſt by Faith, and of Eating and Drinking in Remembrance, that Chriſt died for thee, <hi>are utterly Deleted.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To prove that <hi>Laud</hi> did ſend this Liturgy to <hi>Rome</hi> to be <hi>approved of</hi>; Read a Book of Good Credit, Entitled, <hi>New Survey of the</hi> Weſt Indies, Wrote by a Reverend Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> Mr. <hi>Thomas Gage,</hi> Miniſter of <hi>Deal</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> 'tis in pag. 280. in the Folio Edition; He there tells you, <hi>That being a</hi> Fryar, <hi>he went to</hi> Rome <hi>with</hi> Letters <hi>of Recommendation to Cardinal</hi> Barbarini, <hi>the Pope's Nephew, Entituled,</hi> The Protector of <hi>England: That com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing acquainted with Father</hi> Fitzherbert, <hi>of the</hi> Engliſh Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge <hi>of</hi> Jeſuits, <hi>he highly praiſed Archbiſhop</hi> Laud, <hi>and ſaid, That he not long ſince</hi> ſent a Common Prayer Book (<hi>which he had</hi> compoſed for the Church of <hi>Scotland) to be</hi> firſt viewed and approved by the Pope and Cardinals; <hi>and, That they</hi> liked it very well for Proteſtants to be Trained up in a Form of Prayer and Service; <hi>yet the Cardinals (firſt giving him thanks for his Reſpect) ſent him word that they thought it was not</hi> fitting <hi>for</hi> Scotland; <hi>that Father</hi> Fitz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herbert <hi>told him, he was</hi> Witneſs of all, <hi>this being ſent for by the</hi> Cardinal <hi>to give him his Opinion about it, and of the Temper of the</hi> Scots. <hi>And that</hi> Laud <hi>hearing the</hi> Cenſure <hi>of the</hi> Cardinals, <hi>concerning his Intention and</hi> Form of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, <hi>to ingratiate himſelf the more in their Favour, Corrected ſome things in it, and made it more harſh and unreaſonable for that</hi> Nation.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="56" facs="tcp:57844:34"/>This <hi>Good Man,</hi> Mr. <hi>Gage,</hi> after he had here related the matter as above, expreſſes himſelf thus: This moſt <hi>True Relation</hi> of Archbiſhop <hi>Laud,</hi> I have oft ſpoke of in private Diſcourſe, and publickly in Preaching; and <hi>I could not in Conſcience omit it here, both to vindicate the juſt Cenſure of Death,</hi> whi<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h the Parliament gave againſt <hi>him,</hi> and to <hi>reprove</hi> the ungrounded <hi>Opinion</hi> and <hi>Error</hi> of ſome <hi>Ignorant Spirits,</hi> who have ſince his Death, highly <hi>exalted</hi> and <hi>cryed</hi> him up as a <hi>Martyr.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>'Tis worthy of Notice, that theſe <hi>Paſſages</hi> (making <hi>Laud</hi> to appear a <hi>great Villain</hi>) were by the means of <hi>Prieſt Craft</hi> left out of the Impreſſion in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Something like this of Mr. <hi>Gage,</hi> may be found in Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Burnet</hi>'s <hi>Memoirs of Duke</hi> Hamilton, <hi>fol.</hi> 83. he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, That in the Year 1638. one <hi>Abernethy,</hi> who from a <hi>Jeſuit,</hi> turned a zealous <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> ſpread a ſtory in <hi>Scotland</hi> which took wonderfully, of the Liturgy of that Kingdom, being ſent to <hi>Rome</hi> to ſome <hi>Cardinals</hi> to be <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed</hi> by them; and that Seignior <hi>Con,</hi> (the Popes Nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio to the Court of <hi>England</hi>) had ſhewed it to <hi>Abernethy</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> and though <hi>Con</hi> denied it afterwards, as is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, yet it doth not follow that what <hi>Abernethy</hi> aſſerts, was <hi>falſe,</hi> for it is well known, that <hi>Con</hi> being a <hi>Jeſuit,</hi> might <hi>Lye</hi> for the Holy Church.</p>
                     <p>If I had time, and that this Book would not be too large, I could produce very many more inſtances of King <hi>Charles</hi> his <hi>Tyrannical Oppreſſing</hi> his Subjects of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi> I ſhall end this Melancholly Story with the Heads of the many <hi>Articles</hi> of <hi>Miſ-government</hi> of that <hi>Prince,</hi> viz.</p>
                     <p>His taking <hi>Buckingham, Laud,</hi> and many more Evil Counſellors into the higheſt Favour, and being Govern'd by them.</p>
                     <p>His <hi>Popiſh Match,</hi> and <hi>Private Articles,</hi> in favour of <hi>Popery.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="57" facs="tcp:57844:34"/>His receiving a Letter from the <hi>Pope,</hi> and ſending him an <hi>Anſwer,</hi> calling him moſt <hi>Holy Father,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>His Pardoning 20 <hi>Popiſh Prieſts,</hi> &amp;c. purſuant to the <hi>Private Articles</hi> of <hi>Marriage.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>His moſt unchriſtian like <hi>Betraying the Iſle of Rhee</hi> and <hi>Rochell,</hi> a ſad Story.</p>
                     <p>His plucking up the <hi>Root</hi> of all <hi>Property,</hi> by taking the <hi>Peoples Goods</hi> againſt their <hi>Wills,</hi> and their <hi>Liberties</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Law.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>His giving <hi>Commiſſions</hi> to <hi>Try</hi> and <hi>Execute</hi> his Subject by <hi>Martial Law.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>His Raiſing <hi>Money</hi> by <hi>Loans</hi> againſt <hi>Law.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>His requiring <hi>London,</hi> and other places, to ſet <hi>out Ships</hi> for him at their <hi>own Charge.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>His <hi>Billotting Soldiers</hi> (many of which were <hi>Papiſts</hi>) on his poor Subjects.</p>
                     <p>His giving <hi>Commiſſions</hi> to ſeveral <hi>Lords</hi> to raiſe Money by way of <hi>Exciſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>His ordering his Treaſurer to pay 30000 <hi>l.</hi> to buy a large number of <hi>German</hi> Horſe, with Arms, both for <hi>Horſe</hi> and <hi>Foot,</hi> to be brought to <hi>England</hi> againſt the <hi>Parliament.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>His cauſing Mr. <hi>Chambars,</hi> a Merchant, to be fin'd 2000 <hi>l.</hi> for complaining of the hard Uſage the Merchants of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> had.</p>
                     <p>His oppreſſing, and Impriſoning all Ranks and Orders of Men <hi>Unjuſtly.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>His threatning the <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> if they would not give <hi>Money.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>His ſhameful betraying the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> and keeping the Charity of <hi>England</hi> from them.</p>
                     <p>His having, without doubt, a great Hand in the <hi>wicked</hi> Iriſh <hi>Rebellion.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>His large <hi>Demonſtration</hi> of his <hi>Piety,</hi> by ordering a <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration</hi> of <hi>Sports</hi> on the <hi>Lord's Day.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="58" facs="tcp:57844:35"/>His giving <hi>Wicked, Arbitrary,</hi> and <hi>Tyrannical Orders, Inſtructions</hi> and <hi>Commiſſions</hi> to the Earl of <hi>Strafford,</hi> Lord <hi>Lieutenant</hi> of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and endeavoured to ſave him from the Parliaments <hi>Juſt</hi> and neceſſary <hi>Proſecution.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>His ſuffering the Biſhops, <hi>Gauden</hi> and <hi>Duppa,</hi> to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a lying Book, call'd, <hi>Eicon Baſilice,</hi> and to put it out in his Name, the better to juſtify his evil Actions againſt his People.</p>
                     <p>His cauſing the <hi>Star-Chamber</hi> and <hi>High Commiſſion</hi> Courts to be made uſe of, to the great Grievance of the People of <hi>England.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>His falſely charging with <hi>Treaſon,</hi> and unjuſtly impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning the Lord <hi>Mandevil,</hi> Mr. <hi>Hollis,</hi> Mr. <hi>Strode,</hi> and many others, and would produce <hi>no Witneſs</hi> againſt them.</p>
                     <p>His <hi>Tempting</hi> and <hi>Incouraging</hi> his <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Iriſh</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to come and <hi>Deſtroy</hi> the <hi>Parliament.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>His dealing moſt <hi>Baſely</hi> and <hi>Treacherouſly</hi> with the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> whilſt <hi>Treating</hi> at <hi>Uxbridge.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>His having a hand in the untimely <hi>Deaths of King</hi> James the Firſt, and Prince <hi>Henry.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>His being an <hi>Exorbitant</hi> and <hi>Outragious Tyrant</hi> upon the People of <hi>England.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:57844:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Murder will Out:</hi> OR, THE KING'S LETTER, JUSTIFYING THE MARQUESS of <hi>ANTRIM,</hi> And declaring, That what he did in the <hi>Iriſh Rebellion,</hi> was by Direction from his Royal <hi>Father</hi> and <hi>Mother,</hi> and for the Service of the Crown.</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>Be aſtoniſhed, O ye Heavens, at this, and be ye hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribly afraid, be ye very deſolate, ſaith the Lord,</p>
                     <bibl>Jer. 2. 12.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <p>For there is nothing covered that ſhall not be revealed, nor any thing hid which ſhall not be known, <hi>or</hi> come abroad,</p>
                     <bibl>Mat. 10. 26.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>London,</hi> Printed 1698.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb facs="tcp:57844:36"/>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:57844:36"/>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>IRELAND,</hi> 
                        <date>Aug. 22<hi>d.</hi> 1663.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <salute>Ever Honoured Sir,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>LAST <hi>Thurſday</hi> we came to Tryal with my Lord Marqueſs of <hi>Antrim,</hi> but according to my Fears (which you always ſurmiſed to be in vain) he was by the King's Extraordinary, and Peremptory <hi>LET<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TER of Favour,</hi> reſtored to his Eſtate, as an <hi>Innocent Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt.</hi> We proved Eight Qualifications in the <hi>Act of Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement</hi> againſt him, the leaſt of which made him unca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of being reſtored as <hi>Innocent.</hi> We proved,
<list>
                        <item>1. <hi>That he was to have a hand in ſurprizing the Caſtle of</hi> Dublin, <hi>in the Year,</hi> 1641.</item>
                        <item>2. <hi>That he was of the Rebels party before the</hi> 15th. <hi>of</hi> Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember, 1643. <hi>which we made appear by his hourly and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent intercourſe with</hi> Renny O Moore, <hi>and many others; being himſelf the moſt notorious of the ſaid Rebels.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>3. <hi>That he entred into the Roman Catholick Confederacy before the Peace in</hi> 1643.</item>
                        <item>4. <hi>That he conſtantly adheard to the</hi> Nunctio's <hi>Party, in oppoſition to His Majeſty's Authority.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>5. <hi>That he ſat from time to time in the Supream Council of</hi> Kilkenny.</item>
                        <item>6. <hi>That he ſigned that execrable Oath of Aſſociation.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>7. <hi>That he was Commiſſionated, and acted as Lieutenant General, from the ſaid Aſſembly at</hi> Kilkenny.</item>
                        <item>8. <hi>That he declared by ſeveral Letters of his own Penning, himſelf in Conjunction with</hi> Owen Ro Oneale, <hi>and a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Oppoſer to the ſeveral Peaces, made by the Lord Leiute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with the</hi> Iriſh.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>We were ſeven Hours by the Clock in proving our Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence againſt him, but at laſt the King's Letter being opened, and read in Court, <hi>Rainsford,</hi> one of the Commiſſioners, to us, <hi>That the King's Letter on his behalf was Evidence without Exception,</hi> and thereupon declared him to be an <hi>Innocent Papiſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:57844:37"/>This Cauſe (Sir) hath (though many Reflections have paſſed upon the Commiſſioners before) more ſtartled the judgments of all Men, than all the Tryals ſince the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of their ſitting; and it is very ſtrange and wonderful to all of the <hi>Long Robe,</hi> that the King ſhould give ſuch a Letter, having diveſted himſelf of that Authority, and repoſed the Truſt in the Commiſſioners for that Purpoſe: And likewiſe it is admired, that the Commiſſioners having taken ſolmn Oaths, <hi>To execute nothing but according to, and in purſuance of the Act of Settlement,</hi> ſhould, barely upon His Majeſty's Letter, declare the Marqueſs <hi>Innocent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To be ſhort, there never was ſo great a Rebel, that had ſo much favour from ſo good a King: And it is very evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to me, though young, and ſcarce yet brought upon the Stage, that the conſequence of theſe things will be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry bad; and if God of his extraordinary Mercy do not prevent it, War, and (if poſſible) greater Judgments, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be far from us; where Vice is Patroniz'd, and <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trim,</hi> a Rebel upon Record, and ſo lately and clearly proved one, ſhould have no other colour for his Actions but the King's own Letter; which takes all Imputations from <hi>Antrim,</hi> and lays them totally upon his own Father.</p>
                  <p>Sir, I ſhall by the next, if poſſible, ſend you over one of our Briefs againſt my Lord, by ſome Friend: It's too large for a Pacquet, it being no leſs in bulk than a Book of Martyrs. I have no more at preſent, but refer you to the King's Letter, hereto annexed.</p>
                  <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>CHARLES</hi> R.</signed>
                           <salute>RIght Truſty and well-beloved Couſins and Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> We greet you well.</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>How far We have been from interpoſing on the behalf of any of Our <hi>Iriſh</hi> Subjects, who by their miſcarriages in the late Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion in that Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> had made themſelves unworthy of Our Grace and Protection, is notorious to all Men, and We were ſo jealous in that particular, that
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:57844:37"/>
ſhortly after Our return into this Our Kingdom, when the Marqueſs of <hi>Antrim</hi> came thither to preſent his duty to Us, upon the Information We received from thoſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who then attended Us, by a Deputation from Our Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> or from thoſe who at that time own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed our Authority there, that the Marqueſs of <hi>Antrim</hi> had ſo miſ-behaved himſelf towards Us, and Our late Royal Father of Bleſſed Memory, that he was in no degree wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the leaſt Countenance from Us, and that they had manifeſt and unqueſtionable Evidence of ſuch his Guilt. Whereupon We refuſed to admit the ſaid Marqueſs ſo much as into Our Preſence, but on the contrary committed him Priſoner to our Tower of <hi>London</hi>; where after he had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued ſeveral Months under a ſtrict reſtraint, upon the continued Information of the ſaid Perſons, We ſent him into <hi>Ireland,</hi> without interpoſing the leaſt on his behalf, but left him to undergo ſuch a Tryal and Puniſhment, as by the Juſtice of that Our Kingdom ſhould be found due to his Crime, expecting ſtill that ſome heinous Matter would be objected and proved againſt him, to make him uncapable, and to deprive him of that Favour and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection from Us, which we knew his former Actions and Services had merited. After many Months attendance there, and (We preſume) after ſuch Examinations as were requiſite, he was at laſt diſmiſſed, without any Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and without any tranſmiſſion of Charge againſt him to Us, and with a Licenſe to tranſport himſelf into this Kingdom. We concluded that it was then time to give him ſome inſtance of Our Favour, and to remember the many Services he had done, and the Sufferings he had undergone, for his Affections and Fidelity to Our Royal Father, and Our Self; and that it was time to redeem him from thoſe Calamities, which yet do lie as heavy upon him ſince, as before Our happy Return: And thereupon We recommend him to you Our Lieutenant, that you ſhould move Our Council there, for preparing a Bill to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:57844:38"/>
be tranſmitted to Us, for the Re-inveſting him the ſaid Marqueſs, into the Poſſeſſion of his Eſtate in that Our Kingdom, as had been done in ſome other Caſes. To which Letter, you Our ſaid Lieutenant returned Us an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, That you had informed Our Council of that Our Letter, and that you were upon conſideration thereof, unanimouſly of Opinion, that ſuch a Bill ought not to be tranſmitted to Us, the reaſon whereof would forthwith be preſented to Us from Our Council. After which time We received the incloſed Petition from the ſaid Marqueſs, which We referred to the conſiderations and examinations of the Lords of Our Privy Council, whoſe Names are men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in that Our Reference, which is annexed to the ſaid Petition, who thereupon met together, and after having heard the Marqueſs of <hi>Antrim,</hi> did not think fit to make any Report to Us, till they might ſee and underſtand the Reaſons which induced you not to tranſmit the Bill We had propoſed, which Letter was not then come to Our Hands: After which time We have received your Letter of the 18<hi>th.</hi> of <hi>March,</hi> together with ſeveral Petitions which had been preſented to you, as well from the Old <hi>Soldiers</hi> and <hi>Adventurers,</hi> as from the Lady <hi>Marchioneſs</hi> of <hi>Antrim,</hi> all which We likewiſe tranſmitted to the Lords <hi>Referees.</hi> Upon a ſecond Petition preſented to Us by the Lord Marqueſs, which is here likewiſe encloſed, commanding Our ſaid <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferees</hi> to take the ſame into their ſerious conſideration, and to hear what the Petitioner had to offer in his own Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and to report the whole matter to Us, which upon a third Petition herein likewiſe incloſed, We required them to be expedite with what ſpeed they could. By which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberate Proceedings of Ours you cannot but obſerve, that no importunity, how juſt ſoever, could prevail with Us to bring Our Self to a Judgment in this Affair, without very ample Information. Our ſaid <hi>Referees,</hi> after ſeveral Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and peruſal of what hath been offered to them by the ſaid Marqueſs, have reported unto Us, That they have
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:57844:38"/>
ſeen ſeveral Letters, all of them the hand-writing of Our Royal Father to the ſaid Marqueſs, and ſeveral <hi>Inſtructions</hi> concerning his treating and joyning with the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> in order to the King's Service, by reducing to their Obedience, and by drawing ſome Forces from them for the Service of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> That beſides the Letters and Orders under His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's Hand, they have received ſufficient Evidence and Teſtimony of ſeveral private Meſſages and Directions ſent from Our Royal Father, and from Our Royal Mother, with the Privity, and with the Directions of the King, Our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, by which they are perſuaded, that whatever Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, Correſpondence or Actings, the ſaid Marqueſs had with the Confederate <hi>Iriſh Catholicks,</hi> was directed or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by the ſaid <hi>Letters, Inſtructions</hi> and <hi>Directions</hi>; and that it manifeſtly appears to them, that the King, our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, was well pleaſed with what the Marqueſs did, after he had done it, and approved the ſame.</p>
                        <p>This being the true ſtate of the Marqueſs his Caſe, and there being nothing proved upon the firſt Information a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, nor any thing contained againſt him in your Letter of <hi>March</hi> 18. but that you were informed, he had put in his Claim before the Commiſſioners appointed for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuting the <hi>Act of Settlement</hi>; and that if his Innocency be ſuch as is alledged, there is no need of tranſmitting ſuch a Bill to Us as is deſired; and that if he be <hi>Nocent,</hi> it conſiſts not with with the Duty which you owe to Us, to tranſmit ſuch a Bill, as if it ſhould paſs into a Law, muſt needs draw a great Prejudice upon ſo many Adventurers and Soldiers, which are, <hi>as is alledged,</hi> to be therein concerned. We have conſidered of the <hi>Petition</hi> of the <hi>Adventurers</hi> and <hi>Soldiers,</hi> which was tranſmitted to Us by You; the Equity of which conſiſts in nothing, but that they have been peaceably in Poſſeſſion for the ſpace of 7 or 8 Years, of thoſe Lands which were formerly the State of the Marqueſs of <hi>Antrim,</hi> and others, who were all engaged in the late <hi>Iriſh Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>; and that they ſhall ſuffer very much and be ruined, if
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:57844:39"/>
thoſe Lands ſhould be taken from them. And We have likewiſe conſidered another Petition from ſeveral Citizens of <hi>London,</hi> near 60 in Number, directed to our Self, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they deſire, That the Marqueſs his Eſtate may be made liable to the payment of his juſt Debts, that ſo they may not be ruined in the favour of the preſent Poſſeſſors, who (they ſay) are but a few Citizens and Soldiers, who have disburſed very ſmall Sums thereon. Upon the whole mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, no Man can think We are leſs engaged by Our Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and by the Act of Settlement, to protect thoſe who are <hi>Innocent,</hi> and who have faithfully endeavoured to ſerve the Crown, how unfortunate ſoever, than to expoſe to Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice thoſe who have been really and maliciouſly guilty. And therefore we cannot in Juſtice, but upon the <hi>Petition</hi> of the Marqueſs of <hi>Antrim,</hi> and after the ſerious and ſtrict Inquiſition into his Actions, declare unto you, That We do find him <hi>Innocent</hi> from any Malice or Rebellious Purpoſe againſt the Crown; and that what he did by way of Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence or Compliance with the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebels, was in order to the Service of Our Royal Father, and warranted by his Inſtructions, and the Truſt repoſed in him, and that the benefit thereof accrued to the Service of the Crown, and not to the particular advantage and benefit of the Marqueſs. And as We cannot in juſtice deny him this Teſtimony, ſo We require You to tranſmit Our Letter to Our Commiſſioners, that they may know Our Judgments in this Caſe of the Lord of <hi>Antrims,</hi> and proceed accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly. And ſo We bid you heartily farewel.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>
                              <hi>Given at Our Court at</hi> White-Hall,
<date>
                                 <hi>July</hi> 10. <hi>in the</hi> 15<hi>th. Year of our Reign,</hi> 1663.</date>
                           </dateline>
                           <signed>By His Majeſty's Command, <hi>HENRY BENNET.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                        <postscript>
                           <p>Entred at the Signet-Office,</p>
                           <closer>
                              <dateline>
                                 <date>
                                    <hi>July</hi> 13. 1663.</date>
                              </dateline>
                           </closer>
                        </postscript>
                        <trailer>To Our Right Truſty and Right en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely Well-beloved Couſin and Counſellor, <hi>James</hi> Duke of <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond,</hi> Our Lieutenant General and General Governour of Our Kingdom of <hi>Ireland;</hi> and to the Lords of Our Council of that Our Kingdom.</trailer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="proclamation">
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:57844:39"/>
                  <div type="license__by_Charles_I">
                     <head>King <hi>Charles</hi> I. his Order to the Archbiſhop of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> for Printing his Declaration concerning Sports on <hi>Sundays.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <opener>
                        <signed>CHARLES <hi>R.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </opener>
                     <p>Canterbury, <hi>See that Our</hi> Declaration concerning Recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions on the Lord's Day after Evening Prayer, <hi>be Printed.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="preamble_to_proclamation__by_Charles_II">
                     <head>The KING'S Majeſties Declaration to His Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, concerning Lawful SPORTS to be Uſed.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <signed>By the KING.</signed>
                     </opener>
                     <p>OUR Dear Father of Bleſſed Memory, in his return from <hi>Scotland,</hi> coming through <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> found that his Subjects were debarred from Lawful Recreations upon Sundays after Evening Prayers ended, and upon Holy Days: And He prudently conſidered, that if theſe times were taken from them, the meaner ſort, who labour hard all the Week, ſhould have no Recreations at all to refreſh their Spirits. And after his return, he farther ſaw that his Loyal Subjects in all other parts of his Kingdom did ſuffer in the ſame kind, though perhaps not in the ſame Degree: And did therefore, in his Princely Wiſdom, Publiſh a Declaration to all his loving Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, concerning Lawful Sports to be uſed at ſuch times, which was Printed and Publiſhed by his Royal Commandment, in the Year 1618. in the Tenor which hereafter Followeth.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="text_of_proclamation__by_Charles_I">
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:57844:40"/>
                     <opener>
                        <signed>By the KING.</signed>
                     </opener>
                     <p>
                        <hi>WHereas upon Our</hi> return the laſt Year out of <hi>Scotland,</hi> We did publiſh Our Pleaſure, touching the Recreati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Our People in thoſe parts under Our Hand; for ſome Cauſes Us thereunto moving, We have thought good to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand theſe Our Directions then given in <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> with a few Words thereunto added, and moſt appliable to theſe parts of Our Realms to be Publiſhed to all Our Subjects.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Whereas We did juſtly in Our</hi> Progreſs through <hi>Lanca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> Rebuke ſome Puritanes and preciſe People, and took or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that the like unlawful Carriage ſhould not be uſed by any of them hereafter, in the prohibiting and unlawful Puniſhing of Our Good People, for uſing their Lawful Recreations, and Honeſt Exerciſes upon Sundays and other Holy-days, after the Afternoon Sermon or Service: We now find, that two ſorts of People, wherewith that Country is much infected, (We mean Papiſts and Puritans) have Maliciouſly traduced and calumniated thoſe Our juſt and Honourable Proceedings. And therefore, leſt Our Reputation might upon the one ſide (though innocently) have ſome Aſperſion laid upon it, and that upon the other part, Our Good People in that Country be miſled by the miſtaking and miſinterpretation of Our meaning; We have therefore thought good hereby, to clear and make Our Pleaſure to be manifeſted to all Our Good People in thoſe parts.</p>
                     <p>It is true, that at Our firſt entry to this Crown, and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, We were informed, and that too truly, that Our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Lancaſhire</hi> abounded more in Popiſh Recuſants, than any County of <hi>England,</hi> and thus hath ſtill continued ſince to Our great Regret, with little amendment, ſave that now of late, in Our laſt riding through Our ſaid County. We find both by the Report of the Judges, and of the Biſhop of that Diocſes, that there is ſome Amendment now daily beginning, which is no <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>all Contentment to Us.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="11" facs="tcp:57844:40"/>The report of this growing Amendment amongſt them, made Us the more ſorry, when with Our own Ears We heard the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Complaint of Our People, that they were barred from all Lawful Recreation, and Exerciſe upon the Sundays Afternoon, after the ending of all Divine Service, which cannot but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce two Evils: The one, the hindering of the Converſion of many, whom their Prieſts will take occaſion hereby to vex, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading them that no honeſt Mirth or Recreation is Lawful or Tolerable in Our Religion, which cannot but breed a great Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contentment in Our Peoples Hearts, eſpecially of ſuch as are peradventure upon the point of Turning. The other Inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is, that this Prohibition barreth the common and meaner ſort of People from uſing ſuch Exerciſe, as may make their Bodies more able for War, when We, or Our Succeſſors ſhall have occaſion to uſe them. And in place thereof, ſets up fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Tiplings and Drunkenneſs, and breeds a number of idle and diſcontented Speeches in their Ale-houſes. For when ſhall the Common People have leave to Exerciſe, if not upon the Sundays and Holidays, ſeeing they muſt apply their Labour, and win their Living in all Working Days.</p>
                     <p>Our expreſs Pleaſure therefore is, that the Laws of Our Kingdom and Cannons of Our Church, be as well obſerved in that County, as in all other Places of this Our Kingdom. And on the other part, that no Lawful Recreation ſhall be barred to Our Good People, which ſhall not tend to the breach of Our aforeſaid Laws, and Cannons of Our Church: Which to expreſs more particularly, Our Pleaſure is, That the Biſhop, and all other Inferiour Church-men, and Church-wardens, ſhall for their parts be careful and diligent, both to inſtruct the Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, and Convince and Reform them that are miſled in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, preſenting them that will not Conform themſelves, but obſtinately ſtand out to Our Judges and Juſtices: Whom We likewiſe Command to put the Law in due Execution againſt them.</p>
                     <p>Our Pleaſure likewiſe is, That the Biſhop of that Dioceſs take the like ſtraight Order with all the Puritanes and Preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:57844:41"/>
within the ſame, either conſtraining them to Conform themſelves, or to leave the County according to the Laws of Our Kingdom, and Cannons of Our Church, and ſo to ſtrike e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually on both Hands, againſt the Contemners of Our Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and Adverſaries of Our Church. And as for Our Good Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Lawful Recreation, our Pleaſure likewiſe is, That after the end of Divine Service, Our Good People be not diſturbed, letted, or diſcouraged from any Lawful Recreation, ſuch as Dancing, either Men or Women, Archery for Men, Leaping, Vaulting, or any other ſuch harmleſs Recreation, nor from ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of May-Games, Whitſon-Ales, and Morris-Dances, and the ſetting up of May-Poles, and other Sports therewith uſed, ſo as the ſame be had in due and convenient time, without im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediment or neglect of Divine Service: And that Women ſhall have leave to carry Ruſhes to the Church for the decoring of it, according to their old Cuſtom. But withal, We do here ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count ſtill as prohibited all unlawful Games to he uſed upon Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>days only, as Bear and Bull-baitings, Interludes, and at all times in the meaner ſort of People by Law prohibited, Bowling.</p>
                     <p>And likewiſe, We bar from this Benefit and Liberty, all ſuch known Recuſants, either Men or Women, as will abſtain from coming to Church or Divine Service, being therefore un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of any Lawful Recreation after the ſaid Service, that will not firſt come to the Church, and ſerve <hi>God:</hi> Prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in like ſort, the ſaid Recreations to any, that though conform in Religion, are not preſent in the Church at the Ser-Service of <hi>God,</hi> before their going to the ſaid Recreations. Our Pleaſure likewiſe is, That they to whom it belongeth in Office, ſhall preſent and ſharply puniſh all ſuch as in Abuſe of this Our Liberty, will uſe theſe Exerciſes before the ends of all Divine Services for that Day. And We likewiſe ſtraight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Command, that every Perſon ſhall reſort to his own Pariſh Church to hear Divine Sirvice, and each Pariſh by it ſelf to uſe the ſ<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>id Recreation after Divine Service. Prohibiting likewiſe any Offenſive Weapons to be carried or uſed in the ſaid times of Recreations. And our Pleaſure is, That this
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:57844:41"/>
Our Declaration ſhall be Publiſhed by Order from the Biſhop of the Dioceſs, through all the Pariſh Churches, and that both Our Judges of Our Circuit, and Our Juſtices of Our Peace be informed thereof.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Given at Our Mannor of</hi> Greenwich, <date>
                              <hi>the Four and Twentieth Day of</hi> May, <hi>in the Sixteenth Year of Our Reign of</hi> England, France <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>and of</hi> Scotland <hi>the One and Fiftieth.</hi>
                           </date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="corroborating_proclamation__by_Charles_II">
                     <head>Here follows King <hi>Charles</hi> II. Corroborating Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to have the Recreations and Sports to be uſed on the Lord's Day.</head>
                     <p>NOW out of a like Pious Care for the Service of God, and for ſuppreſſing of any Humors that oppoſe Truth, and for the Eaſe, Comfort, and Recreation of Our well deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving People, Wo do ratifie and publiſh, this our Bleſſed Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Declaration: The rather, becauſe, of late in ſome Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Kingdom, We find that under pretence of taking away Abuſes, there hath been a general Forbidding, not only of ordinary Meetings, but of the Feaſts of the Dedication of the Churches, commonly called Wakes. Now Our expreſs Will and Pleaſure is, that theſe Feaſts. with others, ſhall be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, and that Our Juſtices of the Peace in their ſeveral Diviſions ſhall look to it, both that all Diſorders there, may be prevented or puniſhed, and that all Neighbourhood and Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, with Manlike and Lawful Exerciſes be uſed. And We farther command Our Juſtices of Aſſize in their ſeveral Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuits, to ſee that no Man do Trouble or Moleſt any of Our Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al and Dutiful People, in, or for their lawful Recreations, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving firſt done their Duty to God, and continuing in Obedience to Us and Our Laws. And of this, We command all Our Judges, Juſtices of the Peace, as well within Liberties as
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:57844:42"/>
without, Mayors, Bayliffs, Conſtables, and other Officers, to take notice of, and to ſee obſerved, as they tender Our Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure. And We farther Will, that Publication of this Our Command be made by Order from the Biſhops through all the Pariſh Churches of their ſeveral Dioceſſes reſpectively.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Given at Our Palace of</hi> Weſtminſter, <date>
                              <hi>the</hi>
18th. <hi>of</hi> October, <hi>in the Ninth of Our Reign.</hi>
                           </date>
                        </dateline>
God ſave the King.</closer>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <head>A true Copy of the Commiſſion ſaid to be given by the King to his Catholick Subjects of <hi>Ireland,</hi> with the War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and Depoſition annexed.</head>
               <div type="letter">
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>From our Camp at</hi> Newrie <date>
                           <hi>this</hi>
                           <hi>Fourth of</hi> Nov. 1641.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Philem. O. Neale, Rorie Macguire.</signed>
                     <salute>
                        <hi>To all Catholicks of the Romiſh Party, both</hi> Engliſh <hi>and</hi> Iriſh, <hi>within the Kingdom of</hi> Ireland, <hi>we wiſh all Happineſs, Freedom of Conſcience, and</hi> Victory <hi>over the</hi> Engliſh He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks, <hi>who have for a long time Tyrannized over our Bodies, and uſurped by Extortion our Eſtates.</hi>
                     </salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>BE it hereby made known unto you all our Friends and Country-men, That the King's moſt Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Majeſty, (for many great and urgent Cauſes him thereunto moving, repoſing Truſt and Confidence in our Fidelities) hath ſignified unto us by his Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, under the great Seal of <hi>Scotland,</hi> bearing date at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> the firſt Day of this Inſtant <hi>October,</hi> 1641.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:57844:42"/>
and alſo by Letters under his Sign Manuel, bearing date with the ſaid Commiſſion; of divers great and heinous Affronts that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proteſtants, eſpecially the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament there, have publiſhed againſt his Royal Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative, and alſo againſt our Catholick Friends within the Kingdom of <hi>England.</hi> The Copy of which Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion we have here ſent unto you, to be publiſhed with all Speed in all parts of this Kingdom, that you may be aſſured of our ſufficient Warrant and Authority herein.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="commission">
                  <head>The Commiſſion.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>CHARLES,</hi> by the Grace of God, King of <hi>England, Scotland, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> Defender of the Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </signed>
                     <salute>To all Our Catholick Subjects within Our Kingdom of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> Greeting.</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Know ye,</hi> That We for the Safeguard and Preſervation of Our Perſon, have been enforced to make Our Abode and Reſidence in Our Kingdom of <hi>Scotland</hi> for a long Seaſon, occaſioned by reaſon of the Obſtinate and Diſobedient Carriage of Our Parliament in <hi>England</hi> againſt Us; who have not only preſumed to take upon them the Government, and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of thoſe Princely Rights and Prerogatives, that have juſtly deſcended upon Us from Our Predeceſſors, both Kings and Queens of the ſaid Kingdom, for many hundred Years laſt paſt; but alſo have poſſeſſed themſelves of the whole Strength of the ſaid Kingdom, in appointing Governours, Commanders and Officers in all parts and places therein, at their own Wills and Pleaſure, without Our Conſent, whereby We are deprived of Our Sovereignty, and left naked without Defence. And foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as We are (in Our ſelf) very ſenſible, That thoſe Storms blow aloft, and are very likely to be carried by the Vehemency of the <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Puritan</hi> in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Copy.</note> 
                     <hi>Proteſtant Party</hi> into Our Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and endanger Our Regal
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:57844:43"/>
and Authority there alſo. <hi>Know ye therefore,</hi> That We re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing much Care and Truſt in your Duties and Obedience, which We have for many Years paſt ſound, do hereby give un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you full Power and Authority to Aſſemble and meet together with all the Speed and Diligence that <hi>a Buſineſs of ſo great a Conſequence</hi> doth require, and to Adviſe and Conſult toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by ſufficient and diſcreet Numbers, at all Times, Days and Places, which you ſhall in your Judgments hold moſt Conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient and Material for the Ordering, Settleling and Effecting of this <hi>Great Work</hi> (mentioned and directed unto you in Our Letters) and to uſe all politick Ways and Means poſſible to poſſeſs your ſelves (for Our Uſe and Safety) of all the Forts, Caſtles and Places of Strength and Defence within the ſaid Kingdom (except the places, Perſons and Eſtates of our Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al and Loving Subjects the <hi>Scots</hi>) and alſo to Arreſt and Seize the Goods, Eſtates and Perſons of all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proteſtants within the ſaid Kingdom, to Our uſe, and in your care and ſpeedy performance of this Our Will and Pleaſure, we ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive your wonted Duty and Allegiance unto Us, which We ſhall accept and reward in due time.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Witneſs</hi> Our ſelf at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> 
                        <date>the firſt day of <hi>October,</hi> in the Seventeenth Year of Our Reign.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
                  <argument>
                     <p>More of theſe ſecret Intreagues of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt and Second, you will find in a Book, Entituled, <hi>Great</hi> Britain's <hi>Miſeries,</hi> in a ſhort Hiſtory of the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold Difficulties this Kingdom has laboured under theſe 40 Years laſt paſt.</p>
                  </argument>
               </div>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:57844:43"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>A LETTER</hi> From Pope <hi>Gregory XVth.</hi> to <hi>Charles Steward,</hi> Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> and ſince King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> during the time of his being in <hi>Spain:</hi> As likewiſe the ſaid Prince's Anſwer.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>Both taken out of the Hiſtory of <hi>England,</hi> at the Pages 1162, 1163, 1164. Written by the Sieur <hi>Andrew du Cheſne;</hi> being the Third Edition, printed at <hi>Paris,</hi> in the Year 1641, by <hi>William Loyſon</hi> at the Pallace in the Middle of the <hi>Priſoners Gallery;</hi> and which are alſo to be met with in the <hi>French Mercury</hi> of the Year 1623, when theſe Letters were Written, both which the ſaid King never Diſown'd.</p>
                  </argument>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Moſt Noble Prince,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>AFter wiſhing you all immaginable Health, and the Illumination of Gods Divine Grace, We give you to Underſtand, That whereas <hi>Great Britain</hi> has always abounded in Virtues, and in Perſons of ſingular Merit and Eſteem, and conſequently fill'd both Worlds with the Glory of its Renown; ſo ſhe has alſo very fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently exacted the Conſideration and Commendation of the Apoſtolick See. And indeed the Holy Church was
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:57844:44"/>
but yet in its Infancy, when the King of Kings pitch'd upon it, for the Portion of his Inheritance, and which he did with ſo great Zeal and Affection, that ſcarce the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Eagles got poſſeſſion of it before the Croſs: And we may withal Obſerve that many of its Kings likewiſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inſtructed in the ſureſt means of their Salvation, have all along prefer'd the Holy Croſs to the Regal Scepter, and the Doctrine of Religion, either to Ambition or Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs, tranſmitting thereby Examples of Piety both to foreign Nations and Poſterity: So that having ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently merited in Heaven, the Privileges and Preeminences of Beatitude, they have alſo Obtain'd on Earth the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphal Ornaments of never-dying Sanctity. And now altho' the Church of <hi>England</hi> has for ſome time, been born and ſeperated from the true Catholick Faith, yet at the ſame time we perceive the Court of <hi>Great Britain</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorn'd and embelliſh'd with ſo many Moral Virtues, that we cannot but be encourag'd in our Love towards her, and ſhould Acknowledge her as one of the chiefeſt Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Chriſtian Name, provided ſhe were but Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lify'd, and Influenc'd with the Orthodox, and Univerſal Truth. For which reaſon, and ſo much the rather, as we have the deepeſt Sence of, and the ſincereſt Reſpect for, the Glory of your moſt Serene Father, and your own great Natural Abilities, ſo we heartily and paſſionately deſire that the Gates of Heaven may be ſet open to you, and the Tenets of the True Church be receiv'd by you. Moreover, whereas <hi>Gregory the Great,</hi> Our Glorious Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſor of moſt pious Memory firſt taught the People of your Nation to obey the Law of the Goſpel, and to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to the Apoſtolic Authority, ſo we (tho' Inferiour to him, both in Piety and Virtue) yet of the ſame Name and Dignity with him, do think it but reaſonable that we follow his holy Steps, and endeavour to procure the Salvation of your Country, eſpecially at thsi Juncture, when your happy Intentions, Moſt Noble Prince, have
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:57844:44"/>
rais'd in us hopes of a ſucceſsful Event. Therefore as you are at preſent at the Court of the moſt Catholick King, with Inclinations to make an Alliance with the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> we cannot but extreamly commend Your Deſign; and the rather, by reaſon that we are ſatisfy'd that your principal end in it is, the promoting the Advantage of our Supream Prelacy and Dignity: For ſince you ſeem ſo earneſtly to deſire the <hi>Infanta</hi> of <hi>Spain</hi> in Marriage, we may eaſily infer that in all probabily the ancient ſeeds of Chriſtian Piety, which have formerly flouriſh'd ſo proſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly in the Hearts of the Kings of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> may revive and recover their priſtine Glory in you, and we cannot think that he who profeſſes ſo ſincere an eſteem for ſuch an Alliance, ſhould be an Enemy to the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Religion, or be ever enclin'd to moleſt the Holy See. In purſuance whereof we have commanded continual and moſt humble Orations, to be put up to the Father of Mercies that it would pleaſe his Divine Goodneſs to eſtabliſh you, as the blooming Flower of Chriſtendom, and the Sole Hopes of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> in the Throne of your Noble Anceſtors, who for the moſt part, have all made it their chiefeſt Buſineſs, to Aſſert the Authority of the Soveraign Pontificat, and to combat the Monſters of Hereſy. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to Yourſelf the Modells of former Ages; inſpect the Behaviour of your Fore-fathers, and they will ſhew you, what Method you are to take to get the Throne of Bliſs; and what Policy Temporal Princes have always made uſe of, to inherit an Eternal Kingdom. Behold your gloriours Predeceſſors Enthron'd above! Who for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, waited on by Angels went to <hi>Rome,</hi> to Honour and do Homage to the Lord of Lords, and to the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors of his Holy Apoſtle <hi>St. Peter.</hi> Their Works and Examples are of ſo many Voices, whereby God Exhorts you to imitate their Lives, to whoſe Empire you ſhall one day arrive. Is it poſſible that you can ſuffer the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:57844:45"/>
Hereticks, to Profane and Condemn thoſe Holy Men, whom the Faith of the Church, enjoyns us to believe to Reign above the Clouds with <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi>; and to have command and Authority over all the Principalities and Potentates of the Earth? See theſe bleſſed Saints ſtretch out their Arms, to Conduct you ſafe to the Court of this moſt Catholick King; and behold with what Ardour they deſire to lead you to the Boſom of the Mother-Church; That Church which is often ſuppliant with inexpreſſible Agonies, before the Throne of Almighty Wiſdom, for your Reformation and Safety, and which even now ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders its Apoſtolick Charity, with all imaginable Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Affection, to receive you to her ſelf; You, that are her Darling Son; You, that are her moſt deſir'd, tho' hitherto her too miſguided, Off-ſpring! Certainly you can never be more Obliging to the Chriſtian State, than to put the Prince of Apoſtles into the poſſeſſion of your moſt noble Iſland, which has almoſt all along hitherto approv'd its ſelf the moſt potent Arbiter both of Church and State. The moſt glorious Work will the eaſier be Effected, if you firſt ſhew an Example, by Opening to God that knocks at the Door of your Heart, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in conſiſt the Abſolute Happineſs and Salvation of this Kingdom. This is ſo great Charity, occaſions us to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that You, and your moſt Serene Father, ſhould be qualify'd with the glorious Titles of Deliverers, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorers of the Ancient and Paternal Religion of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> which we hope may be ſpeedily Effected, by means of the great Power and Goodneſs of God, in whoſe Hands the Hearts of Kings are, and who cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes the People of the Earth to receive Relief, and which we ſhall always be ready to Favour and Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage to the utmoſt of our Power: In the mean time, be pleas'd to underſtand by the Contents of this Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that for Our parts We will omit nothing that may
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:57844:45"/>
anywiſe tend to procure your Happineſs; and that We ſhall never repent of having writ it, if it may be but ſo efficacious, as to raiſe the leaſt Spark of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Faith in your Breaſt, whoſe Benefit we ſo much deſire, and to whom We wiſh long Life, and an endleſs Encreaſe of all Chriſtian Virtues. <hi>Given at</hi> Rome, <hi>in the Palace of</hi> St. Peter, <hi>the</hi> 20th. <hi>Day of</hi> April, 1623, <hi>and in the Third Year of Our</hi> Pontificat.</p>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>This Letter was deliver'd to the ſaid Prince by the Pope's Nuncio, accompany'd by all the</hi> Italian <hi>Lords, who were then at the Court of</hi> Spain.</p>
                  </argument>
               </div>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:57844:46"/>
                  <head>King <hi>CHARLES</hi> I's. ANSWER, (Being then PRINCE of <hi>WALES</hi>) TO THE POPE'S LETTER.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Moſt Holy Father,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I Have received Your Holineſſe's Letter with infinite ſatisfaction, paying all imaginable reſpect to the Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Good Will, with which your Holineſs writ it. But what has occaſion'd me inexpreſſible Pleaſure was, to read of the generous exploits of the King's, my Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, in whoſe deſerv'd Commendations Poſterity hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto has not been a little Niggardly. I am willing to believe Your Holineſs ſet their Example before my Eyes, that I might endeavour to imitate them in all my Actions, for in truth, they have often expoſed, both themſelves and their Dominions, for the Exaltation of the Holy See; inſomuch that their Courage, with which they attack'd the Enemies of the Holy Croſs, has ever approved it ſelf
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:57844:46"/>
as vigorous, as my endeavours ſhall always be to intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce Peace, good Intelligence, which have hitherto been ſo much wanting into Chriſtendom; for as the common Enemy of Peace labors inceſſantly to inſult Hatred and Diſſention into the hearts of Chriſtian Princes, ſo I am of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, that the Glory of God requires indiſpenſably that they ſhould be united, and I do not value my ſelf in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deſcended from ſo many great Princes on any account, ſo much as in my Unfeigned and true Zeal, to purſue the footſteps of their Piety. To ſupport me in which deſign, it is no ſmall advantage to me, to be back'd by the Will and Pleaſure of my moſt Honour'd Lord and Father, and the pious Intention of his Moſt Catholick Majeſty, both who are more than ordinarily concern'd to think of the great Calamities that muſt neceſſarily proceed from a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>union among Chriſtian Princes. This the unexampled Prudence of Your Holineſs has foreſeen, while you deem'd the Marriage between me and the <hi>Infanta</hi> of <hi>Spain,</hi> to be ſo abſolutely neceſſary for the Publick Good, and nothing is more certain, than that I ſhall be always moſt paſſionately deſirous of an Alliance with a Prince who has the ſame Sentiments of the true Religion with my ſelf; wherefore I earneſtly beg Your Holineſs, to believe that I have always been very far from encouraging any Noval<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in Religion, or from favouring any Faction oppoſite to the Intereſt of the <hi>Apoſtolick See</hi>; but on the contrary, have ſought after all occaſions, to take away any ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions or jealouſies I might lie under, being reſolved to employ the remainder of my Days, in the practiſe of one Religion, and one Faith, ſince we ought all to follow alike in <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> in purſuance whereof, I ſhall for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture avoid no hazards, and cheerfully undergo all manner of Inconveniencies, even to the Expoſing of my Life and Fortune, upon an occaſion that will undoubtedly be ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable and well-pleaſing to God. Nothing more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:57844:47"/>
but that I humbly thank Your Holineſs for ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting me to this unworthy Addreſs, and I alſo earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beſeech Almighty God, to grant Your Holineſs Health in this World, and Eternal Happineſs in that to come, after ſo many Labours and Fatigues, which your Holineſs has undergone for the Propagation and Preſervation of the Holy True Church.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Signed, <hi>CHARLES</hi> R.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="treaty">
                  <head>The ſubſtance of the Articles of Peace made and conclud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſts and Rebels, by <hi>James</hi> Lord Marqueſs of <hi>Ormond,</hi> for, and on the behalf of His Majeſty King <hi>Charles I.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THE Subſtance of the <hi>Proclamation</hi> is, That whereas the Lord Marqueſs of <hi>Ormond,</hi> Lord Lieutenant of <hi>Ireland,</hi> by virtue of an Authority given him by King <hi>Charles</hi> I. had agreed to a <hi>Peace,</hi> on his ſaid Majeſties ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, with the General Aſſembly of <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> of that <hi>Kingdom</hi>; all the Inhabitants are obliged to take No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice thereof, and to be <hi>Obedient</hi> to the ſame at their <hi>Peril.</hi> Alſo that the <hi>Motives</hi> which induced that King to ſuch a <hi>Peace,</hi> were the Benefit and Traffick of his Subjects, and to put a ſtop to the Miſeries which they had ſo long un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergone. Sign'd <hi>Ormond,</hi> and Dated from the Caſtle of <hi>Kilkenny</hi> the 17<hi>th. June,</hi> 1648.</p>
                  <p>The Subſtance of the <hi>Articles</hi> are, That in conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his ſaid Majeſties having been acknowledg'd <hi>Right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> and <hi>Lawful</hi> Sovereign, by his <hi>Dutiful</hi> and <hi>Loyal</hi> Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:57844:47"/>
the <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and for their hearty <hi>Proffers</hi> of doing him all imaginable ſervice that King was pleas'd to Grant.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That that they ſhall have the free <hi>Exerciſe</hi> of their <hi>Religion,</hi> without being ſubject to any <hi>Penalties</hi> for the ſame; That they ſhall not be forc'd to receive any other than what is Agreeable to their <hi>Conſcience</hi>; That they ſhall not be oblig'd to take the <hi>Oath of Supremacy,</hi> but only bind themſelves to be <hi>True</hi> and <hi>Faithful</hi> to the King, as their <hi>Temporal Lord.</hi> Nevertheleſs, the Lord Lieutenant does not pretend to alter the Eſtabliſhed State of <hi>Spiritualities,</hi> having no Authority for that purpoſe; but however, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes that the ſaid <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> ſhall not be interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in any of their <hi>Poſſeſſions</hi> and <hi>Juriſdictions,</hi> till His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, upon a full conſideration of their deſires, ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare his further Pleaſure in the next <hi>Free Parliament,</hi> wherein alſo theſe gracious Confeſſions are to be Enacted as Laws.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That a <hi>Free Parliament</hi> ſhall be call'd in <hi>Ireland</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in 6 Months, or as ſoon after as 12 Perſons nam'd in this <hi>Article,</hi> or the major part of them, ſhall deſire; and that in the mean time, theſe <hi>Articles</hi> ſhall be inviolably obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved as <hi>Laws:</hi> Yet in caſe a <hi>Parliament</hi> be not held within 2 Years after the Date hereof, then is the Lord Leiutenant, at the Requeſt of the ſaid Twelve, to Convene the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral States for the better ſettling of Affairs in that <hi>Kingdom</hi>; and that the Contents of theſe <hi>Articles</hi> are to be tranſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into <hi>England,</hi> according to the uſual Form to be paſſed in <hi>Parliament</hi> there, and that no Alterations to the preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of the King's <hi>Catholicks,</hi> or <hi>Proteſtant Subjects,</hi> ſhall be made either here or there, other than what His Majeſty ſhall declare his <hi>Pleaſure</hi> in, for the ſatisfaction of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, or than ſuch Matters, as the then Lord Leiutenant ſhall propoſe to both, or either Houſes for the Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:57844:48"/>
of His Majeſties Service, and the Peace of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, but which muſt not in the leaſt intrench on theſe preſent <hi>Articles.</hi> Moreover, this <hi>Parliament</hi> may either Repeal or Suſpend <hi>Poyning's</hi> Law, which imports that no <hi>Parliament</hi> ſhall be held in <hi>Ireland</hi> till the <hi>Acts</hi> are firſt Certify'd into <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. That all <hi>Acts</hi> made to the prejudice of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholicks, ſince the <hi>7th.</hi> of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1641. ſhall be null and void, and that they be vacated accordingly in the next Parliament, and in the mean time they have no Force.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. That all Proceſſes in prejudice of the ſaid Roman Catholicks, made ſince the ſaid <hi>7th.</hi> of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1641. ſhall be made void in ſuch manner, as no Memory ſhall remain thereof; and this, when ever the ſaid Twelve, or the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor part of them ſhall deſire the ſame, and in the interim they are to be of no Force, and what has already been done upon their Account, is to be reſtor'd, or made good.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. The <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> ſhall be deem'd qualified to Set in the ſucceeding <hi>Parliaments.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6. All Debts are to remain as they were on the 23<hi>d.</hi> of <hi>October,</hi> 1641. notwithſtanding any Alliance made on account of theſe Proceſſes, and this to be Enacted by the next <hi>Parliament.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">7. That the Eſtates, and reputed Eſtates, of all the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the Counties of <hi>Cannought, Clare, Thomond, Limerick</hi> and <hi>Tipperary,</hi> be ſecured to them according to the 25<hi>th. Article</hi> of the Grant in the 4<hi>th</hi> Year of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Reign, to be held by the ſame Rents and Tenures as they were in the ſaid 4<hi>th.</hi> Year. And as for the Laws in the Counties of <hi>Kilkenny</hi> and <hi>Wickloe,</hi> to which His Majeſty was Entitled by Offices found for him during the Earl of <hi>Stafford</hi>'s Government, the State of them is to be conſidered the next intended <hi>Parliament,</hi> when his Majeſty
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:57844:48"/>
will Aſſent to what is Juſt and Honourable; and that the Act for limitation of His Majeſties Titles, for the ſecurity of his Subject's Eſtates in this Kingdom, be paſs'd in the ſaid <hi>Parliament,</hi> purſuant to what was Enacted in the 21<hi>ſt</hi> Year of <hi>James</hi> I. in <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="8">8. All Incapacities impos'd on the <hi>Iriſh Catholicks,</hi> to be taken away in the ſucceeding <hi>Parliament,</hi> and they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled to Erect <hi>Inns</hi> of <hi>Court,</hi> or <hi>Free Schools,</hi> where the Lord Lieutenant in conjuction with the Twelve, or the major number of them, ſhall think fit, and the Students and Scholars are to take only an <hi>Oath of Allegiance</hi>; this like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe is to be Enacted by the next <hi>Parliament.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="9">9. <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> are to be deem'd, qualifi'd for any Truſt in the Army, and to be prefer'd according to their reſpective Merits. As, likewiſe to be receiv'd into the <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Government,</hi> with the like <hi>Priviledges</hi>; alſo they are to be entruſted with any Gariſons in the ſame manner. And that, till full ſettlement in <hi>Parliament,</hi> 15000 Foot and 2500 Horſe of the <hi>Iriſh Roman Catholicks,</hi> ſhall be of the ſtanding Army, which number may be either Aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented or diminiſh'd by the power of the Lord Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and the aforeſaid Twelve, or their Majority, as often as they ſhall ſee convenient.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. The King is to receive 12000 Pound annually, in lieu of whatever profits may accrue to him within the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction of the <hi>Court of Wards.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="11">11. No Noble Man for the future is to be allowed to make above 2 Proxies in <hi>Parliament,</hi> and all Blank Proxies to be totally diſallowed. Alſo, where a Baron has not 200 Pound <hi>per Ann.</hi> a Viſcount 400, an Earl 600, a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſs 800, and a Duke 1000, they ſhall be diſabled to ſit in <hi>Parliament,</hi> and the <hi>Commons</hi> alſo are to be ſtated, and reſident within the Kingdom.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. As for the <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>Ireland,</hi> depending on that of <hi>England,</hi> they are left to make ſuch <hi>Declaration</hi> therein
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:57844:49"/>
as ſhall be agreeable to their Laws of their Kingdom.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. That for the future, the <hi>Council Table</hi> is to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd within its own Bounds, and to meddle only with matters of State and Weight, other Buſineſs between Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Party is to be left to the Ordinary courſe of Law.</p>
                  <p n="14">14. Several Acts ſhall be Repeal'd, relating to Wool, Flocks, Tallow, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and divers Officers appointed by the Lord Lieutenant, and the aforeſaid Twelve, or the majority of them, to aſcertain the Rates of all Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize, either to be Exported or Imported.</p>
                  <p n="15">15. All Perſons wrong'd by Offices found in the firſt of King <hi>James</hi> I. or ſince, in the Province of <hi>Ulſter,</hi> and other Provinces of this Kingdom, may Petition His Majeſty, and be Redreſt upon Examination.</p>
                  <p n="16">16. That as to the particular caſes of 16 Perſons nam'd, they may Petition in the next <hi>Parliament,</hi> and ſhall be relieved accordingly.</p>
                  <p n="17">17. The former Inhabitants of <hi>Cork, Youghall</hi> and <hi>Downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garven,</hi> ſhall be reſtored to their reſpective Eſtates, where their Number does not endanger the Garrifons, and ſhall chuſe and return Burgeſſes as formerly.</p>
                  <p n="18">18. An Act of Indemnity to paſs in the next Parliament, to extend to all His Majeſties Loving Subjects of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and Pyrates on the Sea, except ſuch as have been Convicted or Attainted on Record before the 23 of <hi>October</hi> 1641. it ſhall not extend to remit any of the King's Debts, or Subſidies, due before the ſaid time; provided, that ſuch Barbarous Crimes as ſhall be agreed upon by the Lord Lieutenant, and the Twelve, or the Majority of them, be left to be adjudg'd by ſuch Commiſſioners, as the ſaid Lord Lieutenant and the Twelve ſhall Aſſign, and that the power of ſuch Commiſſioners be limitted to two Years. The other <hi>Proviſoes</hi> are omitted for Brevities ſake.</p>
                  <p n="19">19. The great Officers of the Kingdom are excluded from being Farmers of the Cuſtoms.</p>
                  <p n="20">
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:57844:49"/>20. An Act of <hi>Parliament</hi> to paſs againſt <hi>Monopolies,</hi> purſuant to that Enacted in <hi>England,</hi> in the 21<hi>ſt.</hi> of <hi>James</hi> I. with a clauſe to Repeal all Grants of <hi>Monopolies.</hi> Likewiſe Commiſſioners to be appointed by the Lord Lieutenant, and the Twelve, or the majority of them, to rate the Cuſtoms and Impoſitions on <hi>Aquivita, Tobacco,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p n="21">21. Commiſſioners agreed upon by the Lord Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and the Twelve, or their Majority, were to regulate the Court of <hi>Caſtle Chamber.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="22">22. The two Acts prohibiting the Plowing with Horſes by the Tail, and the Burning of Oats in the Straw, to be Repeal<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d.</p>
                  <p n="23">23. That the Grievances Petition'd for by both Houſes of Parliament, and by Agents ſent for that purpoſe in the 4<hi>th.</hi> Year of His Majeſties Reign, ſhall be Redreſſed.</p>
                  <p n="24">24. All Sea Affairs to be determin'd in this Kingdom, and in caſe of Appeal, it may be only to the Chancery of <hi>Ireland,</hi> or to the Parliament of this Kingdom, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til ſuch a Parliament is, the Admiralty, and all Maritine Cauſes, are to be ordered and ſettled by the Lord Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, together with the Advice and Conſent of the Twelve, or their majority.</p>
                  <p n="25">25. That His Majeſties Subjects be eaſed of all Rents and Encreaſe of Rents, raiſed by the Commiſſion for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective Titles in the Lord of <hi>Stafford</hi>'s Government. This to be by Act of Parliament.</p>
                  <p n="26">26. That by Act to be paſs'd in the next Parliament, all Intereſt Money, not ſatisfied ſince the 23<hi>d.</hi> of <hi>October,</hi> 1641. until the perfection of theſe <hi>Articles,</hi> ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſed and forgiven, and that for 3 Years enſuing 5 <hi>per Cent.</hi> ſhall be taken only for Intereſt.</p>
                  <p n="27">27. The aforemention Twelve, immediately after the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of theſe <hi>Articles,</hi> are to be impower'd by the Lord Lieutenant, and the Twelve, or their majority to lay Taxes by Exciſe, or otherwiſe for Payment of the Army and Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſons
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:57844:50"/>
untill there ſhall be a ſettlement in <hi>Parliament.</hi> The Commiſſioners of the Taxes are to conſiſt both of <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi> and <hi>Roman Catholicks.</hi> The Twelve, or their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jority, have likewiſe power to levy all Arrears of Taxes, impoſed by the Confederate <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> and yet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paid, and to call all Receivers. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to Account, either by themſelves, or Commiſſioners. They ſhall alſo have power to Let and Improve the Eſtates of all ſuch as ſhall not ſubmit to this Peace, and the Revenues thereof are to be converted by the Lord Lieutenant, towards the uſe of the Army till ſettled by Parliament. They are likewiſe Empower'd, or the Majority of them, to lay up Arms and Ammunition in Magazines, and for entertaining as many Frigats as ſhall be thought Neceſſary. They may moreover impriſon all that reſiſt this their Power, or elſe diſtrain their Goods. They are alſo to cauſe Books to be made of their paid Impreſts, and to deliver <hi>Duplicates</hi> of them to the Lord Lieutenant. Their Number is to be ſupply'd in caſe either of Death or Diſability of any, by the choice and direction of the reſt.</p>
                  <p n="28">28. That the Lord Lieutenant, together with the Twelve, or the majority, ſhall nominate all Juſtices of the Peace, <hi>Oyer</hi> and <hi>Terminer,</hi> &amp;c. to continue during Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, but whoſe power muſt not extend to before the 1<hi>ſt.</hi> of <hi>May</hi> laſt paſt, nor to determine <hi>Civil Cauſes</hi> exceeding 10<hi>l.</hi> Their Power likewiſe is not to extend to Examine any Injuries done, contrary to the Articles of Ceſſation, by and with the <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> Party, ſince <hi>May</hi> laſt; but thoſe matters are to be determin'd by the indifferent Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that are to be Nam'd by the Lord Lieutenant and the Twelve, or their majority: The Juſtices, Judges, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſhall take an Oath to Execute their Offices faithfully.</p>
                  <p n="29">29. All <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> Governours of Cities, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to continue till removed by <hi>Parliament,</hi> and to be ſubject to ſuch as the Lord Lieutenant and the Twelve, or their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ority, ſhall nominate, or ſet over them.</p>
                  <p n="30">
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:57844:50"/>30. All Cuſtoms and Tenths of Prizes ſhall be paid into His Majeſties Receipts, and to the Perſons appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Lord Leiutenant, and the Twelve, or their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jority; and in caſe any Perſon has a Right to any of theſe Offices, and whereunto he may not be admitted till Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement in <hi>Parliament,</hi> then is he to have a Penſion till he is reſtor'd.</p>
                  <p n="31">31. As for His Majeſties Rents due at <hi>Eaſter</hi> next, and from thenceforth to grow due, he will not require them till a full ſettlement in <hi>Parliament</hi> be firſt made.</p>
                  <p n="32">32. The Judges power, appointed as aforeſaid, ſhall commence on the 1<hi>ſt.</hi> of <hi>May</hi> laſt paſt, and continue to the firſt day of the next <hi>Parliament.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="33">33. That ſeveral Courts of Judicature ſhall be Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſh'd in this Kingdom, and their Officers nominated by the Lord Lieutenant, and the Twelve, or their majority.</p>
                  <p n="34">34. The <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> Regular Clergy, not to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb'd in their Poſſeſſions, or Penſions, until a Settlement by <hi>Parliament.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="35">35. That as to all other Demands of the ſaid <hi>Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks,</hi> they be refer'd to His Majeſties Gracious Favour, and further Conceſſions.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Sign'd and Witneſſed by the Lord Leiutenant, in His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Name, and by Sir</hi> Richard Blake, <hi>Chair-man of the General Aſſembly of the</hi> Roman Catholicks, <hi>by their Order and Unanimous Conſent,</hi>
                     </signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>the 17th. <hi>of</hi> Jan. 1648. <hi>and in the</hi> 24th. <hi>Year of King</hi> Charles I's <hi>Reign.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
